<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L0053">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt><title>Anything for a change: TEI edition</title><author>Brooks, Shirley</author><respStmt><resp>TEI conversion</resp><name>Lou Burnard</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<publicationStmt><distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor><idno type="LAE">L0053</idno><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which is believed to be in the public domain. You may copy, modify, distribute and perform this work freely. </licence></availability></publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl type="origin" n="4.8"><author>Brooks, Shirley</author><title type="main" n="anythingforachange">Anything for a Change</title><title type="sub">A Petite Comedy in one
       Act</title><extent>21 pp (UM copy: 234 - 255)<measure type="pp" quantity="37"/>
  <measure type="spCount" quantity="381"/>
  <measure type="spvCount" quantity="1"/>
  <measure type="txWords" quantity="7127"/>
  <measure type="spWords" quantity="6462"/>
  <measure type="stWords" quantity="665"/>
  </extent>
      <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 4, No. 0053</title><idno type="nic">N00527</idno></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015048540333&amp;seq=234 ">UM from
       HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol04/L0053/L0053-um.pdf"/></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="TEI"><ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/L0053.html">TEI</ref></bibl><listEvent>
      <event type="firstPerf" when="1848-06-07" source="textNic" where="Lyceum">
       <desc>Premiered at Royal Lyceum Theatre 7 June 1848</desc>
      </event>
     </listEvent></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc><!--S 1 Comedy F. FARCE--><textClass><catRef target="#sizeS"/><catRef target="#act1"/><catRef target="nic:F."/><keywords><term>FARCE</term></keywords></textClass><particDesc><listPerson>
<person xml:id="L0053_M1">
<persName type="role">Mr. Paul Honeyball </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="119">Honey.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0053_M2">
<persName type="role">Mr. Swoppington </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="124">Swop.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Swap.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0053_M3">
<persName type="role">Mr. Jeremy Census </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="10">Census.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0053_F4">
<persName type="role">Mrs. Honeyball </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="34">Mrs. H.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0053_F5">
<persName type="role">Margaret </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="65">Marg.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0053_F6">
<persName type="role">Eliza </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="27">Eliza.</persName>
</person>

</listPerson></particDesc></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change when="2026-01-11">Standardize header components</change><change when="2026-01-10">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change><change when="2025-11-02">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change>
<change when="2025-09-11">Hand edited @who</change>
<change when="2025-09-07">Metadata updated from new catalogue</change>
<change when="2024-10-03">Header enriched</change>
<change when="2023-09-20">Checked against UM; changed page breaks (old ones are
ed=x)</change>
<change when="2023-05-19">Header confected</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><pb n="1"/>
<front>
<titlePage><titlePart type="main">Anything for a change</titlePart><titlePart type="sub">A petite comedy in one act</titlePart><byline>By <docAuthor>Shirley Brooks.</docAuthor>Author of <title>The Daughter
of the Stars</title>; <title>The Creole</title>; <title>The Guardian
Angel</title>, &amp;c., &amp;c.</byline><docImprint>THOMAS HAILES LACY, 89, STRAND, LONDON.</docImprint></titlePage>
<pb n="2"/>
<performance>
<head>Anything for a change</head>
<p>First produced at the Royal Lyceum Theatre, on Wednesday, June, 7th,
1848.</p>

<castList>
<head>Characters</head>
<castItem><role gender="M">Mr. Paul Honeyball </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Harley.
</actor></castItem>

<castItem><role gender="M">Mr. Swoppington </role><actor sex="M">Mr. C.
Mathews. </actor></castItem>

<castItem><role gender="M">Mr. Jeremy Census </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Honner
</actor></castItem>

<castItem><role gender="F">Mrs. Honeyball </role><actor sex="F">Mrs. Leigh
Murray. </actor></castItem>

<castItem><role gender="F">Margaret </role><actor sex="F">Miss K. Fitzwilliam.
</actor></castItem>

<castItem><role gender="F">Eliza </role><actor sex="F">Miss Marshall.
</actor></castItem>

</castList>
</performance>
<set>
<p>The Scene is laid in “Bee-hive Lodge,” Mr. Honeyball's Residence. The time
occupied is one morning. COSTUMES OF THE DAY. Time in Representation, Fifty-one
Minutes.</p>
</set>
<pb n="3"/>
</front>
<body>
<head>ANYTHING FOR A CHANGE.</head>
<div type="scene">

<stage type="setting">SCENE — An Apartment in “Bee-Hive Lodge”—The window looks
upon a garden. —Doors R. and L.—Pianoforte R.H.—Large couch, tables, chairs,
&amp;c.</stage>
<stage>Enter Eliza, L.H.</stage>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>I wonder whether master and his friend did come last night, after all! They
were to leave London by the ten o'clock train, and to arrive here at four in the
morning. And the door was to be left on the latch, and the double-bedded room
was to be got ready, so Missis might not be disturbed by her husband's return.
There never was such a man—so considerate, and so kind to Missis and the poor
servants! <stage>(goes to door R.)</stage> Yes, they must be there— how somebody
snores! <stage>(comes back.)</stage> I hope it's not Miss Margaret's intended. I
couldn't abide a snoring husband. Ah! here is Missis and Miss Margaret. </p>
<stage>(pretends to be dusting.)</stage>
<stage>Enter Mrs. Honeyball and Margaret, L.H.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Never mind the room, just now, Eliza, but go and see about breakfast for the
gentlemen—they will be getting up soon, I suppose.</p>
<stage> Exit Eliza, D.L.H.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>If Mr. Swoppington had any gallantry, Kate, he would have been up long ago.
Considering that he has never seen me, I think his persevering sleep rather a
bad compliment.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>You mean, Miss Margaret, that you are in a violent hurry to see him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Well, you'll allow that the wish is natural, won't you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Oh! certainly; though, as you have agreed to marry him, his personal
appearance is of no particular consequence, you know.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>I know no such thing, then; and though I have agreed to marry him, and if he
had been my brother's friend for twenty   thousand years, instead of twenty, I
won't have him, if I don't like him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Oh! nonsense. As he has proposed for you on the <pb n="4"/> strength of the
character Paul gave you, of course you can't shew less confidence in your
brother.</p>

</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>I wish Paul would mind his own business, and not go running about finding
husbands for me. This is the ninth he has offered me, within two months.
However, <stage>(laughing)</stage> I know he means it kindly, so I won't
complain. But, Kate, it's perfectly ridiculous <stage>(looking at door
R.H.)</stage> for two men to go on sleeping like this!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<stage> (laughing)</stage>
<p>Keeping a young lady waiting for her intended.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>I wonder what he is like?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Paul says he is very good looking.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and illustrates his notion of beauty, by adding that they resemble one
another. Now, if Mr. Swoppington is such a guy as Paul—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Come, come, I won't hear Paul abused! He may not be strictly handsome—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>No, he is not.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>But he is a very good sort of husband!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Yes, but he snores; I can hear him at this distance.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Perhaps, now, it is Mr. Swoppington!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>No, don't say that, the thing's impossible! But I won't bear this any longer.
Will you knock at the door, and make them   get up?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Not I; let them sleep, poor things!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Shall they? Not if I know it! <stage>(goes to the pianoforte— makes a long
run over the keys)</stage> Do you think they heard that? Stop, I'll play them
something that would wake the Seven Sleepers! <stage>(plays very loud indeed -
as she concludes, the door, R.H., opens, and Honeyball enters, and closes the
door after him.</stage> My dear Paul!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>My dear Kate! <stage>(kisses her)</stage> And how are you? I am so happy to
see you! The four weeks and three days I have been away, have really seemed
quite a month—they have, upon my honour! Margaret, dear, how d'ye do?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Oh, very well, Paul! but where's—where's—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Exactly—out with it, Meg!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Where's my—where's Mr. Swoppington?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Swoppington is at present in bed, where I beg you will allow him to
remain, inasmuch as he has had only two hours sleep, poor fellow!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Ah! he has been restless. He has been thinking of me, of course, and that
kept him awake.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>To use a strong expression—not exactly. For though love, and curiosity, and
such like follies, may disturb one's repose, they don't make one turn other
people out of bed, <pb n="5"/> quarrel for the softest pillow, and otherwise
discompose other people's dormitory arrangements.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>What do you mean?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>   I mean my valued friend, Swoppington—now, I am happy to say, asleep—has
one fault—exactly one!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Why, you wrote us word that he was faultless!</p>

</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Because he had not then rendered me sleepless. But as last night he would not
allow me to close my eyes, they were naturally open to his failing.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>And pray what is it?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Simply this:—He is never satisfied with anything of his own, but always wants
everything that belongs to other people.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Pleasant!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Remarkably! The failing, if indulged in too much, might bring it's possessor
under the unfavourable notice of a dozen of his countrymen. But Swoppington does
not go to such extremes. He only asks for everything he sees, and despises it
from the moment it is his. I hope your married life will be happy,
notwithstanding—very happy!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>The prospect is not inviting.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Yes; for though he spoiled my night's rest—although he insisted upon it, that
I had the best of the two beds, and when we had changed, he grew tired of his,
and made me change back again. Although, when the bed question was settled, he
opened a debate upon the pillows; contending, first, that his was too hard, and
afterwards, that its substitute was too soft; he would have the cloak I threw
over my feet, instead of his own railway wrapper, and then found that the cloak
was not warm enough, and that he   wanted his wrapper again. In spite of all
this, I am bound to recommend him as a husband, seeing that he is well off,
good-natured, intelligent, and, in short, almost as desirable a partner
as—myself.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<stage> (laughing)</stage>
<p>A sad anti-climax, Paul, dear!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Madam, or rather Mrs. Honeyball, you don't appreciate the wonderful good
fortune which gave you such a man as myself. Margaret, you will, I hope, be more
grateful for fewer advantages.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>But, Paul, it seems to me that this young gentleman's changeable nature may
induce him to think that a girl who has accepted him, is no longer worth his
attention, and poor Margaret Honeyball may share the affecting fate of the beds
and pillows.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I think it extremely probable.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>You do?</p>
</sp>
<pb n="6"/>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Indeed, I may say, I think it certain.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Then why did you bring him here?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>To marry you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>And now you think he will refuse.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I think nothing of the kind.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>I wish you would explain yourself.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage> (triumphantly)</stage>
<p>See, now, what it is to have a man of intellect at the head of a
household.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<stage> (laughing)</stage>
<p>But give us a proof that our household is so favoured.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Envenomed sarcasm! never mind, young woman, listen —we must plot.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>   Plot?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I said “plot,” and if it will be any satisfaction to you, I will say it
again.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<stage> (poutingly)</stage>
<p>As for me, I can only say, that if I cannot have a husband without plotting
to gain one, I'll die an old maid.</p>
<pb ed="x" n="6"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Don't use such horrible expressions.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Indeed, I don't know what you are always fidgetting about my marriage
for.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Peg Honeyball, hearken! You are twenty years of age —Mr. Swoppington is an
excellent young man, with a trifling, but ludicrous failing. If you like to give
him up, say so, and he shall go back to town by the mid-day train.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>No, no! that would be inhospitable—and—well, what is it you propose?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Ha! come to your senses, eh? Exactly. Now I'll tell you Swoppington is my
very old friend—good. I went to town, as you know, on our election petition, and
one evening, not exactly knowing what to do with myself—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>And not caring enough for your wife, to sit down and write her a letter—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>My love—the post had gone out, so I looked in at a Casino.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>What's that?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Oh, one of those places which the “early closing” agitation has induced
Philanthropists to open for the moral improvement   of young Holborn. There I
met Swoppington, improving his morals <stage>(aside)</stage> and his Mazourka
polka. <stage>(aloud)</stage> We supped together, and I took occasion to tell
him that you were being courted by our neighbour Jeremy Census, Assistant
Registrar of births, marriages, and deaths. He caught fire at the idea,
threatened to add Jeremy's name to his list of deaths, if he did not discontinue
his addresses—and proposed for you himself.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="7"/>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Which he would not have done, but for having a rival.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Perhaps—and when he loves you on his own account he will be glad that I
invented the story. See what it is to have a man of intellect for a brother!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>And he insisted on accompanying you here?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>He would hear of no delay—he would have taken an express engine, instead of
awaiting the regular train, if I had allowed it—and here he is.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Asleep. But, at all events, he is an original.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I hear him getting up—<stage>(going to door)</stage> hush—yes!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>At last—now you can present him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Not a bit—you forget my plot.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Explain it, then, and make haste.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Now you two go into the garden, and I will come to you. I don't want him to
see you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Not see us?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>No, not yet! Now go—and trust to me, a man of intellect. Do you hear?
Away!</p>
<stage>Exeunt, hastily, Margaret and Mrs. Honeyball, through C.</stage>
<stage>Enter Swoppington, R.H.D.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage>(L.H.)</stage>
<p>   Up at last, Swoppington! I think you have had a pretty good spell, eh?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Come—I like that—I do, upon my honour. You who <pb ed="x" n="7"/> made one
long splendid sleep, while I did nothing but toss about, and twist about like a
porpoise with something on his mind. I'd give anything to sleep like you. You
too, who had the best bed, and the softest, and the warmest—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Well, you chose your bed.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I know I did, and I chose wrong, as I always do in everything. Come what
will, I am always worse off than anybody else. But where are the ladies?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Gone out, hours ago—gone for a walk in the woods. Why, you don't suppose we
keep London hours here and feel that if we're obliged to breakfast at noon, we
have been called up in the middle of the night! <stage>(takes out his
watch)</stage> It's nearly—it's nearly—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (runs to him)</stage>
<p>I say! where did you get that watch?—what a nice watch—a capital watch! where
did you get it?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Get it? I got it at a watchmaker's—Dent's, I believe.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I don't believe you did. It's a beauty—a love—the captain of watches—does it
go well?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Loses rather.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="8"/>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Now, that's just what I like, too; I like a watch that loses —one don't seem
to get old so fast. Swop with me for mine, will you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>No! I rather like this—I prefer keeping it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Well, lend it me, then, for a bit; come, I'll lend you anything of mine you
like. I'll lend you my umbrella.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I've got half-a-dozen umbrellas.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>How you must steal! but I'll have a watch like that, in spite of you, see if
I don't. I'll buy one, instead of this beast of a thing. <stage>(takes out
his)</stage> Here's a regular old warming-pan for you, isn't it?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>No, a devilish fine repeater!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I hate a repeater—who wants to carry a churchful of chimes in his waistcoat?
I wish you'd swop. <stage>(Honeyball turns away, pettishly.)</stage> By
Jupiter!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>What about him?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>What a prime shooting-jacket that is! A capital fit, and a good colour. Is it
London-made? Here, let me try it on for a minute—<stage>(pulling off his
own)</stage> do, there's a good fellow! </p>
<stage>(pulls at it.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Will you let my coat alone, you'll have the buttons off! <stage>(gets
away)</stage> I'll give it you one of these days—<stage>(aside)</stage> when
it's worn out.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>No, will you though?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Yes! And now I'll give you something else. <stage>(goes to bell)</stage>
We'll have breakfast. </p>
<stage>(rings bell, L.H.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>But the ladies—won't they sit down with us?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>No, not they—they breakfasted early. </p>
<stage>(sits at table, L.H.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>And very right, too—I wish I had breakfasted early.   What foolery it is to
breakfast at such an hour as this! </p>
<stage>(sits on chair near piano.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Well, you know, this is liberty hall—you are not obliged to eat anything—you
can wait till dinner, if you like—I sha'n't.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>No, no! if you eat, I'll eat, I'll do as you do. </p>
<stage>(sits at table, R.H.)</stage>
<pb ed="x" n="8"/>
<stage>Enter Eliza, with breakfast, L.H.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>That's right, Eliza, give us breakfast!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<stage> (laying cloth)</stage>
<p>You'll take coffee, sir?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and tea to follow.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>What a nice little girl—deuced pretty—and handy, and quiet, just what a
servant ought to be! Such a girl's a treasure in a house. I'll engage her
myself—I shall want servants. <pb n="8"/>I say, Eliza, what wages does he give
you? I'll give you twice as much— is it a bargain?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Sir! </p>
<stage>(gets R. of Swoppington.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Not a bit of it—not a bit of it! I mean to keep Eliza— she knows our ways,
and wo don't want to part with her.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes, you let her come to me, and I'll tell you what I'll do for you; I
know such a nice black woman, called Celia—she's just come from Trinidad, to
some friends of mine at Bayswater— I'll engage her for you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>A black woman?—get out!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>He say's he'll double my wages—he knows a good servant, when he sees one,
that's certain.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>How nicely she's laid that table now—everything in its place—very well done,
Eliza!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Now I'll trouble you not to meddle with my servants.   Eliza, go down stairs
directly!</p>
<stage> Exit Eliza, L.H.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I will have that girl, I'm determined, or, at least, I'll have one just like
her. I say, has she any sisters?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Will you have any breakfast? </p>
<stage>(takes a chair, and is about to sit.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (getting before him, and into his place.)</stage>
<p>I say, let me sit there!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage> (laughing)</stage>
<p>Sit where you like; now, what shall I help you to?—here's some cold fowl—what
part will you have?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Anything—I don't care what.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I hate a man who don't care what he eats</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Well, then, there, where your fork is.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>This bit?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes—that!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>There's the liver wing, then. <stage>(helps him)</stage> I'll take the
gizzard.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You will? Take it—I can't eat anything!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Why not?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>My dear fellow, the gizzard wing is just the part I like; but take it—take
it!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Why, I only took it out of courtesy. There, let me hand it to you! </p>
<stage>(hands it to him.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>No, no! If you don't want it—keep it. You like the liver wing, I suppose?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Yes, I'm very fond of the liver wing!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>So am I—I'm wildly fond of it! </p>
<stage>(change again.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>   Then you've got it. <stage>(aside)</stage> Poor Margaret will have some
trouble with this whimsical devil. I wonder he don't begin to talk about her. We
must lead the conversation that way.</p>
<pb ed="x" n="9"/>
</sp>
<pb n="10"/>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>This fowl's capital!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I'm glad you like it! I say, Swoppington, our poor neighbour, Jeremy Census,
he'll almost go mad when he finds that you are going to marry <hi>her</hi>.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (with his mouth full)</stage>
<stage><hi>Her!</hi> who's her?</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>My sister!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Ah! Then he was very fond of her, eh? </p>
<stage>(indifferently.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Fond? Mad about her!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (eagerly)</stage>
<p>My dear Paul, how enchanted I am that you give my proposal the preference.
Fancy, now, that an angel, like Miss Honeyball, should live to be called Mrs.
Jeremy Census—bah! <stage>(changing his tone)</stage> I don't know that that's
the worst of it, though. Census isn't a bad name—it's a very good name—anyhow,
it's a much better name than Swoppington. Swoppington's a horrid name—just such
a name as they stick into farces. I wish my name was Jeremy Census!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I think you are a great fool, my dear friend! What nonsense it is, that you
always prefer everything that is not your own, to everything that is. For my
part, it's exactly the other way with me. I prefer everything I have; for
instance, my wife, now— I prefer Kate Honeyball to any other wife in the
world.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>How very odd that seems to me, now! that liking one's   own wife better than
another man's. I can't understand it, upon my word!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I hope, however, that when you are married to my sister, you will.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Of course I shall. I say—tell me, is she pretty?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>My sister?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>No, your wife! I don't know her, you know. I wish you would present me—I'm
dying to see her.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>And my sister?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Of course! And your wife—she makes you happy, I suppose?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I have nothing to complain of. </p>
<stage>(both rise.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Lucky fellow! I say, go and find her—I must know her.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>And my sister?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Of course! Now do go—get out! </p>
<stage>(pushes him.)</stage>
<stage> Exit Honeyball, C.D.</stage>
<p> —What a fortunate fellow that is! To marry such a woman as that—a woman with
all the virtues and accomplishments in the world—a woman of mind—a domestic
woman—a woman who loves him—a woman who cares for nobody else. I'm certain
that's her character. And what's he, a humguffin like that, that he should gain
such a wife? What can she see in him? In the first place, he's devilish ugly.
Ugly, though? I don't know. I wish I had his features—I do, upon my word. His
hair is <pb n="11"/>better hair than my hair. His nose is a better nose than my
nose. Why the deuce couldn't I have a nose like his? </p>
<stage>(goes to the glass, R.H.)</stage>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Eliza, L.H.</stage>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Sir, sir, it will do!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>   Yes, it will do; but—Ah! Eliza, is that you?</p>
<pb ed="x" n="10"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Double my present wages—that will do, sir! They give me twelve pounds a year,
but the place is dreadful slavery—so I'll come to you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Dreadful slavery, is it? </p>
<stage>(sits at piano, R.H.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir! So for twenty-four pounds a year, I'll go to London.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You will, will you—directly, eh?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir, directly.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>There's no difficulty in the matter, then?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>No, sir, no difficulty at all. I shall be delighted to come.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Oh, very well, Eliza! I'll tell you what—if you like to come to me for half
the wages you get here—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Half what I get here? What! six pounds a year less?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Exactly! <stage>(aside)</stage> What is that Honeyball about?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Sir, you ought to be ashamed of your self, and it isn't acting like a
gentleman! </p>
<stage>(crying.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>What isn't?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Trying to allure away a poor servant, who is attached to her employers.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You said the place was slavery.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Well, and if I did, I'd sooner wash the stairs with cold water every morning,
and never have a Sunday out, than go to another place for half my wages; and
I'll take and tell the ladies   that you have been trying to seduce me away;
<stage>(crosses and looks off C.D.)</stage> and here they are!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Ah! and I have got this beast of a coat on! I must not risk a first
impression in this thing. I'll try and find one of Honeyball's. Recollect,
Eliza, six pounds a year, and you're mine!</p>
<stage> Exit R.H.D.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Am I?—not if I know it! A nice sort of match for Miss Margaret! A master who
gives short wages can't be a good husband!</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Mrs. Honeyball, Margaret, and Honeyball, C.D.—The Ladies have
altered their dresses; Mrs. Honeyball is dressed as a young lady, and Margaret,
as Mrs. Honeyball, appears with a bunch of keys.</stage>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Upon my word, Paul, I don't think that this trick is justifiable.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="12"/>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Necessity, Kate, necessity!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>I like it! I shall be able to judge of the character of my admirer, without
having to listen to any of his compliments and protestations.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I don't know that! From his whimsical habits, I think that it is to you they
will be addressed.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<stage> (to herself)</stage>
<p>Six pounds!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Where's Eliza? Ah, Eliza!—here!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Eliza! listen to me—to me, your master, with the most profound attention.
Eliza, for this day only, and by particular desire, my wife is my sister, and my
sister my wife.</p>
<pb ed="x" n="11"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>What will they say to that at Doctor's Commons, sir?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha! Understand. girl, that it is for a joke.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>A joke? Ah, I see, sir!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Now don't forget, you are to call my sister my wife.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>   Yes, sir; I am to call your sister my wife.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Don't be a fool! Call Miss Margaret, Mrs. Honeyball.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>And call Mrs. Honeyball, Miss Margaret.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Do you understand the joke?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>No, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>What an idiot you are! Don't you see?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>I am to call you Miss Margaret.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Go to the—go away—go to the devil!—go into the coalhole—shut yourself up,
hide yourself, no matter where; but don't let me see you, or—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Oh, thank you, sir! <stage>(aside)</stage> I'll go and spend the day with my
cousin!</p>
<stage> Exit D.L.H.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>And, now, don't let us make any blunders. You, Margaret, you must look
calmly, and saucily happy, as a married woman, blessed with all she desires in a
husband, should look; and you, Kate, you must keep your eyes down, and be shy,
and monosyllabic, as you pretended to be when I was courting you. Look out, here
he comes!</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Swoppington, he remains near door, R.H.</stage>

<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Come in, my boy—here we are! The ladies have just returned from their walk.
Now let me present you. <stage>(Swoppington comes down)</stage> Mr. Swoppington,
Mrs. Honeyball! </p>
<stage>(presents him to Margaret.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Nice! <stage>(aside)</stage> Nice, very nice! </p>
<stage>(bows.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Swoppington, my sister, Miss Meg, or shall I say   Miss Margaret
Honeyball? </p>
<stage>(presents him to Mrs. Honeyball.)</stage>
</sp>
<pb n="13"/>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Very nice, also! <stage>(aside)</stage> Very nice; but he has got the best of
it, as usual! <stage>(bows to them, but especially to Mrs. Honeyball)</stage> I
can only shew my gratitude to my old friend, Honeyball, for such an
introduction, by venturing to cultivate so delightful an acquaintance as
earnestly as possible. </p>
<stage>(they curtsey; he bows slightly to Mrs. Honeyball, and takes Margaret's
hand, which he detains—they exchange looks.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage> (again taking Mrs. Honeyball's hand, and presenting her to
Swoppington)</stage>
<p>Yes, my dear friend, this is my sister! My sister Margaret, who is, as she
ought to be, delighted, enchanted, to make your acquaintance.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (distantly)</stage>
<p>Miss Honeyball, I really—<stage>(goes over to Margaret)</stage> And I must
certainly quarrel with my friend, for not having brought me sooner into the
bosom of his family. When a man is happy enough to secure a wife with so many
attractions, he—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage> (L.C., aside)</stage>
<p>Go on, young gentleman, go on. My sister was saying—</p>
<pb ed="x" n="12"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I say, Madam, when a man is attended by such fortune, when, with so amiable a
sister, and so charming a wife—</p>
<stage>(Honey takes his arm.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Well, sir, you will not long have reason to envy the happiness of your
friend.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>There's a voice—musical as Alboni's; and there's an eye—talk of eyes after
those! <stage>(aloud)</stage> Why not, Madam?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>For really I believe Miss Honeyball, whom I consider a most charming young
person, has every quality which—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>No doubt, Madam. </p>
<stage>(Honey takes his arm again.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Well, what do you think of my sister?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>   Eh? <stage>(without looking at Mrs. Honeyball)</stage> Charming!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Come, <stage>(taking Margaret's arm in his)</stage> my dear, come, we'll
leave these young folks to become better acquainted. <stage>(going)</stage>
You'll excuse me and my wife! </p>
<stage>(markedly to Margaret.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You are not going to leave us?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>With your intended.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>He's hooked, Peg—he's hooked!</p>
<stage> Exit Honeyball and Margaret, C.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>They've left me alone with the other—I don't know what to say to her; yes I
do! I'll tell her that I don't much think I shall marry her—that will help on
the conversation.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>I declare he won't even look at me. That's <pb n="14"/>not very complimentary
to one's self esteem. However, I must do as Paul wishes me.
<stage>(aloud)</stage> Sir—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Madam! <stage>(aside)</stage> There's a squeaky voice after the other.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>He don't help one much. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Sir, my brother informs me
that—that—you have proposed for my hand—you wish to become my husband.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Miss Honeyball. <stage>(aside)</stage> It will be some time first, I can tell
you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<stage> (laughs aside—aloud)</stage>
<p>We are alone, sir, as you see, so that if you have anything to say to me—as I
suppose you have—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>I had intended to say something remarkably civil, but I'll be hanged if I
haven't forgotten what it was. If her sister-in-law were here, now, I could talk
like an angel. Ah! I know. <stage>(aloud)</stage> What a pretty woman Mrs.
Honeyball is!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>   You think so?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I do indeed.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Yes, but she is of a very uncertain disposition.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>An uncertain disposition has a certain charm for me. <stage>(aside)</stage>
But this won't do—I must get on better than this. <stage>(aloud)</stage>
However, we are not here to talk about Mrs. Honeyball <stage>(sees
pianoforte)</stage> are we? Ah! I see Mrs. Honeyball is musical—and—to judge by
the compositions I see, a musician of no ordinary calibre.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>She sings; so do I a little—shall I sing you something? </p>
<stage>(goes to instrument)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You?—oh, I shall be delighted, of course!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<stage> (smiling)</stage>
<p>He won't pay me the slightest attention—I'll revenge myself by making him
listen. <stage>(aloud)</stage> This is a little song written by a neighbouring
gentleman.</p>
<pb ed="x" n="13"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>A bumpkin bard—the poet of the County Journal, I suppose—a treat, no doubt.
Oh, Lord!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<stage> (taking her seat)</stage>
<p>I think you will like it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>I'm sure I sha'n't. <stage>(aloud)</stage> No doubt. Will you pardon me, if I
sit down here—I always like music better when I'm sitting.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>By all means.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (taking the arm chair)</stage>
<p>Now to make one's fate as light as the melancholy circumstances of the case
will allow. I say, what a nice arm chair this is, I'll make Honeyball give me
this chair, see if I don't. <stage>(she runs over the keys)</stage> Ah, the
infliction! </p>
<stage>(she sings the first verse of the following song, and while she is
singing - </stage>
</sp>
<pb n="15"/>
<stage>Margaret enters, C.D.</stage>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>   He's gone to sleep. Now, that <hi>is</hi> a shame, for the air is
remarkably pretty.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Is that the way you make conquests? My dear Kate, I don't mind trusting my
lovers with you, you don't betray one's confidence.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Do you know, Margaret, I think he's half an idiot. I've done all I can—I give
him up. You may sing the rest of the song, and try if you can do better.</p>
<stage> Exit C., to L.</stage>
</sp>

<spGrp>
<head>SONG, Margaret - "LOVE KNOWS NO SLEEP."</head>
<stage>Words by Shirley Brooks, Music by Edward Fitzwilliam. -
Published.</stage>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<lg>
<l>Love knows no sleep!—the silent Hours </l>
<l>   That fold his roses, light his star, </l>
<l>And chain, with links of dew-bright flowers, </l>
<l>   The steeds that roll his golden car. </l>
<l>When parted lovers distant lie </l>
<l>   In midnight slumbers pure and deep, </l>
<l>Who guides the dream, who wakes the sigh, </l>
<l>   But watchful Love?—Love knows no sleep! </l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Love knows no sleep!—his pulses play </l>
<l>   When wilder passions sink to rest, </l>
<l>As, when the storm has passed away, </l>
<l>   The sea-bird clings to Ocean's breast. </l>
<l>When wearied Hopes with day expire, </l>
<l>   When throbs not Joy, nor Sorrows weep, </l>
<l>Love guards unquench'd his altar-fire, </l>
<l>   A beacon true—Love knows no sleep!</l>
</lg>
</sp>
</spGrp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Sleeps still! What a talent he has for sleeping. I'll   change the tune.</p>
<stage>(Plays a lively tune very loud—he wakes, sees her, and drops on his knees
on her R.)</stage>
<pb ed="x" n="14"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Eh? What! a transformation?—a fairy tale?—one of Ovid's metamorphoses?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>No, it's only me, sir! I have ventured to take the place of my poor sister,
whose voice sent you to sleep.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Sleep? good gracious, no! Don't suppose so for a moment. I was only nodding.
But don't let me interrupt you, pray continue!</p>
</sp>
<stage>(SONG.—Margaret. — Any Air contrasting, by its liveliness, with the
foregoing song — through and after the song, Swoppington applauds her.)</stage>
<pb n="16"/>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Heyday! how enthusiastic you are all on a sudden; in poor Margaret's presence
you were cold and melancholy.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Oh! yes—no—the fact is—fatigue—a long journey, but in <hi>your</hi> presence,
madam, you see how different I am.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>Now for it! <stage>(to him)</stage> Sir!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Your presence instantly dispels all my melancholy, and renders me quite
another being!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>It can hardly be necessary for me to remind you, sir, that you are addressing
a wife—the wife of your friend.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I know it, Madam, I know it. <stage>(aside)</stage> Confound it!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>That you have made urgent proposals for the hand of a young lady—that you
have been accepted—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>True, Madam, true. <stage>(aside)</stage> And it's very disagreeable.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>And really, I must also inform you that the young lady in question is a
paragon of virtue.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Don't chill me with paragons of virtue; for my part, I like a woman with a
few faults—I may say, full of faults.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>   Indeed! If Margaret Honeyball fail to enchant you, I don't know what kind
of person would suit you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I could tell you, if I dared; but I must not. I have seen such a woman; but
Paul Honeyball has put perfect happiness out of my power.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Sir, if you persevere in language of this sort—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Forgive me, I mean no offence—but—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>I must leave you. <stage>(aside)</stage> I know I shall die with
laughing!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Nay, do not go!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>I'll try to hear him out.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>The struggle is idle! I must speak! I know I shall get into an awful scrape;
but there's no help for it! Oh, Madam, that you should have done this!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Done what?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>That you should have gone and married Honeyball!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Well, sir?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>No, Madam, it is not well!—read Alfred Tennyson—</p>
<l>“Is it well to wish thee happy, </l>
<l>   Having known me, to decline </l>
<l>On a range of lower feeling— </l>
<l>   On a narrower heart than mine?” </l>
<pb ed="x" n="15"/>
<p>—You did not know me then in those days; that, you will say, makes a
difference. But you might have known me—a small voice might have whispered
“Swoppington,” and you might have   waited until you did know me. I waited, you
see, madam <pb n="17"/>—I did not go and marry—I said to myself, there is the
adored, the divine— what's your christian name, Madam?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Kate.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Just so—I said to myself, there is the adored, the divine Kate, waiting for
me. I will treasure up my affections for her; but the divine Kate has not
waited, and I am undone, very much undone.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>But, sir—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>No matter, madam, I forgive you—I will not reproach you—your own heart must
reproach you, to say nothing of your husband, who of course renders your life
one long misery. Don't tell me he does not, because I know he does—I happen to
know he does. But he shall not ill-treat you longer, madam, no, I will protect
you from his ferocity. I have read Alexander Dumas, Madam, Eugene Sue, George
Sand—and I know my course. I will call him out, madam! I am a dead shot! I will
displace him—destroy him—remove him —shoot him, in fact!—you will be a widow—I
will marry you, and we'll go together in a cab to the Norwood Cemetery, and weep
over his grave!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<stage> (laughing)</stage>
<p>Wouldn't it be awkward for me to marry a man who had killed my husband?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Oh! but I'll kill him so gently, he sha'n't feel it; he'll rather like it,
than not.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>There, sir, that will do—a joke is very well—now leave   off, or I shall be
angry.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I have done, Madam; but I beg you distinctly to understand, that if I am
turned out of this house, I shall take you with me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Me?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Yes. Did you ever read Homer, Mrs. Honeyball? If you have, you will remember
that Helen was carried off from Menelaus by Paris. Very good—I'm Paris, you're
Helen, Honeyball is Menelaus, and, off we go.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>But, as I am a party to the matter—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You! Well, that's true, Madam, listen—did you ever have the tooth-ache?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>No, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I'm sorry for that—no—I'm glad of it. I have the toothache sometimes, Madam,
and to cure it, I always carry a large bottle of laudanum; that bottle is now on
my dressing table, in that room. If you don't consent to leave this house, and
to be mine, I'll swallow that bottle, cork, label, and all.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>That is too dreadful to contemplate. I consent.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You do, you do, and you won't retract?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>I never break my word.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="18"/>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>And you will be mine?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>I will.</p>
<stage> Exit D.L.H.</stage>
<pb ed="x" n="16"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You will! <stage>(calling after her)</stage> What you mean by “You will?—She
will! She won't retract—why, what have I done?   My private impression is, that
I'm in a dream, and though it's a very pleasant one, it appears to me to be
leading up to some curious catastrophe. I wish I could wake, just to be quite
sure what I am about. <stage>(dances a few steps)</stage> Here comes Honeyball,
how shall I get out of the scrape? he'll turn me out of his house. </p>
<stage>(dances again.)</stage>
<p>— <stage>Enter Honeyball, C.D.</stage> Well, Honeyball!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I beg your pardon, old fellow, for leaving you to your own devices; but you
know that when the master of a house has been away for a month, and when he's a
man of intellect, to whom the household looks up, there are so many things for
him to do, and see after—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Don't mention it, I've been very happy. <stage>(aside)</stage> He don't seem
to suspect. Helen has not betrayed me to Menelaus.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>I should like to know how my plot gets on—I can't find my wife anywhere.
<stage>(aloud)</stage> I say, Swoppington—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Well, Menelaus, what is it?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Why do you call me Menelaus?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Why shouldn't I?—answer me that!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Because I don't like it—at least, I can't see the—I don't see the fun of it.
I don't, upon my honour.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Well, I know I have no right to call you so—yet—but what were you going to
say?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Why, my sister—you've seen her, and you say nothing on the subject.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>Ah! I must dodge him a little, and see how the   land lies.
<stage>(aloud)</stage> My dear Honeyball, we have been friends for years! When
we were boys, we bit our apples across, and each took a piece. When we were
hobbledehoys, we cut our cigars, and each smoked half. And now that we are men,
we are equally happy to share anything we have—is it not so?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Anything, my boy—anything!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I knew you'd say so. Now, you are going to share your family with me,—you
have but a wife and a sister, and you are going to give one of them to me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I am.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I mean, of course, your sister—your angelic sister. I adore her—in fact, I am
desperately in love with her!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>My dear boy, I am rejoiced! <stage>(changes his looks and <pb n="19"/>his
tone to those of extreme anger)</stage> No, you are not a dear boy, and I'm not
rejoiced at all!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>What's the matter?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Can Kate have been playing the coquette?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I love her—I adore her—and I'll marry her directly!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>A moment, my friend—a moment! Do me the favour to examine your feelings. Are
you sure—perfectly sure—quite certain that it was my sister whom you admire?—you
are so changeable.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I changeable! I never changed my mind in all my life! <pb ed="x" n="17"/>
<stage>(aside)</stage> I wonder if he suspects anything! <stage>(aloud)</stage>
Well, I admit that once or twice I have changed my intentions, but this time I
am   resolute. I love your sister, and I'll marry her—are you satisfied?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Delighted! <stage>(aside)</stage> He can't marry my wife! What a fool I am to
be annoyed at such nonsense! <stage>(aloud)</stage> But you must obtain her
consent, you know.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I have it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>You have it?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Yes, Menelaus.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I tell you not to call me by that name—I don't like it. What—Kate has
consented to marry him! <stage>(suddenly)</stage> I say, Swoppington—tell me,
were you alone with my sister? You were, I suppose?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Didn't you go out and leave us?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Ah! Well, I only want to know, not that it is of much importance; but, you
were perfectly respectful, of course.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Respectful! how should you behave, if you were left alone with a young
lady?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I? ah! that's another matter. Why, you are an engaged couple, certainly, and
you might think—there are trifling ceremonies—you might have thought yourself
justified in asking for a —a—kiss, eh?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Well, I should say there was no very great harm in that, under the
circumstances.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>But I should say there was great harm, under the circumstances, very great
harm.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>What a fuss you make about nothing! and me too—why   you couldn't make more
fuss if I had been kissing your wife!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>My wife?—no, I shouldn't have made half such a fuss!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>What do you say? Well, now, I'll call that the height of hospitality!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Pooh, pooh! what am I saying?—I don't mean <pb n="20"/>that, of course; I
only mean—I mean, that I should not have been surprised if you had admired Mrs.
Honeyball.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Your sister is worth a dozen of her—and to prove that I think so, I'll marry
her directly:</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Never!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>What! not marry her?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Never!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Opposed again. Do you mean to say I shan't marry your sister?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I do!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swap.</speaker>
<p>But I will, I tell you. Oh, Honeyball!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I am resolved.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I who have known and loved her so long!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Eh! what?—why you met her to-day only, for the first time.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You think so. <stage>(aside)</stage> Now for a thumper.
<stage>(aloud)</stage> But the secret can be kept no longer, we are old
lovers.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>What do I hear? distraction!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Yes, we met at Ramsgate, two years ago; we flirted on the Pier, raffled in
the libraries, danced at Tivoli, and sat upon the <pb ed="x" n="18"/>   beach to
look at the bathing machines. I always used to pay for her chairs. We parted—we
are now re-united for ever.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage> (wildly)</stage>
<p>And this is my wife, upon whom I believed I had made the first impression!
Raffled at Ramsgate, and I have married such a woman!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Married his sister?—the man's mad!</p>
<stage>Enter Mrs. Honeyball, C.D.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>Oh, here you are, Paul.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage> (in a loud voice, and seizing her arm)</stage>
<p>Wicked woman!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>What's the matter with you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Woman, prepare for my vengeance! You, Madam, I will drag before that
respectable family, the Ecclesiastical Court— and as for your lover—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>What lover?—tell me, there's a dear!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>You, sir, I will have your life.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You certainly won't; I want it myself—it's the only thing of mine that I
value.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>But, Honeyball. </p>
<stage>(goes up C.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage> (repulsing her)</stage>
<p>Back, Madam, don't Honeyball me!</p>
<stage>Enter Margaret, L.H.D.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Paul!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>I'll go and fetch all the rural police of the district, horse and foot.</p>
<stage> Exit Mr. and Mrs. Honeyball, C to L.</stage>
</sp>
<pb n="21"/>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>What can this anger mean?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I only told him that I insisted on marrying his sister.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Ah! then you will marry her?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Never!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>   Please do, you are bound in honour.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>You desire it? I'll do what I can; but don't you lose sight of me, or I shall
certainly break down.</p>
<stage>Enter Eliza, L.H.D.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>He's here!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Who's here?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Census, he's here; master sent to him to come, and I was to tell you,
miss, who are not m0iss, that missis, who is not missis—no, don't let me make a
mistake—master, who is Miss Margaret—I don't know, but here's Mr. Census.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Mr and Mrs Honeyball, and Census, C. from L.</stage>

<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Then, you swear to me, Kate, by all the oaths in the world, that you never
flirted at Ramsgate, and never sat on the sands to look at the bathing
machines?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F4">
<speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
<p>I swear to you, I was never out of London until you married me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>On consideration, that affidavit is satisfactory. Then it is not you whom
he—</p>
<pb ed="x" n="19"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Hold your tongue.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<stage> (to Margaret)</stage>
<p>Are you sure it is you whom he—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F5">
<speaker>Marg.</speaker>
<p>Hold your tongue.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (going to Census)</stage>
<p>What a nice stick. </p>
<stage>(takes it from him, and pulls the head off.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>There now, sir, you've pulled the head off.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Never mind, I say—I'll buy this of you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>I don't want to sell it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I'll give you my umbrella for it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>I tell you it was a present, and I don't want to part with   it. </p>
<stage>(he goes and puts it into corner.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>A muff! What good glasses these are, just my sight. I never can get my sight,
not even at Dolland's.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>Now, Mr. Honeyball; you sent for me to arrange for a marriage. You must come
to my office, and if you'll give me the names I'll get everything ready. Hollo!
where are they?—I had them, just this moment.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Had what?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>My spectacles.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="22"/>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Eh! where can they be? <stage>(Everybody looks)</stage> I don't see them
anywhere.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>There they are—those are mine, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>I'll give you my umbrella for them.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>Nonsense, sir. </p>
<stage>(snatches them.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Oh, you needn't be in such a hurry, you've nearly pulled my nose off—I don't
like my nose, but it would be inconvenient to have it pulled off.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>Now, Mr. Honeyball!</p>
</sp>
<stage> Honeyball stands by, and tells him what to write. Meantime, Swoppington
goes up and inspects the stick, and takes it up. The head falls off—business of
regaining the stick, then the head - finally Census obtains them.</stage>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>All right!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>Then all you have to do is to sign this paper. Now, Miss Honeyball.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<stage> (jumping up)</stage>
<p>What are you talking about? Miss Honeyball, indeed! <stage>(aside)</stage> No
such luck! <stage>(aloud)</stage> What an old blunderer you are!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M3">
<speaker>Census.</speaker>
<p>Confound you, what do you mean by calling me a   blunderer? Once for all,
does Miss Honeyball mean to sign or not?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>What—again—what? <stage>(Margaret signs)</stage> Am I to believe my eyes? She
goes—she dips—she signs—let's see, “Margaret Honeyball!”—it's she—it's you—it's
he—it's we—it's thou—it's they—she's mine—I'm hers!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M1">
<speaker>Honey.</speaker>
<p>Hallo! he's going it again. Are you satisfied?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Yes, I am perfectly satisfied, for the first time in my life. Satisfied with
what has fallen to my lot, and my dear little wife, here, will confirm me, I
hope, in my good intentions for the future, for I give her due notice, it will
be her fault, and not mine, if I ever wish for a change again.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_F6">
<speaker>Eliza.</speaker>
<p>If you should, sir, I should be happy to come to you— for double my present
wages—and my tea and sugar.</p>
<pb ed="x" n="20"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L0053_M2">
<speaker>Swop.</speaker>
<p>Still, I must say, I hope for the sake of the author of the little plot we
have just unravelled, that it will be the opinion of all present, that for once,
at least, “Anything for a Change” has proved better than no change at all.</p>
</sp>
<stage type="tableau"> Census. Mrs. H. Honey. Swop. Marg. Eliza</stage>
<stage>Curtain.</stage>

</div>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>