<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L1058">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt><title>My Poll and my partner Joe: : TEI edition</title><author>Haines, John Thomas</author><respStmt><resp>TEI conversion</resp><name>Lou Burnard</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
<publicationStmt><distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor><idno type="LAE">L1058</idno><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which is believed to be in the public domain. You may copy, modify, distribute and perform this work freely. </licence></availability></publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl type="origin" n="71.8"><author>Haines, John Thomas</author><title type="main" n="mypollandmypartnerjoe">My Poll and My Partner Joe</title><title type="sub">A Nautical
       Drama in three acts</title><title type="music">The Music Selected and Arranged by Mr.
       Jolly</title><extent>48 pp (UM copy: 268 - 316)<measure type="pp" quantity="46"/>
  <measure type="spCount" quantity="478"/>
  <measure type="spvCount" quantity="18"/>
  <measure type="txWords" quantity="16231"/>
  <measure type="spWords" quantity="12864"/>
  <measure type="stWords" quantity="3367"/>
  </extent>
      <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 71, No. 1058</title><idno type="nic">N01722</idno></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453772&amp;seq=268 ">UM from
       HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol71/L1058/L1058-um.pdf"/></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="TEI"><ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/L1058.html">TEI</ref></bibl><listEvent>
      <event type="firstPerf" when="1835-09" source="text" where="Surrey">
       <desc>Premiered at Royal Surrey Theatre Sept. 1835; Nicoll date 1835-08-31</desc>
      </event>
     </listEvent></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc><!--M 3 DramaMusic M.D. MELODRAMA--><textClass><catRef target="#sizeM"/><catRef target="#act3"/><catRef target="nic:M.D."/><keywords><term>MELODRAMA</term></keywords></textClass><particDesc><listPerson>
<person xml:id="L1058_M1">
<persName type="role">CAPTAIN OAKHEART</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="20">Oak.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M2">
<persName type="role">LIEUTENANT MANLY </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="6">Manly.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M3">
<persName type="role">BEN BOWSE </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="18">Bowse.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M4">
<persName type="role">BLACK BRANDON </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="40">Bran.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="9">Brand.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M5">
<persName type="role">ZINGA </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="15">Zinga.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M6">
<persName type="role">HARRY HALLYARD </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="112">Harry.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="114">Harry</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M7">
<persName type="role">JOE TILLER </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="44">Joe.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M8">
<persName type="role">WATCHFUL WAXEND </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="62">Wax.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M9">
<persName type="role">WILL WALL-IT </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="9">Wall.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M10">
<persName type="role">SAM SNATCHEM </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="8">Snatch.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M11">
<persName type="role">OLD SAM SCULLER </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="37">Scul.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Scull.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_M12">
<persName type="role">JEROME</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="9">Sent.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_F13">
<persName type="role">MARY MAYBUD </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="45">Mary.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="46">Mary</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_F14">
<persName type="role">ABIGAIL HOLDFORTH </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="11">Abig.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_F15">
<persName type="role">ZAMBA </persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1058_F16">
<persName type="role">DAME HALLYARD</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="10">Dame.</persName>
</person>

<person xml:id="L1058_Mul">
<persName type="spkr" n="8">All.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="2">Watermen.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Chorus of Sailors.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Sailors.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Harry &amp;Joe.</persName>
</person>

<person xml:id="L1058_M17">
<persName type="role">[Midshipman]</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="2">Middy.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Seaman.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Sailor.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Mid.</persName>
</person>


<person xml:id="L1058_M18">
<persName type="role">[Jew duffer]</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="2">Jew.</persName>
</person>


</listPerson></particDesc></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change when="2026-01-11">Standardize header components</change><change when="2026-01-10">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change><change when="2025-11-02">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change>
<change when="2025-09-11">Some @who correction by hand</change>
<change when="2025-09-07">Metadata updated from new catalogue</change>
<change when="2025-04-29">Header enriched</change>
<change when="2023-05-19">Header confected</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text><pb n="1"/>
<front>
<titlePage><titlePart type="main">My Poll and my partner Joe: </titlePart><titlePart type="sub">A Nautical Drama, In Three Acts.</titlePart><byline> By <docAuthor>John Thomas Haines,</docAuthor> author of
<title>Austerlitz </title><title>Ocean Life </title><title>Richard Plantagenet,
</title><title>Alice Gray </title><title>Angeline </title><title>Amilie
</title><title>Breakers Ahead </title><title>Charming Polly </title>
<title>French Spy </title><title>Henriquez </title><title>Haunted Hulk
</title><title>Jacob Faithful </title><title>Invisible Husband
</title><title>Harold Love and Mystery </title><title>Nick of the Woods
</title><title>Rallin the Reeter </title><title>Wraith of the Lake
</title><title>Wizard Skiff </title><title>Elizabeth Lazarus
</title><title>Armstrong the Shipwright </title><title>Two Locksmiths
</title><title>Wizard of the Wave</title><title> Phantom Ship
</title><title>Iron Hand </title><title>Claude Duval </title>&amp;c.
&amp;c.</byline><titlePart type="desc">the Music Selected and Arranged By Mr. Jolly. </titlePart><titlePart type="desc">With an Illustration, and Remarks By D. G.</titlePart><docImprint>Thomas Hailes Lacy, Theatrical Publisher, London</docImprint></titlePage>
<performance>
<p>As Performed at the Royal Surrey Theatre (under the management of Mr.
Davidge), September, 1835. The celebrated Nautical Drama, (founded on a popular
Song of the renowned Naval Poet, Charles Dibdin,)</p>
</performance>
<p>The Medley Overture and the Music selected from the popular Naval Airs of the
celebrated Author of the Song on which the Piece is founded, by Mr. Jolly. The
Scenery entirely new, and taken from ACTUAL VIEWS ABOVE BRIDGE, &amp;c., by Mr.
Phillips and Assistants. The Machinery by Mr. T. Hagley. The Dresses, with a
strict attention to actual Costume of the period, by Messrs. Asbury &amp;Brown
and Mrs. Walker. The Decorations by Mr. Eallett.</p>
<castList>
<castItem><role gender="M">Captain Oakheart </role><roleDesc> (of H. M. Sloop
Polyphemus)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. Bannister.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Lieutenant Manly </role><roleDesc>(of
Ditto)&gt;</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. Norman.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Ben Bowse </role><roleDesc>(a
Boatswain)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. Cullen.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Black Brandon </role><roleDesc>(Captain of a
Slaver)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. Dillon</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Zinga </role><roleDesc>(a Negro)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. C. Pitt.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Harry Hallyard </role><roleDesc>(the Pride of
Battersea Hard)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. T. P. Cooke.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Joe Tiller </role><roleDesc>(his Friend and
Partner)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. R. Honner.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Watchful Waxend </role><roleDesc>(a Psalm-singing
Cobbler, nicknamed the “Bishop of Battersea”)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. W.
Smith.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Will Wall-it </role><roleDesc>(Landlord of the Crown
and Crozier)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. Young.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Sam Snatchem </role><roleDesc>(a
Bailiff)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. Asbury.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Old Sam Sculler </role><roleDesc>(a
Waterman)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. Mortimer.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="M">Jerome </role><roleDesc> (a Sentinel)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. Maynard.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Mary Maybud </role><roleDesc>(called “Pretty Poll of
Putney”)</roleDesc><actor sex="F">Miss Macarthy.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Abigail Holdforth </role><roleDesc>(a Shoebinder from
Bullock Smithy)</roleDesc><actor sex="F">Miss Martin.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Zamba </role><roleDesc>(a Negress)</roleDesc><actor sex="F">Miss Cross.</actor></castItem>
<castItem><role gender="F">Dame Hallyard </role><actor sex="F">Mrs.
Stickney.</actor></castItem>
</castList>
<p>Four Years are supposed to elapse between the 1st and 2nd Acts, and Six
Months between the 2nd and 3rd Acts.</p>
<div type="programme">
<head>Programme of the Scenery and Incidents.</head>

<p>View of the Hard or Landing Place, and of the opposite Shore.</p>
<p>INTERIOR OF SCULLER'S HOUSE.</p>
<p>The Maid of Allwork—Industry and expectation—The Sunday Wherry and every-day
Boat—Joe's present—The Frog and the Shark—How to pay a Friend's Debt—Honesty
against Knavery—I never forgive an Insult—The promised Wedding.</p>

<p>EXTERIOR of HARRY'S HOUSE, with GARDEN, and VIEW of the OPPOSITE SHORE.</p>

<p>A DOUBLE ROWING HORNPIPE,</p>
<p>By Mr. T. P. Cooke and Miss Macarthy, in lieu of the Flag Hornpipe in the
Third Act.</p>
<pb n="6"/>
<p>Act II.- Quarter-Deck of the Polyphemus - Open Sea,.</p>
<p>A Reprimand for doing too much—No right to do good against orders—Sail
a-head.</p>
<p>BETWEEN DECKS OF A SLAVE SHIP.</p>

<p>STRONGHOLD OF THE SLAVERS! THE SEA FAR BELOW!</p>

<p>TREMENDOUS EXPLOSION!</p>
<p>Interior of the “Seaman's Friend” Inn, Portsmouth.</p>
<p>The Docks, &amp;c.—Ships' Company paid off—Bum-boats ahoy!—Hay bags
aboard—Fiddlers and Frying Pans—The Warrant Officer—Poll's letter—A Sailor's
love—Home, Home, sweet Home—The Legacy—The stock of Leather and Wax—Off for
London—My Mother—my Poll—my partner Joe!</p>
<p>INTERIOR OF JOE'S HOUSE.</p>
<p>Banks of the Thames—Exterior of Joe's House, and of Dame Hallyard's—the
Sailor's Return— the Dead Light—the Secret—the Recognition.</p>
<p>INTERIOR OF MARY'S HOUSE.</p>
<p>The proof in print—A Seaman's Log of his hopes, fears, joys, and agonies—A
false one's excuses—Is she true—is he honest—my Mother's Will!</p>
<p>DEATH!—I,—MY POLL AND—</p>
</div>
<pb n="7"/>
<div type="liminal">
<head> REMARKS</head>
<head> “My Poll and my Partner Joe </head>
<p>NATIONALITY becomes a virtue when it springs from feelings inspired by the
land of our birth. “The man that don't like <hi>England</hi>," exclaimed honest
Jack Fuller, in the heat of parliamentary debate, <hi> "damn him, let him leave
it !"</hi></p>
<p> In turning over the page of history, we contemplate with enthusiasm the
martial prowess of our ancestors, who were called to defend not only their own
liberties, but those of mankind. Britain has maintained her proud supremacy
among nations through a long series of ages; trampled down stern oppression ,
that threatened , and (with her own glorious exception) had well nigh spread
abroad, universal anarchy; and crowned the august work by giving peace to the
world, and freedom to the slave.</p>
<p> Whatever brings to our recollection the triumphs of the past deserves our
gratitude; but when genius applies itself to the task, how truly it commands our
admiration! The deeds of heroes were the favourite theme of the poets of old,
and their noblest strains were devoted to immortalise patriotism and valour.</p>
<p> Blessings on the memory of the bard, “and palms eternal flourish round his
urn," who first struck his lyre to celebrate the wooden walls, , and the brave,
generous, Jack Tars of unconquered and unconquerable Old England ! If earth hide
him, light be the green turf on his breast; if ocean cover him, calm be the wave
on its surface! - May his spirit find rest where souls are blessed , and his
body be shrined in the holiest cave of the deep and silent sea!</p>
<p> Among the naval lyrics that roused and kept alive the ardent spirit of our
seamen is “My Poll and my Partner Joe." We remember when every manly heart beat
to this national melody; but other tastes (“the fruits of calm times and a long
peace" ) are come upon us ; we have little sympathy for past glories. “Ye
Mariners of England, ” and “Here, a sheer Hulk , lies poor Tom Bowling," are
lost in (“Most Forcible Feeble!”) “Oh, no, we never mention her, " and “I'd be a
Butterfly." .</p>
<p> “ My Poll and my Partner Joe, " once so sweetly vocal, is now in strumental
in filling many bright eyes with tears, and the manager's purse with money. This
English song has suggested to Mr. Haines a drama as truly English, and that
promises to rival it in popularity.</p>
<p> In Harry Hallyard we behold a British tar, bold as Mars, brawny as Hercules,
and comely as Adonis ; in Joe Tiller, his friend and partner in a trim-built
wherry, a lad with a soul equally fiery, but a body of less herculean
dimensions. If Harry' s <hi>prose</hi> is of greater unction, Joe' s
<hi>verse</hi> is more than a match for it; for Joe builds the lofty rhyme where
the sea-mew does its nest, mounted aloft on the top-mast head. Among the
sailor's many virtues, prudence and worldly wisdom are not generally the most
shining; yet Hal is an exception; for, though deeply enamoured of his pretty
Poll, he resolves not to marry until industry has put him in possession of some
ready coin ; and that golden wish being now realised, the nuptials are at <pb n="8"/> hand. An unexpected appeal to his generosity introduces two very
opposite characters- Black Brandon, the captain of a slave-ship, and Sam, a
supreme oddity, a bailiff' s tail, timid, snuffling , and quaintly pragmatical;
with one eye blocked up, and the other set in garnets! Hal' s savings are
applied to rescue an ancient, broken-down mess. mate from the rude grasp of this
raggamuffin body-snatcher, and the wedding is about to be postponed , when Mary
Maybud, commonly called “ Pretty Poll of Putney," charmed with the generous
self-denial of her sailor, proffers him her hand, which is accepted with prompt
enthusiasm; and Watchful Waxend, a psalm- singing cobler and the Bishop of
Battersea, is deputed forthwith to solemnise the holy rites; a task of no small
difficulty to that devout prelate, seeing that his red nosed reverence is ever
on the reel with a crozier in one hand, and an ale-jug in the other. The jolly
young watermen and their lasses are assembled, the fiddles are going, and the
punch is getting pretty freely on board, when an ugly customer intrudes, es
corting a press- gang, who exercise without delay their detestable trade. Joe
claims protection as waterman to a fire-office, but for Harry there is no
retreating: the Phænix cannot restore him to his lady-bird, nor the Norwich
Union accelerate his own. For this good office he is indebted to his gruff
friend; butm 'tis useless to kick against the pricks, and every black bristle in
the beard of sable Brandon rises in retribution for an insult that Hal's just
indignation had offered to this savage trafficker in human flesh. The parting
between the distracted lovers; Harry's consignment of his pretty Poll to the
brotherly guardianship of his partner Joe; his adventures on board the
Polyphemus; the capture of a slave-ship; the liberation of the negroes; the
ludicrous recognition of the Battersea Bishop in the odour of sanctity, who
saves Hal's life by a well directed shot from a beer barrel; the storming and
blowing-up of the strong-hold of the slavers; negro gratitude; "tremendous
explosion;" and a fearful catalogue of etceteras that occupy an interval of four
years, are best described by the scenery, machinery, and performers of the
"Royal Surrey". — The sequel is mournful: Harry returns rich in fame and
fortune, accompanied by the soaking prelate, who in manners, costume, attitude
is so whimsically metamorphised into a sea monster, as to leave but few traces
of his former identity. Hal, in his long absence had been killed by the
newspapers; and Mary following the example of Southerne's heroine, Isabella,
marries Joe Tiller, and greets her first love on his return with the astounding
intelligence. — The surprise, sorrow and indignation of Harry Hallyard the
remorse, shame, and agony of the despairing f wife, were finely depicted by T.P.
Cooke and Miss Macarthy. The accidental death of Partner Joe at this sad crisis
terminates the tragic scene; he dies as he lived with honour but <hi>Honner</hi>
(too good an actor to be thus prematurely cut off dies not with him.</p>
<p>It is pleasant to behold an audience crammed to the roof expressing their
sympathy with the scene by silence and tears, and shouting their emulation of
fun and drollery with uproarious delight; — it is pleasant to behold our happy
countrymen, with their sweethearts and wives leaving the pandemoniums of treason
to their buffoon mendicants and enjoying a few hours of rational entertainment.
Who cares for <hi>Tom Duncombe</hi>, when he can see (a much better actor!) <hi>
Tom Cooke</hi>? — Or Partner <hi>Joe (of Middlesex!)</hi> when he can make merry
with the <hi>Bishop of Battersea</hi>? The Church in danger! By the rubicund
proboscis of the right reverend Hierach ! we would pull the caitiff by the nose
(as the devil's chaplain did Carlisle and Saint Dunstan did the devil!) who
should raise such a false alarm! The Bishop in his pulpit was hailed by a full
pit and <hi> both</hi> sees was <pb n="9"/> equally popular ! — a cobler-prelate
in leather-pontificalibus; a black muzzled Jack Tar in blue jacket and trousers,
with a portentous pig-tail, from which depended a holyday rosette of true blue!
Talk of cheap knowledge and penny politics! Here a man may be happy for hours
for sixpence aye, and (liberty and equality for ever!) <hi>look down</hi> upon
his master!</p>
<p> We are not in love with sentimentality (like virtue!) for itself alone. No
man likes mustard <hi>per se</hi>. In this drama our sympathies are awakened by
justice and humanity, and tis highly seasoned with a plentiful infusion of fun.
By virtue of the latter commodity, we are reconciled to Mr Sam Snatchem and
swallow with epicurean greediness his rich morsels of equivoque and pun. His
delicate appreciation of Poll's pretty foot ("'Tis not like a <hi>pickaxe</hi> —
as much behind as before!") redeemed his queer obliquity of vision and unique
breeches and top boots. This prime buffoon, in the person of Mr Asbury, was
<hi>sui generis</hi>. — The law of arrest loses its terrors in such a scarecrow
representative: were Sam to pop his head among his old acquaintances in the
house when the motion is discussed the bill would be lost!</p>
<p> Great praise is due to Mr T.P. Cooke, Miss Macarthy, and our pious friend
the bishop, Mr W. Smith. We were much amused with the nimble-tongued loquacity
of (Miss Martin) a west-end milliner and cher ami of the prelate's! The house
rang with her orthographical <hi>variations</hi> that would have puzzled
<hi>Walker</hi> and given old <hi>Tom Sheridan</hi> a fit of the cholic and
contributed some new readings to the excellent work now in progress of the
venerable <hi>father</hi> Sheridan Knowles.</p>
<p> Mr Haines has chosen a happy subject and treated it happily and Mr Davidge
by its adoption, deserves the unprecedented success that has attended its
production. Let the public be won by patriotic spectacles and we shall not have
cause to lament that our national character among the humbler orders of society
is degenerated into apathetic, not say brutal, indifference. Though <hi>now</hi>
dwelling in peace, the trumpet of war may ere long startle from our pleasant
dream of security and to whom shall we <hi>then</hi> look for protection? Not
the mischievous brawlers in high life and low— for base poltroons they are, and
timid as treacherous — but the brave spirits who have done us good service in
the hour of peril, and whose glorious example has inspired a succession of
youthful heroes to conquer or die for their country ! It is wise to infuse the
<hi>amor patriæ</hi> into popular amusements: national songs work wonders among
the million. In Little Russia, no sooner are postillions mounted for a journey,
than they begin hum a patriotic air which they often continue for hours without
intermission. The soldiers sing during a long and fatiguing march; the peasant
lightens his labour in the same manner; and in a still evening, the air vibrates
with the cheerful songs of surrounding villages.</p>
<p> Peace to the souls of the heroes whose bones lie mouldering in the
battle-field! On England's glory — now nerveless cold and (thanks to the
barking, foul-mouthed curs of democracy!) almost dead, — England's glory shall
the brave long-tried patriot inscribe "RESURGAM!" — for Wellington has not
conquered nor Nelson died in vain ! </p>
<p>D. G. </p>
</div>
<pb n="10"/>
<div type="costume">
<head>Costumes</head>
<p><label>Captain Oakheart and Lieut. Manly.</label>—Naval uniforms.</p>
<p><label>Black Brandon</label>.—1st dress: Long pea coat, red waistcoat, rough
blue cloth trousers, glazed hat, shoes and buckles. 2nd dress: blue jacket,
petticoat trousers, check shirt, leather belt and buckle.</p>
<p><label>Harry Hallyard.</label>—1st dress: Waterman's scarlet jacket, &amp;c.
2nd dress: Sailor's nankeen suit. 3rd dress: Sailor's blue suit.</p>
<p><label>Joe Tiller</label>.—1st dress: Blue brummagem, with a fireman's badge,
blue breeches, white hose, shoes and buckles. 2nd dress: brummagem, white
jacket, low-crowned hat, with crape band.</p>
<p><label>Old Sam Sculler.</label>—Old green brummagem, red waistcoat, plush
trousers, shoes and buckles, low-crowned hat.</p>
<p><label>Watchful Waxend.</label>—1st dress: Red waistcoat, with sleeves, black
breeches, with red and black patches on the seat, red hose and nightcap, shoes
and buckles. 2nd dress: Brown coat, glazed hat, black neckerchief, leather
apron, &amp;c. 3rd dress: Sailor's jacket bound with canvas, very large blue
trousers, check shirt, tremendous whiskers, long pig-tail, with blue ribbon at
the end, high straw hat, with blue ribbons.</p>
<p><label>Will Wall-it.</label>—Waterman's old suit.</p>
<p><label>Sam Snatchem.</label>—Shabby green coat, queer top-boots, white
hat.</p>
<p><label>Ben Bowes.</label>—Sailor's blue suit.</p>
<p><label>Zinga</label>.—White trunks and shirt, black arms and leggings, black
belt and buckle.</p>
<p><label>Mary Maybud.</label>—1st dress: Old-fashioned light chintz gown, with
the tail drawn up, red skirt, straw hat and ribbons, muslin apron, &amp;c. 2nd
dress: half-mourning cotton gown, white neckerchief, black mittens.</p>
<p><label>Abigail Holdfast.</label>—1st dress: Chintz gown, drawn up, scarlet
skirt, straw hat, &amp;c. 2nd dress: Handsome yellow sarcenet pelisse, crimson
sarcenet gown, straw bonnet, with large white veil, and ostrich feathers.</p>
<p><label>Dame Hallyard.</label>—Old fashioned dark chintz gown, black mittens,
mob cap, white apron.</p>
<p><label>Zamba.</label>—White frock, mob cap, red shoes.</p>
</div>
<pb n="11"/>
<note type="orig">[Mr. Lacy's Second List.]</note>
</front>

<body>
<head>My Poll and my partner Joe.</head>
<div type="act">

<head>ACT I. </head>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene First. </head>
<stage>—Interior of the Crown and Crozier Public House at Battersea; the Hard,
or landing place, seen at the back, and the opposite shore visible through the
large window; boats passing and re-passing as the curtain ascends.</stage>
<stage>Watermen discovered seated, smoking and drinking—Old Sam Sculler reading
a newspaper—Watchful Waxend seated near him, tipsy—Will Wall-it, the landlord,
attending— the company laughing.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>You may laugh, you profane scoffers; but I stick like wax to my religious
spirit.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M9">
<speaker>Wall.</speaker>
<stage> (R.)</stage>
<p>That you do, Master Waxend, and to my full proof spirit, too! </p>
<stage>(they all laugh)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>You're all going by steam to the diabolical oven— drinking and sotting from
morning till night! <stage>(to Wall-it)</stage> Fill my pot! You'll be thirsty
enough in the next world, and no beer; there they allows none to be drunk on the
premises.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M9">
<speaker>Wall.</speaker>
<stage> (bringing beer)</stage>
<p>Your beer, Master Watchful. Money!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Oh, stick it up. <stage>(turning to the Watermen)</stage> Don't trust me, but
read the Commen—Com-en-tatories of Julius Cæsar. </p>
<stage>(they all laugh)</stage>

</sp>
<stage>Enter Joe Tiller from the Hard, L. C.</stage>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Harry Hallyard not here yet!</p>
<l>Then I must forth again to wander by the river, </l>
<l>To see if I my par-tener and kind friend can diskiver.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Ah, Master Joe, you're a poet; why don't you turn your thoughts to holy
subjects? Why don't you do as somebody did—write a legacy in a country
churchyard?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>An elegy, you mean.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Well, I know; some people call 'em t'other way. <stage>(drinking)</stage> All
the world's a sot! <stage>(drinking again)</stage> Ah, you little think how
drinking wears out the soul.</p>
<pb n="12"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>So much the better for you cobblers.</p>
<l>  If drinking wears the soul away, </l>
<l>   Why add a little leather; </l>
<l>For, till our welting does decay, </l>
<l>   We'll drink and stick together.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<p>Bravo! capital, Joe! hurra!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>That would make a capital psalm. I'll uplift my voice. <stage>(singing
loudly)</stage> “If drinking wears—”</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (rising)</stage>
<p>Hold your tongue, Master Waxend. I've got athwart of the account of the great
battle of late; here's a full list of the killed and wounded.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<stage> (rising, and coming forward)</stage>
<p>Oh, let us hear—let us hear.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M9">
<speaker>Wall.</speaker>
<stage> (crossing to Sculler)</stage>
<p>Is Dan Deadeye there?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>No.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M9">
<speaker>Wall.</speaker>
<p>Or Sam Scupper? or Charley Coil? or Mike Marline?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>No, no!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M9">
<speaker>Wall.</speaker>
<p>I'm glad of that—they left a long score unpaid. Now, I shouldn't mind if Ben
Binnacle was popped off; he was the only as one paid his shot afore he sailed;
and I've got his shore togs in keeping.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (starting)</stage>
<p>What's this? Harry Heartly dead! Harry! Poor fellow! poor fellow!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (L.)</stage>
<p>What! Harry that you were bound for?—That's   bad news, Master Sculler; he'll
never come back to pay his debt.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>No, Joe; and if they come upon the poor old waterman, why, they must e'en
sell his boat, and make a beggar of him at once.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>That'll be hard; let's hope better: no one would be Philistine enough to rob
a poor white-headed old man of his last crust.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (R. C.)</stage>
<p>Philistine!—Ha! the Philistines were common robbers—all Dick Turpins, every
one of them!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>You're too learned for us, Master Watchful; but I will say, it's a hard
law:</p>
<l>For if a man is taken to prison, </l>
<l>And stripped of everything that's his'n, </l>
<l>'Twere better far to stop his wizzen.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<p>Capital! capital!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M9">
<speaker>Wall.</speaker>
<p>Bravo, Master Joe! Why, you're quite the Byron of Battersea!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (modestly)</stage>
<p>I does a little poetical poetry; it comes natural to me.</p>
<pb n="13"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (standing on a chair, and drinking)</stage>
<p>Yes, the spirit naturally gets over us. Hear me preach.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<stage> (pushing him off the chair)</stage>
<p>No, no! no preaching.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Come, don't be cast down, Master Sculler. Where's Harry Hallyard? I've got a
little present for him—something   as I've been writing about his pretty
Poll—his Poll. Well, he desarves her, for a better lad with a truer heart never
feathered an oar.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Right, lad; Harry's the pride of the Hard, and Mary's the prettiest, aye, and
the most industrious wench on either side of the river. It's a pleasure to see
her little fingers go—stitch, hem, hem, from morning till night. She's been a
daughter to me, since her father died. Poor fellow, his was a brave end. Well as
I was saying, she's looked up to me because I was his friend; and a neater cabin
than old Sam Sculler's ain't to be found near the Thames—all her work. And now,
if these harpies come for poor Heartly's debt, they'll sell up all the sticks,
and leave the old man without a rag of canvas to weather out his days.
<stage>(sighing)</stage> Well, well!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>But they won't do that, Master Sculler; come, come, keep a good heart. But as
I was telling you, I've written a something about Mary.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<p>Let us hear.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (taking out a paper)</stage>
<p>Here it is. I—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Them charity schools is a good thing. </p>
<stage>(all laugh)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Ah, laugh away—they are a good thing. How many children they save from
depravity! how many do they teach the difference between a brute and a man! I
learnt in one; and I should think I was unworthy the charity shewn to me, if I
ever stooped to deny it: for, mark ye, my lads,—</p>
<l>  When the mountains so high are kiver'd with snows, </l>
<l>What a very cold wind from the top of 'em blows! </l>
<l>But when great ones and rich ones are kind all the while, </l>
<l>What a very warm sun's for the poor in their smile!</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Good lad! good lad!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (tipsy, singing loudly)</stage>
<p>“When them mountains so “high”—common time—“when—”</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<stage> (stopping him)</stage>
<p>Silence! silence!—Let's hear Joe's verses.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Now, lads. </p>
<stage>(reading)</stage>
<l>Near Putney bridge there lived a maid, </l>
<l>   “More bright than May-day morn”</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Oh, stop! stop!—I've heard something like that in a hymn—long metre. </p>
<stage>(singing)</stage>
<l>“On Richmond Hill there lived a lass, </l>
<l>More bright than May-day morn”</l>
<pb n="14"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>Watermen.</speaker>
<p>Oh, fie! oh!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (offended)</stage>
<p>Well, I'll never write no more. I'm no pirate—I never steals another man's
ideas; at all events, you can never be robbed. </p>
<stage>(they all go up and sit)</stage>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Black Brandon, R. 2 E.—the Landlord bows to him—he advances
sullenly, and takes a seat, eyeing the company.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>This is the Crown and Crozier?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M9">
<speaker>Wall.</speaker>
<p>It is, sir; the best house above bridge for comfort and respectable
company.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (sneeringly)</stage>
<p>So I perceive. Bring me some rum; I have business in this neighbourhood</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M9">
<speaker>Wall.</speaker>
<p>Can I assist you in—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (surlily)</stage>
<p>  You can—bring the rum, and be hanged to you!</p>

</sp>
<stage>  Exit Wall-it, muttering R.</stage>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (drawing his seat near Brandon)</stage>
<p>Sir, were you ever among the niggers?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (starting and looking fiercely at him)</stage>
<p>Why do you ask?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>You'd make a capital slave-driver.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Dare you insult me?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Don't wax wrath, or I shall bristle up myself—Hear me preach!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Psha! fool!</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (he thrusts Waxend back, who falls over his seat—the Watermen rise
tumultuously.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (interposing)</stage>
<p>Come, come, sir; you are forgetting yourself, and insulting the clergy. This
is the Bishop of Battersea; and—</p>
<l>If the church is knocked down with such gaiety, </l>
<l>Why there'll be pretty pickings for the laity.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Am I among madmen here? Oh, here's the rum. <stage>Re-enter Wall-it,
R.</stage> Hark ye, landlord: is there one Sculler, a waterman, living in these
parts?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (coming forward)</stage>
<p>My name's Sculler—Old Sam Sculler.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>You had a friend named Heartly?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Ah, poor fellow!—I have just read of his death.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Then you must be aware he can't pay a certain debt he owed, and that you are
bound for it—here's the agreement, and so old gentleman, hand over the
rhino.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>  Great Heaven! I'm a ruined man!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (drinking)</stage>
<p>This rum's not so bad.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>You will give me time to look about me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>I want the money! <stage>(going to R. 2 E. and beckoning off)</stage> You
must talk to this gentleman about time.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="15"/>
<stage>Enter Sam Snatchem, R. 2 E.—he crosses to Sculler, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (pointing to Sculler)</stage>
<p>There's your prisoner!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Oh, my lapstone! what a gentleman! Baalam and his ass! Oh, ye captivators of
corpusses! hear my voice.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (to Waxend)</stage>
<p>Silence! or I'll spoil your voice for a month to come. <stage>(to
Sculler)</stage> Where's the rhino?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>If you insist on your demand, I am a beggar.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>Away with him!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M10">
<speaker>Snatch.</speaker>
<p>You see, my old cove, here's the parchment—no gammon about it—all reg'lar. So
you'd better out with the yellow 'uns, and stash all patter.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>I must sell my boat.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M10">
<speaker>Snatch.</speaker>
<p>To be sure; you must put up the floater. Take my advice; I'm the honestest
chap as is—has a feeling for the misfortunate: never resist the law; if a man
claims your vestcoat, let him have it, or you'll lose your kicksies in trying
the argument.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Away with him!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (R. C.)</stage>
<p>This is too bad. What, lads, will you see Old Sam Sculler, a man whose hairs
are grown white in honesty and industry, dragged like a dog to a gaol?
<stage>(crossing to Snatchem)</stage>   Let go your hold!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M10">
<speaker>Snatch.</speaker>
<p>Don't resist the law. Take my advice: if a man kicks you, rub the place; for
if you strike agin, ten to one if you has witnesses as to who was the
degressor.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>Watermen.</speaker>
<p>Down with them! down with them!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Look to your prisoner. Stand back, I say!</p>
<stage>  (he thrusts Sculler over to Snatchem, throws himself between them and
the approaching Watermen, and levels a pistol at them.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (running behind, and jumping on a chair)</stage>
<p>I'm a man of peace—hear me preach!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Quick! quick! away!</p>
</sp>
<stage>Snatchem is dragging Sculler towards the door, R. 2 E., when Harry
Hallyard enters suddenly, L. 2. E.—he darts forward hastily, and knocks
Snatchem's hat over his eyes, seizes Brandon's pistol, throws him round to the
corner, L. and points it at him.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Ahoy! what boats are foul here? An old wherry run down by a coal-barge!
Damme! stand back!</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (a loud shout, and a momentary picture of consternation and
surprise.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Who the devil are you, that board strangers like a red squall, without leave
or notice!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Who am I? I'm the happiest dog on the Thames; <pb n="16"/> got the best
craft, and the prettiest sweetheart; will pull a match with any man between
bridges; know how to serve a friend, 'specially an old one; always pay my rent;
can wash my own shirts; and hate lawyers.—Now, who the devil are you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M10">
<speaker>Snatch.</speaker>
<stage> (pushing up the hat from his eyes)</stage>
<p>Don't resist the law—take my adwice.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>So I will, lad. </p>
<stage>(knocking his hat over his eyes again— the Watermen follow Harry's
example, and hustle him from one to the other.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (R. C.) (interposing)</stage>
<p>Don't, lads, don't! Hark ye, Harry; you are a fine fellow, and I know will
listen to reason. This is Harry Heartly's debt; he, poor fellow! is dead,
and—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>  Harry dead!—Poor Harry! Well, but who's this gentleman that's come to shoot
us all?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (L.)</stage>
<p>I demand payment of the debt.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>When the devil demands his due, then look out: you'll be saying you knew me,
but I'll send notice that I never kept such company.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>A truce to this foolery! Am I to be paid, or must the man go to prison?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Why, look ye, sir: if your demand be a just one, it would be folly to
resist.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M10">
<speaker>Snatch.</speaker>
<p>That's right—take my adwice!—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>It would be vain to resist, as I've said; but you would never be so
stone-hearted as to strip an old man of the hard earnings of sixty years of
weary toil, and that, too, for a debt not his own. To pay your demand, he must
sell his boat; then what remains for him? He must go to the workhouse; the
winter of his days must be passed at the fireless hearth of charity, after
having honestly toiled away his summer to build himself a home of independence.
You wouldn't break the old man's heart?—Or, if you would, your own must be of
stone so hard, that all the paviours of London couldn't break it up to
macadamize one foot of road to the poorhouse, the last resting place you would
send him to.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>All the preaching in the world won't talk me out of my debt: my money, or a
prison for him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<p>  Shame! shame!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Hold, friends! Here, I will be bail for him, and Will Wall-it, here, will be
bound with me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M9">
<speaker>Wall.</speaker>
<stage> (R.)</stage>
<p>That I will!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (L.)</stage>
<p>Thank you, lads, thank you!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (to Brandon)</stage>
<p>And, do you hear? do you and your devil's imp beat down to the old man's
house in half an hour; and if my Poll is what I think her, we'll board you in
the smoke of a salute you little expect. Lead the way, landlord. <pb n="17"/>
<stage>(to Sculler)</stage> Cheerly, old heart!—'Tisn't every squall that
capsizes a boat.—Cheerly! cheerly!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<p>Hurrah! hurra!</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (Exeunt, Harry, R. 2. E., Sculler and the rest shouting— Snatchem is
following, when Waxend who is sitting at the back, R., knocks his hat over his
eyes, and the scene closes.</stage>
</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene Second. </head>
<stage>—A Room in Sculler's House.</stage>
<stage>Enter Mary Maybud, with needle-work, followed by Abigail Holdforth,
L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>And so, seeing you at work, you see, ma'am, I thought I'd make bold to ask
you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>Well, but my good girl, London is a large place, and the industrious never
need starve in it. What trade are you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<p>I'm a shoe-binder, ma'am, from Bullock Smithy. I'm a girl of moral
perpensities, can sing a psalm, or beat a carpet; and, as for turning a corner
in the binding-way, leave me alone for neatness.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>But what made you come away from your own town?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<p>There it is: one of my moral perpensities got the better of me—I fell in
love.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>And not being able to meet a return, you ran away from the object?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<p>No, I runned after the object: he was obliged to emigrate through a
misfortune—a wicked hussy swore a filiation to him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Then you should endeavour to forget him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<p>I can't forget him; and I thought it was best to come away, for fear they
should swear something of that sort to me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>I am sorry I cannot serve you; I am an orphan, and obliged to work for every
meal. I am content to do so, because I think, somehow, that the bread we have
earned must eat the sweeter. I am a stranger, too, to London; I never travel  
farther from Putney than just down the river in Harry's boat to Westminster
Bridge—yes, once I made a voyage to Hungerford Market. So, you see, my good
girl, I could direct you but badly; but if you had written to this lover of
yours—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<p>I did, bless you!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Then you know his direction?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes: the girl at the huckster's shop wrote three times for me, and I saw
the letters carefully directed, “Mr. Watchful Waxend, London.”</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (aside)</stage>
<p>So, so, Mr. Watchful! <stage>(aloud)</stage> You had <pb n="18"/> better look
in again towards evening; I have an old friend here who can, perhaps, advise
you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<p>I'm much obliged to you. Be so good as to say that I can turn my hand to
anything: I can hem and seam, and trundle a mop; nurse the baby, or turn a
mangle; I can bind shoes, and make hay; milk a cow, or sing a psalm; and don't
forget to say, that I'm a girl of strong moral perpensities.</p>
<stage>  Curtseys and exit, L.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>So, so; here's a discovery for the Bishop of Battersea! as my Harry calls
Waxend. Oh, dear! I wish our marriage was over!—And yet, I'm sure, if Harry was
to ask me, I should put it off for another year. Harry's to row for another
wherry in a month. La! if he was to win that, as he did the last!—that might
alter affairs. Mr. and Mrs. Hallyard, with two boats of their own!—I'd have one,
with a white awning all fringed round, and a flag at the stern, for Richmond
parties,   and t'other for every-day work—Joe should row that. I like Joe,
because he's Harry's friend, and he's so good-natured and poetical, and because
he's so kind to me;—yes, he should row the every-day one, and my Harry should
sit like a king in the other; and then, when there happened to be no company, he
should just pull me and the little ones down to—La! what am I thinking of? We've
neither got the boat nor the little ones yet.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (singing without)</stage>
<l>“Poll, dang it; how d'ye do? &amp;c.</l>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Joe Tiller, door L. C.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Ah, my pretty Mary! I've been longing all the day to have a peep at your blue
eyes. Why, what's the matter?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (pouting)</stage>
<p>I don't like your singing about Poll this, and Poll that. My name's Mary.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>I mean no disrespect, Mary; but ar'n't you called Pretty Poll of Putney?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>Oh, yes; and there's a parrot at the public-house —she calls herself Pretty
Poll of the King's Arms.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, forgive me.</p>
<l>Oh, kill not my heart with a frown from your eyes, </l>
<l>For if you look angry, the poor flutterer dies. </l>
<l>Men may talk as they like, each pretends he's a wise 'un,— </l>
<l>A frown from a woman to true love is pison.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (mildly)</stage>
<p>Well, I'm sure I don't frown—I'm not angry, Joe; only, you see, Harry is in a
fair way to be a most respectable proprietor of boats; and he wouldn't like his
wife   to be called Poll Hallyard this, and Poll Hallyard that. Decent people
must have decent comportment.</p>
<pb n="19"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Very true, Mary; every word you say is wisdom:</p>
<l>There's some folks speaks wisdom and sense every minute, </l>
<l>Some, when they opens their mouth, always puts their foot in it. </l>
<p>But here, Mary, I've brought you a present. <stage>(taking a ring from a
paper)</stage> Here's a ring—a keeper: when Harry gives you a plainer ring, but
of more value—ha!—then, Mary, put this on—his friend's present as a guard to
protect his own. Harry loves you dearly, Mary, but not more than Joe loves
you—as—as a friend.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Yes, Joe, I know you do; and I'll wear your ring, and dance with you at our
wedding.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Will you, though?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (without, L., door, C.)</stage>
<p>Yo ho! the pretty Mary, there!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Oh, here he comes! <stage>(imitating)</stage> Yo ho! there, the saucy Harry!
yo ho!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (without)</stage>
<p>Yo ho!—Now, a long pull, old one!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>I forgot to tell you—don't be alarmed—Harry sent me forward that you mightn't
be alarmed,—but poor old Sculler—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>What—what of the old man?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Is going—to—to prison.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>To prison!</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Harry Hallyard, door L. C.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (running to him)</stage>
<p>  Oh, Harry! the old man—my dear Harry— <stage>Enter Old Sculler, door L.
C.</stage> Ha! <stage>(rushing to Sculler, and embracing him)</stage> You are
not gone, then! What—what is the meaning of this? <stage>Enter Black Brandon,
Sam Snatchem, and several Watermen, door L. C.</stage> What men are those? Is it
true? is it true?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>Come, cheer up, lass!—Why, you're as troubled as Chelsea Reach in a gale.
Only shipped a little of the bilge water of misfortune: you and I must lend him
a hand to bale him dry. Hark ye, lass—come here. </p>
<stage>(they retire up, R.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M10">
<speaker>Snatch.</speaker>
<stage> (L.—to Brandon)</stage>
<p>She's a pretty little 'un, an't she?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>Silence!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M10">
<speaker>Snatch.</speaker>
<p>Got a nice little vaist, and a neat article of a foot; not like a pick-axe—as
much behind as before.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Fool! hold your tongue!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (coming forward with Mary)</stage>
<p>Go and fetch it, then, <pb n="20"/> Mary—will you?—There's a little queen;
and I'll talk a bit to these visitors. <stage>  Exit Mary, R.</stage> Come, old
heart, we're on the right tack; now just listen to me. <stage>(crossing to and
eyeing Brandon, who meets his gaze with ferocious defiance)</stage> Hark ye, my
black-looking friend, it strikes me that, after all, you're a sort of a kind of
a pirate. The paper you've brought is right, but how the devil did you run foul
of it? Come, shew your reckoning, as they say at sea. Who are you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>  Who am I? I am one who thinks the frog of the river looks well when he
questions the shark of the sea.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>That observation's true in your log—shark, indeed; but when we get the shark
in the shallows; let him look out.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (significantly)</stage>
<p>The frog would look pretty in the Atlantic.—I never forget an insult.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Tell us how I may insult a callous heart like yours, and I'll do it, that
your memory may last for ever. <stage>(looking off, R.)</stage> Ah! here comes
the best girl in the world, with a load of ammunition that shall founder your
cockleshell. <stage>Enter Mary, R., with a canvas bag.</stage> Give it me, my
lass. Look at that girl: she's life and all the world to me; even your iron soul
must tell you I'm a happy fellow, for she loves me. Bless her blue eyes! they
are heaven's stars to me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (R. C.)</stage>
<p>Harry—Harry! remember—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>I must talk to 'em, lass; and just now my heart feels like a member of
Parliament—it could speechify till a dissolution; but, hang it, girl. I hope to
more purpose. <stage>(to Brandon)</stage> Well, as I say, we love each other; we
were both poor; I won a wherry; it enabled me to earn and to save money; she
worked hard, too; we agreed to marry when we had saved thirty pounds; there's
the sum. <stage>(throwing the bag at the feet of Brandon)</stage> Your debt is
thirty-two; will you take it?—No!—There's the black demon of avarice grinning in
every wrinkle of your ugly phis-og. But there, sir, <stage>(throwing down
another bag)</stage>   I have earned a pound to-day—that makes thirty-one; and
if you don't take that, and discharge the old man, damme, I'll give you both a
pound's worth of drubbing to get a full receipt. </p>
<stage>(throwing off his jacket)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (interposing)</stage>
<p>Stay, Harry, stay! It were a pity a humble and honest man should ever foul
his hands by a contest with either a tyrant or a rogue. I don't mean to say,
sir, you are the one or the other; but there's another pound, earned by honest
labour: take your full demand, and quit the house before this gallant spirit
<stage>(pointing to Harry)</stage> bursts <pb n="21"/> through the bonds of
prudence, and makes you do it by the window.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Brand.</speaker>
<stage> (taking up the money, and laying down the paper)</stage>
<p>This is all I want; you can talk about honesty when I'm gone; it's not a
saleable commodity, and I know nothing about it. But hark you, sir,
<stage>(turning fiercely to Harry)</stage> —I've already told you I never forget
an insult; we shall meet again. <stage>(to Snatchem)</stage> Come, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M10">
<speaker>Snatch.</speaker>
<p>She's a werry pretty one, for all that, though there is a bit of the
brimstone, too.</p>
<stage>  (Harry turns and moves towards him—he darts off, door R. in
flat)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Why, old man, the tears are in your eyes; give us your hand; Poll and I have
only to wait another year or two, and you are happy.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>But I have prevented <hi>your</hi> being so.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Pshaw, never mind that; Harry, you're a noble fellow— Mary, you're a queen.
I'll help you, I'll never go to the Crown   and Crozier; but every farthing I
can save, you shall have; we'll soon have the thirty pounds.</p>
<l>With a long pull and a strong pull, we'll shoot the bridge in style, </l>
<l>And we'll have the thirty pounds, yet be merry all the while.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>What a happy man I am, old heart, though the shark has sheered off with the
gold. Hang the mopusses!— what care I for the world's ups and downs, while I've
my Poll and my partner Joe?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>You were made for each other, and I am the cause of a continued
separation.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Not so; the money we have paid was Harry's, my earnings were trifling; and I
love him more for sacrificing the means of our marriage, than I did for earning
them; for that sacrifice was for you, my second father. <stage>(turning to
Harry)</stage> Why should we not struggle together as man and wife, as singly;
if you think my hand a reward for your noble devotion, take it—I will be yours,
even to-morrow.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (mad with joy, and kissing her)</stage>
<p>Eh, what, mine— to-morrow—my dear Mary; run, Joe, run down to Tommy
Teazepsalm, the parish clerk; tell him I'm to be married to-morrow —run, old
man, run to Will Wallit, tell him to send me in a store of grog, we'll be merry
to-night, my dear Mary; bless that fellow's black-looking ugly mug, if he hadn't
come I shouldn't—oh, my eyes, married to-morrow; Mary mine— what will old dame
say; married to-morrow; cut and run;   my dear Mary—bear a hand, bear a
hand.</p>
</sp>
<stage>  Exit in extacies, door, R. C.</stage>
<pb n="22"/>
</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene Third. </head>
<stage>—Outside of Harry's House, with a Garden looking over the River—the
opposite shore seen—boats passing— oars leaning against the door,
&amp;c.</stage>
<stage>Dame Hallyard discovered bringing on a table, near R. 2 E.— Watchful
Waxend seated on a stool near the table, smoking.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<stage> (R.)</stage>
<p>And so Harry said I was to welcome some friends.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (R. C.)</stage>
<p>Yea, welcome them with a joyous spirit. <stage>(drinking)</stage> I feel that
thou hast made me welcome; I should like a little heeltap, a little more wax on
the thread. </p>
<stage>(offering the glass)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<stage> (rising)</stage>
<p>You shall have it, though you're rather shaky now.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (rising and coming forward, C.)</stage>
<p>The struggling of the spirit is mighty within me; I want to preach, and I
can't till I've finished my pipe.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<p>And so, my boy—bless him—is going to have a merry-making; well, well, I
suppose Mary and he have made up the match: some mothers wouldn't like a young
wife coming home, and turning them out of office, but I know the wench—a better
doesn't breathe by the old river.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Ah, women are troublesome spirits.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<p>What do you mean? you never suffered by them.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Haven't I, though; their love has been my ruin; I looked too much after the
flesh; I worked very hard at my trade; but I couldn't help leaving a few Waxends
about.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<p>Pooh, you should have got married, as my Harry means to do: there's every
thing ready for him; there's his pipe, and Mary's favourite mug, and old Sam
Sculler's backey-box. Oh, what a happy old woman I am to have two such  
children.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (without, L. U. E.)</stage>
<p>Mother—Dame Hallyard—hoy, there!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<p>Here they come. <stage>Enter Harry, Mary, Joe, old Sam Sculler, and Watermen,
L. U. E.</stage> Oh, my dear boy, welcome all of you; Mary, my lass, give us a
bus; well—Eh, where is it to be? Have you agreed—Um! can I have a new cap made?
Hark ye, old Sam, you and I'll dance a jig at the wedding.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>That we will, old lass; ah, you don't know.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<p>Why, what's the matter?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Come here. </p>
<stage>(they go up, C.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Well, Mary, here's the Bishop all ready to marry us. How does your reverence
feel to day? Is the <pb n="23"/> spirit strong within you—for we've news, news
that will shake it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (very drunk, looking at his glass.)</stage>
<p>Thanks to your good mother, it's pretty strong; I had it waxed a little
more.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (R. C.)</stage>
<p>Master Watchful, were you ever in love.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (R.)</stage>
<p>Twenty-seven times.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Oh, shameful.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>Do you know a place called Bullock Smithy?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (staggered)</stage>
<p>I've heard of it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Were you ever in love there?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>The spirit was strong.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Did a girl ever swear—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (interrupting)</stage>
<p>  Don't mention it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>A girl from Bullock Smithy is here.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (alarmed)</stage>
<p>Here—then I must fly.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>But she will see you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>She shan't—it's not mine; mine are like wax-dolls, with hair like bristles,
and eyes as sharp as an awl. I'll fly— I'll not be made a victim; one more sup
<stage>(drinking)</stage> and I'll exile myself as far as Tuttle Street.
Farewell, Battersea—I'll— I'll not be sacrificed.</p>
<stage>  (falls, and tumbles off in great terror, R.—they all laugh— Dame
Hallyard and Sculler come forward)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<p>Boy, you've done a noble action; hang the pence, Mary and I will soon save it
up again; there's a grunter yet in the stye; the wherry's tight and light; you
are strong and willing, and Mary's active and industrious. As for me, I shan't,
I suppose, be able to reckon much on myself after a little time. Baby's clothes
are tedious things for an old woman—Eh, boy; eh, Mary. </p>
<stage>(laughing)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Come, let us be merry; take a seat, dad. <stage>(they all sit round the
table)</stage> Joe, run yourself ashore; Mary and I moor together. Mother, what
matters it which way the wind blows, so that our hearts are true, and we have no
leaks in our conscience; fill out a bumper—let's drink a health to Mary— I'm so
happy we're to be married to-morrow.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<p>Fill, fill—I'll drink that—I'll drink that.</p>
<stage>  (while they are busy regaling, a boat rolls on, L. U. E., filled with
Sailors)</stage>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Ben Bowse and Pressgang, landing quietly from the boat—Black
Brandon comes forward.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (pointing to Harry)</stage>
<p>Those are the men—fine young fellows. </p>
<stage>(retires)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>  Aye, Aye.</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (the Sailors approach silently—Harry snatches a kiss from <pb n="24"/>
  Mary—raises his glass, and is about to drink her health when Bowse taps him on
the shoulder)</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>You must come with me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (rising)</stage>
<p>Who are you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>The king wants men.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>What do you mean?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>You'll make a devilish good sailor, and must serve him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>Harry &amp;Joe.</speaker>
<p>Pressed!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Pressed!—Oh! no, no!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<stage> (R.)</stage>
<p>He'll come back an officer, my girl; and he'll have his friend with him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>No, you're out of your reckoning there. <stage>(crossing to Bowse)</stage> I
serve a fire-office—here's my protection.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<stage> (looking at the paper)</stage>
<p>All's right—you're safe.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (R. C.)</stage>
<p>And must he go! oh, sir, for pity—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>Pity ar'n't among the articles of the press service, my pretty dear.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Right. Fiends incapable of pity first gave birth to the idea, and by fiends
only is it advocated. What! force a man from his happy home, to defend a country
whose laws deprive him of his liberty? But I must submit; yet, oh, proud
lordlings and rulers of the land! do ye think my arm will fall as heavily on the
foe as though I were a volunteer? No!—I shall strike for the hearts I leave
weeping for my absence, without one thought of the green hills or the flowing
rivers of a country that treats me as a slave!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>  Duty is duty, and must be done.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<l>So says the thief when he serves the devil, </l>
<l>And does it the readier 'cause it is evil.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Come, Mary, lass, <stage>(she is almost fainting)</stage> cheer up; I'll
return an admiral—be faithful to you in every clime. This little lock of hair
shall be the sheet-anchor of our constancy. Bless you, mother! I must go.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F16">
<speaker>Dame.</speaker>
<stage> (drying her tears, and stifling her sobs)</stage>
<p>You must, boy. I know you will do your duty as a man; but for the sake of the
young lass, and for the old lass, too, don't be rash, my Harry: be a hero—I know
you will—bless you, my son— bless you!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>Dear mother!—Mary, bid me good bye—a kiss, lass!—You will be true to me?
<stage>(Mary points upwards)</stage> All's over.—I'm ready, lads.—Joe, you are
my friend: take care of the wherry—protect Mary and my mother—be to them as I
would! Bless you, Mary! <stage>(kissing her)</stage> I have your promise,
Joe?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>You have.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (wringing his hand)</stage>
<p>Farewell!—Mother—Mary. Heaven bless you all!</p>
</sp>
<pb n="25"/>
<stage>Enter Black Brandon, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (to Bowse)</stage>
<p>Seize him! <stage>(to Harry, sneeringly)</stage> You see I never forget an
insult!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Ah, villain! art thou here? </p>
<stage>(he darts fiercely at Brandon, but is dragged away)</stage>
</sp>
<trailer>END OF THE FIRST ACT.</trailer>
</div>
<note type="orig">A period of Four Years is supposed to elapse between the First
and Second Acts.</note>
</div>
<div type="act">
<head>ACT II. </head>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene First. </head>
<stage>—The Quarter-Deck of the Polyphemus.</stage>
<stage>Enter Captain Oakheart, Lieutenant Manly, and Officers, from the cabin,
R. door in flat.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>Gentlemen, the duty, for the performance of which we are assembled, though a
painful, is an imperative one. To preserve the necessary discipline, we are
compelled to reprimand a brave man for an act that confers honour on the British
flag; yet, while obliged to condemn, we shall applaud and honour in our hearts,
one of the best seamen that ever trod a plank—one of the most fearless spirits
that ever handled a cutlass: his very courage must be restricted with severity,
or his example and extraordinary success will banish subordination from the
fleet.</p>
<stage>Enter a Midshipman, L., with a Guard of Marines, conducting Harry
Hallyard, prisoner—he bows respectively to the Officers.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>You have been four years aboard the Polyphemus?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>Ay, your honour.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>You were a volunteer?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>No, your honour; I was a pressed man, pressed on the day before I was to be
married to the prettiest and best lass in the world. <stage>(taking a lock of
hair out of his bosom, and kissing it)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<stage> (R. C.)</stage>
<p>You are a brave fellow, Hallyard?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>Thank your honour: there's no scarcity of 'em aboard this craft.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Right: I am proud of my crew, but brave men should never forget obedience to
their superiors. You have forgotten your duty; you have been promoted since you
came on board; <pb n="26"/> you are a petty officer, and Mr. Manly has ever been
your friend; yet you have proved yourself ungrateful.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>  Oh, your honour! don't say that—it cuts me to the soul! Do you think I can
ever forget that Mr. Manly did all that he could to get me my pretty Poll's
letter that was lying for me at Trieste, when we were up the Mediterranean? and
he would have got it, too, but sudden orders came for us to join the fleet in
the West Ingees.—My log wouldn't be worth keeping, if I hadn't got that in large
letters. And then your honour's been so kind to me since I've been aboard, that
you've almost made me forget the cruel law that took me from a young bride: so,
what with your goodness, and the ship (bless her!) being called the
Polly—Polyphemus, keeping me always in mind of somebody at home: I've begun to
be almost happy.—Ingratitude! May I spring a leak, and go down in the black sea
of contempt, if ever I take such a villanous cargo on board!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>And yet, Hallyard, you have dared to disobey orders. Mr Manly, state your
charges against him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M2">
<speaker>Manly.</speaker>
<stage> (R.)</stage>
<p>I must first preface, that, in thus complaining of him, I am performing an
imperative duty, with which no private feeling dare to interfere. He will
respect me the more for a conscientious discharge of it, when I publicly avow
that he has twice saved my life.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Oh, your honour! say no more of that. I'd have done it even for sulky Sam,
the cook's mate, though he is the most disagreeable swab in the whole crew.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>  Proceed, Manly, with your charges.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M2">
<speaker>Manly.</speaker>
<p>After orders had been passed to lie close, (we, having in the night crept in,
and anchored under the enemy's guns), he secretly persuaded twelve of the crew
to a breach of discipline. They lowered themselves over the side into the ship's
boat, and, at the imminent hazard of the lives of all, and the destruction of
the commodore's plans, they attempted the cutting out of an armed store-ship,
loaded with ammunition and supplies.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Avast there, your honour! There's a bit of an error in your charge. We did
cut her out, and brought her clear off, in spite of the fire of all their
batteries, and the bellowing and blazing of their flotilla to boot; and if your
honour only remembers the prisoners we brought in—there were just two to a
man—six-and-twenty Spaniards, and we without a scratch, excepting Georgy Gunnel,
who would be so venturesome as to fight six—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Still you were wrong.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Wrong! your honour. Begging your honour's pardon, a great deal of it was your
own fault.</p>
<pb n="27"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Mine?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Aye, your honour, with respect be it spoken.—Don't you remember when you had
me on the quarter, to give me a little jobation, because, in the action of the
day before, I took the trouble to go and fetch the enemy's flag, to tie round
Mr.   Manly's wound—don't you remember that, as I was standing by, you pointed
out where the store-ship lay, and said it would be a glorious thing to
disappoint the enemy of all the powder and stores on board? Ah, I see your
honour recollects; and you said, too, it was an impossibility. Now comes my
fault. Says I, to myself, I don't think so; I knows about a dozen as would do
it, and, as our chaplain says, “damme!” if I don't try. And so I axed 'em, and
they said “yes;” and we tried it, and we did it; and that's all I can say about
it, your honour.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Now, mark what might have been the consequences had you failed. We were in
the presence of an enemy of superior strength; the policy of the commodore was
to hem them with their heavy vessels in shore; day by day we had been creeping
on them, till, on the night in question, we had taken up a position, which with,
every advantage on our side, must have brought them to a battle. Now, as I
before observed, had you failed, our resources and position would have been
known, and the prospects of the war totally destroyed in consequence.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>But as it was, your honour, they thought the devil was among them, and,
standing at all hazards out to sea, dropped like pigeons into the commodore's
hands.—Your honour will admit that, although you punish the cause—</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter a Midshipman, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M17">
<speaker>Middy.</speaker>
<p>Sail on the larboard quarter, your honour.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>What is she?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M17">
<speaker>Middy.</speaker>
<p>  Can't yet make her out. </p>
<stage>(they all listen eagerly)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Jump aloft, Hallyard; take my glass; you've a quick eye—report her build.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>I'm a prisoner, your honour.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>We'll take your parole for the present.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (going)</stage>
<p>Thank your honour. <stage>(returning)</stage> I suppose, your honour, I
mustn't board this craft, whatever she is, till— till I can lay my grappling
irons on her.</p>
<stage>  Exit bowing, L.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Gentlemen, each to his quarters; we will resume when this business is
over.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Re-enter Midshipman, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M17">
<speaker>Mid.</speaker>
<p>Hallyard reports a brig, armed—black hull—a good sailer—no colours.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>My life on it, he is right. Be brisk, gentlemen; we <pb n="28"/> may have
warm work in store; to your quarters—quick! quick!</p>
</sp>
<stage>  Exeunt, door R. in flat—shouts from forward, &amp;c.</stage>
</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene Second. </head>
<stage>—Between decks of a Slave Ship—the ports open—the hatchway seen, C.—a
large cask, L.</stage>
<stage>Slaves discovered chained to the floor—a Seaman walking to and fro,
heavily armed, and carrying a whip—other Seamen hastily passing with powder,
&amp;c.—Black Brandon, with a glass, at the port.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Brand.</speaker>
<p>Curses on her! she walks the water like a witch! Are all the black cattle
safe aboard.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M17">
<speaker>Seaman.</speaker>
<p>Ay, ay.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Brand.</speaker>
<p>Where in the name of the fiend is Bowse? She keeps the weather gage in spite
of us? and yet the Black Bet is no skulker on a wind. Hark ye, ye nigger
animals, if I hear the least noise, or see the least sign of grumbling among ye,
I'll make sharks' meat of every devil of you!—<stage>(looking out of the port
with his glass)</stage> Her sails rise above the waters as fast as the cloud of
a white squall. <stage>Enter Zinga from the hold, C., heavily manacled—he creeps
close to Brandon, and falls on his knees.</stage> What the devil do you
want?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>I would ask mercy, master; poor Zinga begs his wife.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Brand.</speaker>
<p> (R.)</p>
<p>Your wife, fool!—She's in my cabin; had she been kinder, you might now have
had your arms and legs at liberty.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<p>I'll wear your fetters, master; see—they eat into my flesh; yet I will be
happy; let me have my wife—my Zamba!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Brand.</speaker>
<p>You thought to escape me, did you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<p>I followed but the impulses of nature. Three years ago you tore me from my
country,—from the presence of my parents, and the arms of the maid, who is now
my wife; regardless of my shrieks and cries, you dragged me away to   slavery;
my heart was broken; and, if I murmured, the lash was my only answer. Yet,
master, I did not seek revenge; I could have had it. Yes, one night, when you
were sleeping, my knife was at your throat; but I thought of the words the good
white man said to me at my own home, when he taught us his religion, and I
conquered the temptation. Well, I served you faithfully; you again sought my
country to make more slaves; I fled to join my Zamba. Was it a crime? Oh! give
her to me, and I will be your slave for ever! In pity to my agony, spare her!
give her to my arms unharmed!</p>
</sp>
<pb n="29"/>

<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Brand.</speaker>
<stage> (striking him)</stage>
<p>Back, beast!</p>
<stage>  (Zinga staggers, then making a weapon of his chain he rushes to strike
Brandon, who presents his sword—the Seaman draws a pistol, cocks it, and is
about to fire)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Brand.</speaker>
<stage> (preventing him)</stage>
<p>Stop!—If we throw him overboard his carcase may betray us to those bull-dogs.
Give him the whip, and keep an eye upon him. Let us get clear of this hell-cat
in chase, and his hours are numbered.</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (the Seaman strikes Zinga with the whip, till, overcome by pain, he
crouches piteously at the feet of Brandon, who fells him with a blow—Brandon
bursts into a loud laugh, while the Seaman thrusts Zinga among the rest of the
Slaves)</stage>
<stage>Enter Ben Bowse, with a glass in his hand, L. 2 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Brand.</speaker>
<p>What news?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>I've made her out, though her hull isn't above the water, for I know the cut
of her jib. 'Tis the Polyphemus sloop; she that I was boatswain of, and deserted
from, when I fell in with you. We must make more way than we do now, or she'll
walk over us; 'tis the fastest craft in the service.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Brand.</speaker>
<stage> (looking out)</stage>
<p>She's a flying devil! <stage>(distant report of a gun heard)</stage>
Boom—She's began to talk; we must lighten the Bet. <stage>(gun)</stage> Boom
again!—Ah! chatter away!—If we can keep out of the reach of her long
speechifyers for another   hour, we may double her in the dark. Some of our
heavy metal must go over.</p>
<stage>  Exit, R.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>It'll be all of no use, Master Brandon. <stage>(looking out)</stage> See, her
sails flap—she is about to take a longer reach. </p>
<stage>(gun)</stage>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Watchful Waxend, R. 2 E., his dress half-sailor
half-cobbler.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Oh, lord! oh, lord! I wish I was at Battersea! I'd better have fathered all
the children of Bullock-Smithy, than been kidnapped here, and treated like a
white nigger; and now I shall be shot at like a piece of wax stuck in the middle
of a target!</p>
<stage>  (a shout and noise heard on deck)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>There goes Black Tommy overboard.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (to the negroes)</stage>
<p>Oh, Lord! they'll be coming down for some of your black Tommies soon. </p>
<stage>(shouts and noise again)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>There goes his brother Bill.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>My spirit sinks; when they've settled all the bills they will dot and carry
one with me. Oh, Mr. Bowse, who is it they are throwing overboard—how many is
there before it comes to my turn.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>Pshaw, fool! it's the two guns, our heavy thirty-two <pb n="30"/> pounders.
Ha! she feels it, but not enough. <stage>(noise again)</stage> Right, Brandon,
better lose our metal than our lives.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Very right, I'll lose anything rather than my life. </p>
<stage>(gun)</stage>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Black Brandon, hastily, R. 2 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>She nears us fast; will it never be night; curses on her. I've ordered Rasper
to cut eight inches into her ribs; let her shake a bit, so that we can run under
the rock of   Martinique—damn the repairs. </p>
<stage>(looking out)</stage>
<p>Oh! if he was to cut eight inches into my ribs!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Bravo, Bet! she'll bother them yet. <stage>(crash heard, followed by a
gun)</stage> It's all over with us! no, curse it, no—the black cattle shall feed
the fishes first, every mother's son of them. Ah! hark ye, Bowse, do you take
charge of the papers; tie a shot to them, and if we're spoke to, let the fishes
read 'em. </p>
<stage>(crash and gun)</stage>
<stage>Enter a Sailor, L. 2 E.</stage>
<p> What now?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M17">
<speaker>Sailor.</speaker>
<p>They've carried away the quarter bulwarks—shall we heave to?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>The first man that speaks of surrender, I'll scatter his brains about the
deck.</p>
<stage>  Exit Sailor, L.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>I'll hide myself, for I'm sure to speak of it. </p>
<stage>(gets into the cask, and stoops down to conceal himself)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Stay, a thought strikes me; it's getting dark, pick me out one of those
niggers—we'll give him a floating-bath; if they shorten sail to pick him up, we
gain time; if they don't, the sharks will get him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (peeping out of the cask)</stage>
<p>Oh, Lord! they'll be mistaking me for a nigger.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Bowse, I have it; bring me the woman from my cabin.</p>
<stage>  Exit Bowse, L.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (darting forward, and kneeling)</stage>
<p>Master, you will give me my wife—oh, master, mercy, master!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (laughing)</stage>
<p>Ay, ay!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (mad with joy)</stage>
<p>  Master, good master!</p>
<stage>Enter Sailors, with Zamba, L.—she rushes into the arms of Zinga.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Tear them asunder! </p>
<stage>(the Sailors separate them)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (piteously)</stage>
<p>No, no; you mistake: master captain has given me my dear wife, my own Zamba;
master will make Zinga happy.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Tie her in an empty hogshead; let her gently over the side; they'll hear her
shrieks.</p>
<stage>  (they seize her—she screams—Zinga breaks from the Sailors and embraces
her—she is dragged off, Zinga clinging to her, and shrieking—he is pulled back
by the Sailors)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (turning to Brandon)</stage>
<p>You are a white man, can your own God forgive you. </p>
<stage>(falls fainting—Brandon looks out, L.)</stage>
<stage>Enter Ben Bowse, L. 2 E., with papers—shrieks as of Zamba heard in the
shouts—they grow fainter and fainter as she is seen through the port-holes
floating away—they listen.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>'Tis done.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>'Tis a bad act.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>'Tis good policy; see, they shorten sail to pick her up. Now's our time; one
or two more, and we defy them. Are all the papers there?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>They are.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>We gain upon them; yes, they are changing their course to snap at my black
bait: I'll upon deck; have the husband ready for the gudgeons, and, d'ye hear,
if it comes to the worst, you know what to do with the papers.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>Ay, ay. <stage> Exit Brandon, R.—Bowse runs and looks out.</stage> All right,
the poor thing will be saved—ah, them Polyphemus lads are of the right sort;
what a fool have I been to leave her—no matter, I mustn't live to be found
out.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (recovering from his swoon, and rushing to the port)</stage>
<p>Ha, she is there! I see her arms raised for help, and as the wind comes I
hear her wild shrieks—my brain will burst.   Ha! the ship is shortening
sail—they put out a boat—they near her—one moment more and—oh, misery! the cask
is filling—they will be too late—my eyes will start—she sinks— she is lost!—no,
no; a sailor plunges into the waves; I cannot see them now; yes, he rises; she
is in his arms; they take her into the boat. <stage>(rushing forward, and
falling on his knees)</stage> She is saved! thanks, oh, heaven! thanks!
thanks!</p>
<stage>  (a momentary pause—a terrific crash heard—a report of cannon, and then
a loud shout and lamentations—part of a sail drops before the ports, and gives
the effect of the vessel being violently shaken)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<stage> (tying the papers to a ball, and laying them near the hatches)</stage>
<p>The game's up; they've shot away her mast.</p>
<stage>  Exit with the Sailors, rushing off as if to go upon deck.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (creeping out of the cask)</stage>
<p>Oh, lord, how hot I am! my flesh melteth and my spirit waxeth faint. They've
shot away the mast; I wish they had shot away the master. <stage>(guns)</stage>
There, they're at it again;—what a row they're kicking up about these
papers—they seem of consequence; I'll take one or two for my own private reading
when I'm at home at Battersea </p>
<pb n="32"/>
<p> —don't mention Battersea, I'm likely to be battered at sea, here. </p>
<stage>(he takes out some of the papers and hides them in his bosom—gun, and
noise)</stage>
</sp>
<stage>Re-enter Bowse, hastily, L. 2 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M3">
<speaker>Bowse.</speaker>
<p>It's all over; another minute, and they'll board us. <stage>(snatching up the
papers and throwing them through the port into the sea)</stage> Now, then to die
like a man.</p>
<stage>  Exit, R.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (hiding in the barrel)</stage>
<p>Now, then, to live like a man. <stage>(guns—crash)</stage> There seems to be
a deal of welting going on; I hope one side will get leathered. Oh, Bullock
Smithy, Battersea, anywhere but here.</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (Music—noise continued—Sailors cross hurriedly—Zinga rises, looks
round, and tries in vain to force his chains— the Polyphemus is seen through the
ports of the Black Bess—a tremendous crash heard—loud shouts, firing and
clashing of swords)</stage>
<stage>Enter Slavers with Sailors of the Polyphemus fighting— Bowse and Manly,
Harry and Brandon—Bowse is disarmed after a furious conflict, and, rushing past
desperately, jumps through the port into the sea—Brandon is cut down by Harry,
who turns from him, when Brandon fires a pistol, which knocks off his
hat.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (turning upon him)</stage>
<p>Missed, you black looking piratical robber! you'll swing for this. <stage>(to
Captain Manly, pointing to the Negroes)</stage>   There, your honour, there they
are, poor souls, chained all of a row like so many bullocks at Smithfield.
<stage>(pointing his sword at Brandon)</stage> May six of my week days be banyan
days, if I arn't as great a mind to let your ugly soul adrift on its downward
voyage as—but no, I'll leave you to the gallows.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M2">
<speaker>Manly.</speaker>
<p>Let the hold be searched, and the manacles struck off these poor
creatures.</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (Harry goes to the hatchway and looks down, while the Sailors are
releasing the Slaves—Black Brandon, making an effort, rises, and with a small
dirk is about to stab Harry in the back, when Waxend, peeping from the barrel,
shoots him—Brandon shrieks and falls, R.)</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (looking knowingly from the cask)</stage>
<p>There's a ball of wax for you, my boy. </p>
<stage>(he jumps out of the cask, and runs into the corner, L., as if afraid of
the pistol he has fired—Harry turns his head, and looks significantly at
Brandon.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<stage> (raising himself)</stage>
<p>It's all over—run down at last by a Peter-boat!—Well, well! no hanging this
time!—Hallyard, you don't recollect me; but I remember you! I never forget an
insult!</p>
<pb n="33"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (approaching him)</stage>
<p>I recollect that voice—those words! <stage>(recognising him)</stage> Is it
possible?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M4">
<speaker>Bran.</speaker>
<p>Ay, ay; I did a good thing in getting you pressed —made a neat rod for my own
hide. Well, it's all over—the Black Bet and her captain will go to Davy Jones
together. Put me over to the sharks—Ha! ha!—I never forget an insult!
<stage>(hysterically)</stage> Ha, ha, ha! </p>
<stage>(dies)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M2">
<speaker>Manly.</speaker>
<p>Let the ship be cleared of the dead—turn all hands upon deck.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>But the poor woman, your honour, that we picked up, she may have a friend or
a brother among these ebony   gentlemen.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M2">
<speaker>Manly.</speaker>
<p>Right: pass the word for the negro woman.</p>
<stage>  (Music—Zampa's voice is heard without, R. )</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (coming forward and looking anxiously at Harry)</stage>
<p>Zamba! my wife!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (eagerly)</stage>
<p>Your wife?</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (Zinga nods assent—Harry rushes off, R.—re-enters with Zamba, and
throws her into the arms of her husband.—In an ecstacy of gratitude, they
prostrate themselves at the feet of Manly and Harry)</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Lord love my eyes, the poor creeturs are lovyers— she's the Poll of his
heart; tip us your black fin, my honest fellow; there's one at home I'd give the
world to hug in my arms as you do your brown fair one here.—Here's a bit of her
silky hair—it's my breast-plate in the day of battle, and my library of comfort
in the dark hours of the night-watch.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M2">
<speaker>Manly.</speaker>
<p>Hallyard, I shall leave you as prize-master while I return to report to the
captain. <stage>(introducing Waxend)</stage> This poor fellow saved your
life—you must look to him. Come, bear a-hand, lads.</p>
<stage>  Exit, R.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Ay, ay, your honour. <stage>(to Waxend)</stage> Follow me, my lad, we'll
overhaul your log. <stage>(to the Sailors)</stage> And, do you hear, boys? let
the wounded be looked to—let the poor niggers go free upon deck. Dance, you
black angels, no more captivity, the British flag flies over your head, and the
very rustling of its folds knocks every fetter from the limbs of the poor
slave.</p>
<stage>  Exit, R.</stage>
</sp>
</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene Third. </head>
<stage>—Cabin of the Slaver.</stage>
<stage>Enter Harry Hallyard, followed by Watchful Waxend, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>Now, my lad, who are you?—you saved my life and I thank you; I'll do the same
for you another time; but—why, there's something about the build of your
figure-head as strikes me—did you ever cross my latitude afore?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>I don't know what you mean by your latitude, <pb n="34"/> but I've crossed
your door-way at Battersea many a time to see the old dame—capital punch she
used to make—haven't had a drop since.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Why, surely, no—it cant be the Bishop—what Master Watchful Waxend turned
pioneer and slaver!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>I was a slave myself—they made a white nigger of me; I was kidnapped on board
one night when the spirit had mastered me, and I fell asleep at Wapping, and
I've had nothing but wopping ever since.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Give us your hand, it does one's heart good to see any one from the dear
home. Well, and how was my Poll, pretty and constant, eh? and the old lass, old
mother, and Joe, eh? how are they? speak lad, speak. </p>
<stage>(shaking hands violently with Waxend)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>So I—I—I will when you've done joggling so.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Why don't you give fire, then? my heart's up in my mouth. My dear Mary!
<stage>(looking at the lock of hair)</stage> Let out a reef of your jawing
tackle, my lord bishop, or you'll get monkey's allowance.
<stage>(impatiently)</stage> How are they all? how's Poll?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>  I can't tell you, I've been away these three years.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Oh, lord! oh, lord! no news any way; not one letter have I had, and I've
wrote a dozen.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes, stop a bit; I've got one for you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Eh, from Mary? where is it, lad, where is it? How did you get it?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Why she gave it to me to take to the Admiralty the night before I was
kidnapped; and I popped it into my portmantle, and stuck it in with a ball of
wax, and so I've kept it ever since. <stage>(untying his neckerchief, taking out
the letter, and giving it to Harry)</stage> Here it is.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (snatching and kissing it)</stage>
<p>Bless her little fingers! How it smells of cobbler's wax!—never mind—let's
see what she says. <stage>(opening and reading it)</stage> “My dearest, dear
Harry,” Bless her! “we haven't none of us never had no letter from you”—Why, I'd
writ a matter of four before this was writ. “and I do nothing but cry for fear
of some accident.” Bless her pretty eyes, my poor Mary! “Oh, Harry, you ar'n't
unconstant, sure?” I'll be damn'd if I am. “Your poor mother asks the letter-man
every day whether he expects one from you to-morrow. Joe's very kind, and works
like a good one for the old dame.” Bless him! “She's crying over my shoulder
now. Do write—I can't see the paper—excuse blottings, my dear Harry—I must give
over. My heart will break if you don't write—do, soon, my dear, dear own Harry,
and God   bless you.—Mary Maybud. P.S.—Mother's and Joe's love, and mine a
million times.” Thank you, lad, for bringing this; <pb n="35"/> thank you, thank
you; bless them all. </p>
<stage>(sinks his head on Waxend's shoulder and weeps)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Why, Harry, Harry.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Oh, I arn't ashamed of these drops; when the heart's brim full of love and
happiness, it must run over somewhere, and where and why shouldn't it at the
eyes?—I don't think a man has less fire and courage in him for having a little
of the water of affection. </p>
<stage>(crossing to R. C.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (giving Brandon's paper)</stage>
<p>Here's something may serve to brighten you up a bit; may serve, as I say, to
put a little more wax on the thread.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (looking with ecstacy on the papers)</stage>
<p>Where! eh! what! correspondence with the enemy!—Umph—map of a secret cove or
harbour beneath the Rock of Martinique,— plan of the communication with the
fort—list of pirate signals —all's right.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Zinga, R. 2 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (R.)</stage>
<p>It was you, sir, who saved my Zamba's life; I owe you my gratitude. The
object dearest to your heart is glory—I can put the pirate's horde into your
hands; I have been his messenger to the rock for near two years: do you prepare
a strong cable by which you can ascend; put me ashore; I will enter the fort as
if from him; I will lower a rope from above, and—you understand?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>I do, my brave fellow; the rock's ours; you shall   be made a general for
this, and <stage>(turning to Waxend)</stage> you an archbishop; not a moment
must be lost—we are right off the rock now; the enemy will know this vessel;
here we have the signals, and let British courage do the rest, huzza! Dam'me,
I'll plant the British flag on their fort before the moon sinks. Bear a-head,
lads; old England for ever!</p>
<stage>  (Exeunt, R.)</stage>
</sp>
</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene Fourth. </head>
<stage>—Moonlight—the Slaver's Fort and Stronghold on a high rock at the back,
L., approached by a flight of steps cut out of the rock—a rampart running across
from the steps to R. 2 E.—a pole on the rampart with a lamp near the bottom,
with a cord attached to it, the whole having the appearance of immense
height.</stage>
<stage>An armed Sentinel discovered patrolling.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M12">
<speaker>Sent.</speaker>
<p>The Black Bet has taken a long sweep this time; it's my turn for a cruise
next—better than being cooped up in this dog-hole. I thought I made her out this
afternoon; if so, she'll be for running under the rock to-night. Let me see,
this is four hundred feet above the sea, yet I can almost fancy <pb n="36"/> I
feel the spray. <stage>(yawning)</stage> Yaw, aw; and by the booming of the cave
beneath, in spite of the moon's smiling, I should say it will be a rough night.
Yaw—I'm devilish sleepy. <stage>(a signal like a boatswain's call is
heard)</stage> What devil's bird is that chirruping. <stage>(the signal repeated
twice—he runs and looks over the rampart)</stage> 'Tis Brandon—there's the
signal light of the Black Bet under the rock; I must show the lamp for 'em to
hoist the portcullis in the path below. <stage>(raises the lamp by a cord to the
top of the pole)</stage> There's a wind rising, and Brandon's not the man to hug
the shore. We shall lose our supplies. <stage>(yawning)</stage> Yaw—I'd rather
turn in, than be prowling here with a storm brewing—yaw. </p>
<stage>(a knock heard, L. 2 E.—he opens the door)</stage>
<stage>Enter Zinga, L., with a wallet.</stage>
<p> Oh, it's you, Master Nigger, is it; well, what luck this trip?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<p>Good, Master Beargruel, good. Here, <stage>(giving a bottle)</stage> here's a
drop of the good; drink, while I deliver my message.</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (Music, piano—while the Sentinel drinks, Zinga draws a rope from his
wallet and makes fast the end to a staunchion, and drops it over the
rock)</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M12">
<speaker>Sent.</speaker>
<stage> (R. C.)</stage>
<p>I was glad to see that light below as if I'd had a fortune aboard.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (looking over the rampart)</stage>
<p>'Tis a fearful height.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M12">
<speaker>Sent.</speaker>
<stage> (still drinking)</stage>
<p>  It is.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<p>Hark how the wind howls. <stage>(aside)</stage> If their hearts should
fail—'tis too much for mortal courage to contemplate.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M12">
<speaker>Sent.</speaker>
<stage> (turning to Zinga)</stage>
<p>Here's your bottle—yaw, aw.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<p>No, keep it till my return.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M12">
<speaker>Sent.</speaker>
<p>Yaw—right. <stage>  Exit Zinga, L. 2 E.</stage> That black's got a white
soul. I—I'm very sleepy; another pull at the bottle may wake me.
<stage>(drinking)</stage> I wish I was aboard the brig. <stage>(walking about
hastily to keep awake)</stage> I—yaw, aw. <stage>(laying down on the
steps)</stage> Capital; yes, I—yaw. </p>
<stage>(goes to sleep)</stage>
</sp>
<stage>Re-enter Zinga, cautiously, L. 2 E.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M5">
<speaker>Zinga.</speaker>
<stage> (watching)</stage>
<p>The opiate in the brandy has taken effect; now to my task. <stage>(music—he
pulls up the cord he had lowered, and secures the cable which is attached to it
with sticks run through it, and fastens it securely to the stanchion—a
pause—stooping and looking anxiously over the rock)</stage> The rope is pulled;
they will make the attempt; 'tis a fearful peril. I see by the torch in the boat
which the preserver of my Zamba holds, that they have begun to mount; he is the
last, to cut off all retreat; each has his cutlass in his mouth, <pb n="37"/>
and with a raging sea beneath them, are trusted to a single rope—my heart
sickens at their danger. They pause—does one heart shrink? Hallyard is mounting
over the shoulders of those above him; he with his cutlass compels the men to
mount. Should the rope give way—it has worn with their weight upon the
rock—should it break—no, no! they are here.</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (Music—Harry springs over the battlements followed by Sailors, and
shakes hands with Zinga, who points to the Sentinel, whom one of the Sailors has
raised his sword to strike)</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (preventing him)</stage>
<p>No, no, the poor fellow sleeps; all fair and above board. <stage>(securing
the arms of the Sentinel, aud placing them against the rampart, then trying the
door of the fort)</stage>   So, fastened—perhaps this fellow has the keys.
<stage>(searching him)</stage> What's to be done—I have it. </p>
<stage>(he shakes the Sentinel, and the Sailors retire, R.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M12">
<speaker>Sent.</speaker>
<stage> (waking)</stage>
<p>Hollo! who the devil are you?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Silence; I am from Brandon.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M12">
<speaker>Sent.</speaker>
<p>Oh, good; I'll inform Sebastian and the rest.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Do so.</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (Music—the Sentinel goes up the steps and gives three knocks at the
door of the fort—a Guard puts his head from above, the Sentinel gives the
pass-word, “Brandon and the Black Bet”—the Guard retires—Harry motions his men
forward—they range on each side the door)</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M12">
<speaker>Sent.</speaker>
<stage> (to Harry)</stage>
<p>What does this mean?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (seizing him, and putting a pistol to his head)</stage>
<p>That you are in our power; one word, and you die.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M12">
<speaker>Sent.</speaker>
<p>I don't fear death.</p>
</sp>
<stage>  (the door is thrown open, and the Pirates rush out—the Sentinel calls
out “Treachery!” but too late—Harry snatches up the Sentinel's fire-lock, and
discharges it at the Pirates—one of them is seen on the top of the fort bearing
a tri-coloured flag—the Sailors dash into the fort—a general conflict ensues—a
shell is thrown as if from the ship below—it falls among the combatants— Harry
seizes it and hurls it into the fort—an explosion takes place—the fort is blown
up—torches are brought on —Harry attacks and disarms the Commandant, whom he
conquers—the Pirates are subdued—the fort bursts into flames—Harry dashes
through the fire, rushes to the top of the fort, seizes the Pirate with the
tri-coloured flag, hurls him into the sea, and hoists the British Standard,
amidst enthusiastic cheers—tableau)</stage>
</div>
<trailer>END OF THE SECOND ACT.</trailer>
</div>
<div type="act">
<pb n="38"/>
<head>ACT III. </head>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene First. </head>
<stage>—The Interior of the Seamen's Friend Inn, Portsmouth—a large bow window,
C. flat, through which is seen the road and quay beyond, with the docks,
vessels, &amp;c.—a fireplace, R.—the bar, with a glass partition, through which
the people are seen serving, L. 3 E.—tables, forms, &amp;c.—the church bells
ringing a joyful peal.</stage>
<stage>A Fiddler discovered on a high chair, R.—another outside the window, in
the street, playing different nautical tunes—Sailors and Girls dancing—other
Sailors with their Girls on their knees—some intoxicated, sitting on the ground,
examining a Jew duffer's slops and trinkets, and buying handkerchiefs, with
which they decorate the Girls—others they put in their pockets, which are
immediately stolen, and re-sold to the Jew by the Girls—a party of Seamen, quite
drunk, round the fireplace with a frying-pan and a pack of cards—they pour
spirits into the pan, and, amidst uproarious laughter, fry the cards and their
watches—Watchful Waxend, fresh rigged out as a Sailor, sitting C., with a Girl
on each knee, and a long pipe in his mouth.</stage>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>Chorus of Sailors.</speaker>
<l>Sailors lead a jolly, jolly life, </l>
<l>   While roving on the ocean; </l>
<l>In every port they have a wife; </l>
<l>   Of every girl a notion. </l>
<l>  Tol de rol, &amp;c.</l>

</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Yes, my loves, to be sure you shall have as much grog as you can swim in; but
as for the rings and things you want, I'll give you them the next time we come
to Portsmouth. <stage>(the Girls get up, disappointed, and go to those Sailors
who are buying of the Jews)</stage> Oh, dear! <stage>(rising)</stage> Yes,
they'd soon bring the cobblers all to an end. <stage>(to a Sailor, who is frying
his watch)</stage> Hollo, Jack! if you hadn't kept your watch better at sea, you
wouldn't have been able to make so free with your time ashore.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_Mul">
<speaker>Sailors.</speaker>
<stage> (laughing and shouting)</stage>
<p>Bravo! Bishop of Batterseea!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (turning to the fiddler)</stage>
<p>Come, strike up a tune, old Rosin! give me a hornpipe—common time.</p>
<stage>  (a dance)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (without, L.)</stage>
<p>Yo! ho!</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Harry Hallyard, L.—they all cheer him and retire up, except
Waxend.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>Yo! ho! lads!—Here I find you. Rather queerish anchorage, though, </p>
<stage>(pointing to the girls)</stage>
<p>—lots of rocks <pb n="39"/> and quicksands—eh! <stage>(pointing to the
duffers)</stage> and swarming with sharks, too. When I landed I could have knelt
down, but every one was looking;—my heart kept tittuping—tittuping! and the
tears of a whole lifetime seemed swelled into a   large lump just here. So I
pressed Mary's lock of hair, with the iron grip of a seaman, to my heart;
crowded all sail; and, without seeing a single landmark, made this harbour; but
how the devil I managed to steer clear of the chaiseses and the postesses, I'm
jiggered if I can reckon.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>I've seen two or three London-looking chaps about here; and so I—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (eagerly)</stage>
<p>Eh?—Did you ask 'em about Mary, and Joe, and the old house?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>I was just going to do it, when one of 'em says to the other,
<stage>(mimicking)</stage> “Demme! what a 'orrid smell of tah!—I never could
abide the wo-tah, demme!” So, you see, after that, I thought it was no use axing
'em about a waterman's home; for their manners convinced me they were no better
nor lords or linen-drapers, or some such people!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Well, well—have you made soundings about the coach?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Ay, ay.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>And secured the berths?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>Ay.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Then I'll only just beat about here till the captain bears down with a few
gimcracks, that want stowage, and then crowd all sail for London. What's the
name of the craft we're to go by?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>The Nonpareil.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>  The Nonpareil! I wish it had been the Polly, or the Polly-phemus; but never
mind, the Nonpareil will answer for my Mary. So, do you hear? heave a head, and
just make a minute of the exact time they say they'll weigh anchor.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>To be sure I will, and ask all about her rate of sailing: there's a fair
wind—we shall soon be at Battersea. </p>
<stage>Exit, L.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>I'm there now: I can see the old mother, with the bellows in her lap,
listening to Mary, as she reads my last letter about coming home; I can see the
tears standing in the wrinkles of her dear old cheeks; and I can hear Mary's
voice quivering a bit, as she comes to the part where I tell her that I love her
more than ever;—Joe, in the corner, with his pipe, fancying he's shaking hands
with his old friend, Harry, and puffing out the smoke to hide his quivering
lips;—I can see 'em all three, and the old wherry, and Sculler, picking
gooseberries in the garden, and the old clock behind the door, ticking louder as
if to welcome me; I can see 'em—I can hear 'em! What a fool I am! I'm crying
like a boy!</p>
<pb n="40"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M18">
<speaker>Jew.</speaker>
<stage> (coming down, L. C.)</stage>
<p>Von't you puy noting for de pretty tears?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>No, I'll buy nothing; I'll take her home no wishey-washey trinkum-trankums,
no base metal covered with a little finery, like the ugly figure-head of the
Saracen's phisog with a gold beard, but I'll take her the pure coin of an
unaltered affection, and the hard earnings of five years of   toil and
glory.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M18">
<speaker>Jew.</speaker>
<p>Very nice, put you'd petter take dem de earrings or de shoe puckles, ma tear. </p>
<stage>(goes up C., and sits with the girls)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Mary would give all the finery in the world for one word of love. My eyes!
I'm so happy! my heart is as merry as a newly-made middy, and I feel running
before the wind of joy with all the sails of content filled to bursting.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Re-enter Watchful Waxend, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>All right! in half an hour they'll take the peg out of the last! Pooh! I mean
to say, weigh anchor, or, vulgarly speaking, be ready to start in that time.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Hurrah! eh—here, shipmates. <stage>(the Sailors and Lasses come
forward)</stage> Some of us have been five years together; let our parting be a
merry one; order some punch, I'll pay for all; let us have a dance, drink
success to our ship, and then home to our sweethearts and wives. <stage>(Waxend
orders liquor at the bar)</stage> The Polyphemus sloop! the pretty Polyphemus!
<stage>(all shout and drink—aside)</stage> The pretty Polly! Fill again—I wish
the captain would bear down. Now, my lads, Captain Oakheart and the memory of
the brave Manly. </p>
<stage>(they drink)</stage>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Captain Oakheart, L.—they all shout.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Thanks, my brave fellows; I'll give you a toast anon. Hallyard.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Your honour.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>I shall see you in London soon; if you call at my bankers you will find that
your friend, Lieutenant Manly, has made you his heir; you saved his life twice,
Harry! but your   arm couldn't save him from the grim tyrant in the last action,
and as he had no relatives, you will now come into possession of three hundred a
year.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Oh, gemini! three hundred a year! was there ever such a sum?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Don't let wealth spoil you and your pretty Poll, but tell her that your
captain, who admires your honest integrity, will be her father on the day of
marriage, and give her, too, the best protection—a good husband.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Oh, your honour, I'm all over gratitude! Won't <pb n="41"/> Poll be proud,
not of the money, though I thank and bless the good lieutenant for it! (heaven
rest his brave soul!) but to think that your honour, a captain just posted,
should—Oh! my heart, what a jolly day we will have!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Come, my lads! fill me a glass of punch! <stage>(to Waxend)</stage> In the
meantime, my good fellow, here is a purse of fifty guineas for the papers you
furnished us in the slaver.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (taking the purse and bowing awkwardly)</stage>
<p>Oh, thank your honour. <stage>(aside)</stage> My eye! won't I buy a stock of
leather and wax. </p>
<stage>(retires, C.—Harry gives Captain Oakheart a glass of punch)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M1">
<speaker>Oak.</speaker>
<p>Here's our country, and may she always have sons as brave in battle, and as
humane in victory, as the lads of the Polyphemus. </p>
<stage>(drinking)</stage>
</sp>
<stage>  (great shouting without, during which Oakheart takes leave, and exit,
R.—a coach is seen through the window, C. in flat—People enter, L.—Harry and
Waxend take leave, and exit, L.—they are seen through the window to mount the
coach—the confusion recommences, the horn blowing, fiddling, &amp;c.—a Sailor
commences a hornpipe on the roof of a coach, which gives way, and he falls
through amidst great laughter, hurraing, and waving of hats, as the scene
closes)</stage>
</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene Second. </head>
<stage>—Interior of Joe's House.</stage>
<stage>Enter Joe Tiller, with his jacket on his arm, and a crape round his hat,
followed by Old Sam Sculler, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>And so we are to pull the gentleman down to the wharf, eh?</p>
<l>Where the timber from the Swedish coast is floating, </l>
<l>There the gentlemen would go a boating.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>Ay, and we must make haste, too; he said he would be ready in a few minutes,
so come along.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>No, I can't go out without seeing Mary; there's no persuading her out of her
melancholy—</p>
<l>All day she sits in tears, as sure as my name's Tiller, </l>
<l>Like a crying cherry-bum, or else a weeping willer. </l>
<p>I'll be bound, now, she's gone down to the church-yard to sit by the side of
old Dame Hallyard's grave; she's almost always there, and as for a smile on her
face—</p>
<l>They're as scarce to be met with as oysters in June weather, </l>
<l>And as difficult as strawberries in winter time to gather.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Ah, the old dame was a mother to her; and how she <pb n="42"/> used to watch
the poor old woman as she faded day by day! why, you might see her sink inch by
inch into the grave.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (melancholy)</stage>
<p>Yes; and Mary got as pale as a winding-sheet: bless her, I must see her for a
moment, then I'll go to work; work's my comfort. I don't know how it is, but I
feel a sort of a something hanging over me—it's very foolish, I know, but—</p>
<l>When the blue devils is wexing your brain, </l>
<l>  You may drive them away, but they come back again.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Well, then, run down to the church-yard and look for her; I'll go to the Hard
and prepare the boat.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Agreed. <stage>(going in, R., and looking off)</stage> Ha, here she comes!
look at her dear eyes, they're quite red; yet she endeavours to hide them from
me as if my own symphonies didn't inform me.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Mary, R. 2 E., very pale, in a plain neat half-mourning
dress.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (advancing with a melancholy smile, and giving her hand to Joe)</stage>
<p>Did you want me, Joseph?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (L.)</stage>
<p>I was just waiting to say a word to you before I went down to the Hard; you
are still fretting; you shouldn't take on so, Mary, it's breaking my heart.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (R.)</stage>
<p>I won't then, Joe, for you're very kind to me; I will endeavour to be
cheerful, it is my duty to be so; but I've had a dream, and I've been down to
mother's grave, and I couldn't look upon the blue flowers I've planted there
without crying a little—they seemed so like her own dear bright old eyes!
Besides, there's a strange flower grown up among them —I didn't put it there, it
came up of itself, like a message from the dead! It's a—yes, Joe, it's a
Forget-me-Not! <stage>(sobbing)</stage> a Forget-me-Not!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (with emotion)</stage>
<p>Well, well, we never can forget her.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Oh, never! I hope it will not die; pretty bud, to come of itself! I'll water
it every day. Do you know, as I looked at it, I heard her dead voice say the
words as sure as I stand here, so you must forgive me for being a little
melancholy.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>  Yes, Mary, I'm rather low myself to-day; I had a dream—I thought my boat
was run down, and I had a narrow escape of my life.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (anxiously)</stage>
<p>Heaven forbid! you are my last friend.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>I was a fool to let it annoy me—</p>
<l>But if we dream of one thing, it's sure to come con-tra-ry, </l>
<l>Because it is a maxim, you see, my dearest Mary.</l>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (coming forward, C.)</stage>
<p>There's one thing I'm dreaming <pb n="43"/> of that won't come contrary: if
we don't go down to the boat, the gentleman will hire somebody else to row him
down to the wharves, and it's a guinea job. </p>
<stage>(crosses to R.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Right;</p>
<l>And if we lose a guinea, </l>
<l>I know who'll be a ninny. </l>
<p>I don't know when I shall be home, Mary, but Sculler will come with me. Come,
cheer up a bit? go out and buy a few trinkums; call on Mrs. Strop, the barber's
wife; she'll talk you into spirits. God bless you!</p>
<l>Come along, my old chap, and let us diskiver, </l>
<l>If the customer's ready to go down the river.</l>
<stage>(going but returns)</stage>
<p>Good bye, Mary! good bye!</p>
<stage>  Exit with Sculler, R. 2. E.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (C)</stage>
<p>I have called on Mrs. Strop already, and I have seen a newspaper: the ship of
my poor Harry has come home; but, ah? where is he? <stage>(with great
agony)</stage> Stay—stay, Mary! you mustn't think in this way now; yet there can
be no crime   in loving the dead. I loved Harry living, and I can't do wrong in
loving his memory. I passed by the Hard, and I saw the wherry. Joe hasn't taken
out his name, for I could see it through the bit of crape he has nailed over it.
I looked and looked till I couldn't see boat or river; my head swam, and my
heart beat. I'm a silly—silly girl! I ought to have died with his mother; but I
feel I'm burning away. Ha! ha! I'm strong, but it won't last for ever; no—no!
<stage>Abigail Holdforth heard singing without, R.)</stage> Oh, here comes this
silly girl to annoy me; I have no spirits for her prattle.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Abigail Holdforth, dressed in the height of vulgar fashion,
R.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<stage> (speaking rapidly)</stage>
<p>Just comed up to Battersea for a breath of hair; Lunnun is so smoky! We who
gets our livelihood in the fashionable quarters, to be sure, is better off than
them as vegetates in the purloins of the Mansion House; but to me, a native of
the delightful city of Bullock-Smithy, it's all very condense and mistificatory.
So I took advantage of having to measure Mrs. Fubsey, the great maltster's wife,
(who lives within a short distance) for a new Parisian corset, to rustificate
for a day, or, rather, half a day; for I've got to take home Miss Jemima
Jumper's, the dancing-master's daughter's new yeller silk frock, and there a'n't
a stitch done; but I would come to see you, for, you know, you first recommended
me, and though my own talons have exasperated me into a first-rate Magazin des
Modes, I never forgets that to <pb n="44"/> your good nature I'm indebted from
the first. But you don't   look well: as Mrs. Cackle, the poulterer's wife says,
there's a melancholy conglomerification about you. <stage>(a pause)</stage>
What's the matter?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>I am not well. <stage>(aside)</stage> She'll kill me with talk!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<stage> (twirling round, and shewing off)</stage>
<p>Do you like this dress?—Pretty taste, isn't it?—You can't think how the
fellers did stare at me! one sailor-gentleman, in particular: it struck me I'd
seen his face afore;—at first I thought it was your Harry, but—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (starting at the name)</stage>
<p>Oh, do not—do not!—This is cruel!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F14">
<speaker>Abig.</speaker>
<p>I beg your pardon—I didn't think—But I must go to Mrs. Fubsey's: la! she is
such a perdigious size round! Oh, now I think of it, there was somebody with the
sailor-gentleman very like Watchful Waxend; but I was on the coach, and it
couldn't be he. <stage>(going)</stage> Well, good morning.
<stage>(returning)</stage> I must go, or Miss Jumper won't have the yeller
frock, and the Magazin des Modes will lose its charackter for punctualarity.
<stage>(going)</stage> Good morning, my dear! <stage>(returning)</stage>
Remember me to all; good bye!—Comment vous portez vous to you!— Mrs. Fubsey will
be in such a way!—Bye, bye!</p>
<stage>  Curtesying, and talking as she goes off, R.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>The sailor-gentleman she saw!—That's like my dream. In my sleep I thought
Harry had come back; there he was with his manly face tanned by the sun, but
looking better than ever; and his mother was crying with joy; and he was dressed
  like an officer, and opened his arms to me; and I tried and tried, but I
couldn't move near him; yet I saw him, and I heard him speak my name, and I felt
sure that he loved me;—and this was dreaming! Oh! I wish the sleep had lasted!
yes—how I wish I could have died in that dream!—But I awoke, and
I—<stage>(overcome with emotion)</stage> Oh, my heart!—Harry! Harry!</p>
<stage>  Exit in an agony of tears, L.</stage>
</sp>
</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene Third. </head>
<stage>—The Banks of the Thames, and the opposite shore in the distance—the
House of Dame Hallyard, with the shutters closed, R.—another house, L.</stage>
<stage>Enter Watchful Waxend from behind the house, R., in the dress of a
sailor, and smoking his pipe.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (surveying Dame Hallyard's house)</stage>
<p>Well, this is all very odd!—I've been “round the house, and round the house,”
as the riddle says; but every window is as close as a clicker's seam, and Harry
is waiting for me all this while in the road: he wouldn't come for fear of
frightening the old dame and <pb n="45"/> Mary.—He needn't have been afeard;
they've gone out for some frolic on the water. I haven't seen a soul I
know.—Well, I'll go down to the Crown and Crozier; old Wall-it will remember me,
for I owes him two-and-ninepence. But, first, to find Harry, and then—</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Harry Hallyard, hurriedly, R.</stage>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">

<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Avast, lad!—Why didn't you come?—You don't know how my heart has been keeping
reckoning of all the time you've stayed. Have you seen 'em? may I go in?—
<stage>(looking at the house, R.)</stage> Belay, there! I'm taken right aback!—
What's the meaning of all these dead-lights being hung out?— Have they shifted
their anchorage?—Have they fallen foul of any misfortune?—Where's my Poll?
where—where's the old mother?—Speak! say out what intelligence you've got, or I
shall founder with the trembles!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>The house is shut up!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (C.)</stage>
<p>I see—I see!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>I've been round it, and can't find a hole to peep in at.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Well—well!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>So I conclude—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>  What—what?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>That Joe's giving 'em a bit of a nautical discursion on the river.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Right, lad! that's it!—My heart was up in my throat!—There's no harm happened
to the old craft, that the young one has been obliged to sail from her moorings?
No! no!—Joe would take care of that—I know him.—Joe's a true heart!—It's hard,
though, within sight of port, to be blown out to sea again in this fashion.
What's to be done?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<p>I know what I shall do: I shall bear down to the “Crown and Crozier,” and old
Sculler's.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Good—they'll spin you a yarn. Crowd all sail! while I tack about these
latitudes.—I can't leave the old spot. <stage>(hurrying him off)</stage> Come,
lad, bear a hand, and be back in the turning of a handspike!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M8">
<speaker>Wax.</speaker>
<stage> (going, L.)</stage>
<p>I'll be back before you can wax a thread <stage>(returning)</stage> You stay
here, my boy: I'll hoist a signal that shall put a sparable in your heel, and
I'll stick to you like wax!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (impatiently)</stage>
<p>Ay! ay! <stage>  Exit Waxend, L.</stage> No, I can't leave the old house,
though there is nobody to welcome me. I thought I should have been scrunched up
with kissings and huggings, and hard shakings before now; and here, after five
years of danger, no one knows me: the old house shuts its doors against me, and
there's no Polly— </p>
<pb n="46"/>
<p>   no mother—no friend! Well, well! they didn't expect me. My eyes! how glad
they will be to see me when they do come!—What a fool I am! <stage>(crossing to
the house, L.)</stage> I don't know who lives here? But they'll give me some
chart to steer by. I'll knock and ax a question or two. <stage>(knocking, and
coming forward, R. C.)</stage> Yes, there's the old garden, and the little dock
where I used to launch all the small craft I cut out of the bits of wood I got
from Charley Chips, the carpenter! Ah! my pretty Polly was a young one
then!—Law! how she used to laugh to see 'em sail away lop-sided down the river!—
Bless her!</p>
<stage>Enter Mary from the house, L. in flat.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Was it you that knocked at our—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (starting suddenly)</stage>
<p>Ha! that voice! <stage>(turning and seeing her)</stage> Mary!
<stage>(advancing a step or two—she recedes, gazing at him)</stage> Mary! my own
Polly!—Don't you know me?—Harry, my girl!—Harry!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (as if awaking from a dream)</stage>
<p>Alive! <stage>(screaming with joy)</stage> Harry! my Harry! </p>
<stage>(she springs into his arms, and instantly faints)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Gently, my little tender one! But I hardly know myself whether my senses
won't desert the flag.—Lord love her pretty pale face!—Joy's colours I see are
white. <stage>(kissing her)</stage> Polly, lass, cheerly—cheerly!—Come, don't
shut the port of your pretty peepers to give your sailor his welcome, like the
old mother's house there. Mary—my precious Mary! Ha! her recollection's heaving
to; there—there!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (partially reviving, and looking vacantly around, as if striving to
recollect)</stage>
<p>  I thought that—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>—Mary!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>—'Tis he!—'Tis so, then; my dear Harry, you are alive, and—<stage>(rushing
into his arms, but recollecting herself, and screaming)</stage> No!
<stage>(shuddering back)</stage> No! Don't come near me —don't touch me,
Harry!—don't touch me, I say!—It is past!—Oh, cruel deceit!—Don't touch me! I
dare not—I— Oh! my brain is bursting!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (seizing her arm)</stage>
<p>What does this mean?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Oh, for mercy's sake! unhand me! you must not come near me! I am—I cannot
speak the word! Let go—let go! <stage>(struggling wildly)</stage> I shall go
mad! <stage>(breaking from him)</stage> There—there! Oh, pity me! when you know
all, pity me! </p>
<stage>(rushes distractedly into the house, L.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (thunderstruck)</stage>
<p>When I know all! What all? Is this my fond Mary, that—Oh, I'm dreaming!
<stage>(rubbing his eyes)</stage> Not come near her!</p>
</sp>
<pb n="47"/>
<stage>Enter Old Sam Sculler, hastily and agitated, R.—he crosses as if going to
the house, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (catching his arm)</stage>
<p>Avast heaving, old man! A word or two with you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Don't stay me: I'm on business of life and death!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Your answer is life or death to me. Don't you know me, old boy? Why, you
ar'n't altered a bit.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (in astonishment)</stage>
<p>Why, no!—What! can it be Harry Hallyard?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>It is.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (L. C.)</stage>
<p>  We thought you dead.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (C.—eagerly)</stage>
<p>Why's the old house shut up? Where's my mother?—Why does Mary fly from
me?—Tell me quick, old man: my brain's on fire!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (half aside)</stage>
<p>Oh, unhappy business! when he knows all—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>When I know all!—What is there for me to know? Out with the worst. My
mother—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Lies in yonder churchyard.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (staggering)</stage>
<p>Dead!—Poor old mother! and I not here to close her eyes! <stage>(a
pause)</stage> Mary—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Mary is—I—I can't tell you.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Oh, do, old man! if you have any mercy—if you have any recollection of your
green days, when your heart loved, and—speak! speak!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>It must be told. Mary is—Mary is married!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (paralyzed)</stage>
<p>God! married? Mary, that I have loved so truly, married! Oh! <stage>(laughing
hysterically)</stage> Ha! ha! ha!— It's a lie! <stage>(wildly)</stage> You may
as well trifle with a hungry shark!—Come, tell the truth!—Yet she wouldn't come
near me. I'm surely going mad!—Who's her—her—you know what I mean.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Her husband. Joe—your partner Joe.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (nearly falling)</stage>
<p>Oh, is—is this—</p>
<stage>  (he tries in vain to speak, at length bursts into a passion of tears,
and throws herself upon the shoulders of Sculler)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scull.</speaker>
<stage> (supporting him)</stage>
<p>My poor noble Harry! I won't   attempt to comfort you—words would be in vain!
but they were not to blame—I am their witness.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (with sarcastic energy)</stage>
<p>Not to blame?—Oh, no! falsehood isn't a fault, treachery isn't a crime. I
have been five years away, but I have never for a moment forgotten her; I have
worn this lock of hair upon my heart day and night, in the battle, the storm,
and the calm, ever since, and her name, my old mother's, and his, have been
oftener on my lips than my prayers, and dearer to me than the life I ventured.
Well, <pb n="48"/> I come back; I—I—find her false—the friend I loved a villain
—and my poor mother cold and dead! And all through their treachery—no! oh,
no!—they are not to blame! I—I—Curse it! I wish the tears didn't come up in this
way—they are fire! Here, here, take my money—take my watch—take all!
<stage>(putting them into the hands of Sculler)</stage> I earned all for their
sake, and now I have lost them. </p>
<stage>(going, R.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (detaining him)</stage>
<p>Stay, you shall see Joe; I have just come from him, poor fellow! he was well
an hour ago, but he has little life in him now—I am going to tell Mary—they are
bringing him here.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (anxiously)</stage>
<p>Why, what's the matter?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>In helping to unload a barge, the crane-chain snapped, it fell on him, and he
is all but dead.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Um—hark ye: break it to her gently—she'll suffer much; she'll be able to
guess what my heart feels; tell her   gently, and quickly, too.
<stage>(aside)</stage> She must not founder on the banks of poverty! Oh, my
brain! <stage>(to Sculler)</stage> I'll wait for you. Now, be gentle, old man;
she's but a tender thing. Come, come.</p>
<stage>  Exit into the house, L.</stage>
</sp>
</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>Scene Fourth. </head>
<stage>—An Apartment, with a large opening, C. in flat, covered by a chequered
curtain, which, when withdrawn, shews a neatly furnished room, with a glass
door, C. standing open, discovering the garden, the river, and opposite
shore.</stage>
<stage>Enter Mary, in excessive agitation, C. from R., dragging a chair after
her, and holding an old newspaper in her hand—her manner is wild and hurried in
the extreme—she seats herself, C.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (with trembling eagerness)</stage>
<p>I can't see, my eyes flash fire—I wish that I could cry! I did see it
here—no, no! <stage>(searching the paper)</stage> Ha! there, dead! dead! and yet
I have seen him—I have heard him call me his Mary, and I have lived to know
myself another's! Oh! if I could but sink into his mother's grave, and he never
know—but he will know, and he will loathe me—he will curse me! Oh,—do not, do
not, Harry, curse me! no, no! the old woman begged it with tears in her dying
eyes—he won't believe me—I—would I could die at your feet, Harry, that you might
see my heart! I was true; I—oh, don't spurn—I—</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Old Sam Sculler, C. from L.—she falls insensibly from the
chair.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<stage> (coming forward, C.)</stage>
<p>Poor broken-hearted girl! she breathes! <stage>(he goes up, pulls back the
curtain, discovering the room, and Harry Hallyard anxiously peeping in at the
glass-door <pb n="49"/>, and supporting himself by the door-post—beckoning
him)</stage> Look here, Harry, the poor thing's fainted!</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Harry—he advances and gazes for a moment on her— Sculler is going
to raise her.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (preventing him)</stage>
<p>No, no, let her lie still; I hear a noise of voices—they are bringing him—she
must be told first.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>Right!</p>
<stage>  Exit cautiously, on tip-toe, C. to L.</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (gazing sorrowfully on her)</stage>
<p>There she lies in her pale beauty, like a moon-beam on the stilled waters of
the ocean! What a pity she should be as cold as the one and as fickle as the
other! All my world is on that little spot of earth! Oh! if she could conceive
how I love her! even her changing heart would weep for me; but she can't—no, no!
she knows nothing of the holy hopes and the sweet longings of   of a real
love—even now false to me—another's! My soul is pouring out of my eyes in
adoration! I will raise her off the ground, 'tis a coarse bed for so tender a
flower. <stage>(raising her)</stage> I cannot resist the impulse! she will not
know that I have stolen that which is now another's—'twill be the
last—<stage>(kissing her)</stage> —the last, the last, and for ever!</p>
</sp>
<stage>Re-enter Old Sam Sculler, C. from L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>I don't see them yet; has she recovered?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (raising her)</stage>
<p>I think her recollection's heaving to. Here, take her, old man, take her.</p>
<stage>  (Sculler receives her in his arms—Harry overpowered with emotion, leans
on the chair, and weeps)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (recovering)</stage>
<p>It is true! he is dead, and—mother, don't cry so! I—oh, my brain!
<stage>(looking round wildly, and seeing Harry)</stage> Oh, I remember now! </p>
<stage>(she rushes to the paper, holds it up to Harry, pointing in agony to the
place, and throws herself on her knees)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M11">
<speaker>Scul.</speaker>
<p>'Tis the paper with the account of your death.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>What of that? had she loved, she would have hoped it was false, she would
have gone down to—to her grave as—</p>
<stage>(overpowered with emotion)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary</speaker>
<stage> (still kneeling to him)</stage>
<p>Would to heaven I had, Harry! How did I prove my love? though 'tis sin in me
to speak of it now. Two, three, four years elapsed, and no letters from you, but
I never doubted—I tried to prove my love for you by performing all the duties of
a daughter to your mother; still time went on; at last the news came that you
were killed— we saw it in the newspaper—Joe got the list from the
Admiralty—there we saw it again—I won't say how my heart was bleeding as I
watched your poor old mother dying with   the news—she and I wept together, and
prayed for the Peace; <pb n="50"/> I saw she was sinking too; she trembled to
leave me; for your sake she pointed to Joe as a protector—for your sake she
begged, and to let her die in peace, for your sake, Harry, I consented—I became
a wife, but I still loved, I still wept in secret, though duty made me silent.
Go! it is a broken heart now, and my hand is another's, but it is yours till the
grave—till—oh, pity! oh, pity and forgive! </p>
<stage>(she sinks exhausted, and is supported by Sculler)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>I do! I do! but can't believe that you—no—I have stayed to tell you that
there is money—I have earned it for your sake, and if you wish to—not quite to
kill me, you will use it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>No, oh, no!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>You will, Mary!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Oh, spare me!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>You will obey me, if you wish me to forget— forget! oh! that's as impossible
as that I should ever cease to love. But you may have need of it; the shoals of
adversity arn't always to be avoided; even now you are among the breakers. There
it is. <stage>(putting it on the table)</stage> And now—the old man there will
explain; I forgive you, but I don't wish to curse him. God bless you! </p>
<stage>(going)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<stage> (on her knees, clinging to him)</stage>
<p>Oh, pity!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>I do! I do! and do you pity me?</p>
<stage>  (he breaks from her, and rushing up, C., is met by Watermen, &amp;c.,
bearing in Joe, wounded—Mary shrieks, and runs to him—Harry comes down,
R.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<stage> (faintly)</stage>
<p>Bless you, Mary! I hoped to see you again, for—I—I had heard of Harry's
return, and I wished to say   something before I died, to prove that you were
innocent of falsehood to him.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Don't speak—you are bleeding.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>I am; but I must speak. Harry thinks I am a villain, but do explain. I'm
faint!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>I have told him—I—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>And is he convinced?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Joe, I grieve to see you thus; but unless my mother's voice from the grave
assured me of—</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Hold; here—here—here's your mother's will, where she leaves the sticks in the
cottage, and the wherry, and all to me, to marry Mary. You'll see how she urges
it for your sake. Read, Harry, read!—That is her voice from the grave!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<stage> (looking at the will)</stage>
<p>Poor old mother!</p>
<stage>  (kisses it and weeps)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Do you forgive her—forgive Mary?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry</speaker>
<stage> (dropping on his knee by his side)</stage>
<p>I do.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>And Joe?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes!</p>
<pb n="51"/>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M7">
<speaker>Joe.</speaker>
<p>Then I'm happy.—I'm dying! Harry! Mary!</p>
<stage>  (he pulls their hands together, joins them and dies across
them)</stage>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_M6">
<speaker>Harry.</speaker>
<p>He is dead!—Mary!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1058_F13">
<speaker>Mary.</speaker>
<p>Harry! Harry!</p>
<stage>  (they rush into each other's arms, recollect themselves and kneel in
prayer by the side of Joe.—the others take off their hats, and surround him, and
the curtain slowly descends)</stage>


</sp>
<stage>Curtain.</stage>
</div>
</div>
<trailer>Printed by Thomas Scott, Warwick Court, Holborn.</trailer>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>