<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L1388">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt><title>After the Party: TEI edition</title><author>[Anon.]</author><respStmt><resp>TEI conversion</resp><name>Lou Burnard</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt><distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor><idno type="LAE">L1388</idno><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which is believed to be in the public domain. You may copy, modify, distribute and perform this work freely. </licence></availability></publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc><bibl type="origin" n="93.8"><author>[Anon.]</author><title type="main" n="aftertheparty">After the Party</title><title type="sub">A Comedy in one act</title><extent>18 pp<measure type="pp" quantity="18"/>
  <measure type="spCount" quantity="297"/>
  <measure type="spvCount" quantity="0"/>
  <measure type="txWords" quantity="5495"/>
  <measure type="spWords" quantity="4488"/>
  <measure type="stWords" quantity="1007"/>
  </extent>
      <note type="fees">T.H. Lacy's List</note><title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 93,
       No. 1388</title></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453400&amp;seq=225">UM from
       HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol93/L1388/L1388-gb.pdf"/></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="TEI"><ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/L1388.html">TEI</ref></bibl><listEvent>
      <event type="firstPerf" source="text">
       <desc>Premiered at Unknown; date unknown.</desc>
      </event>
     </listEvent></sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <profileDesc><!--S 1 Comedy F. FARCE--><textClass><catRef target="#sizeS"/><catRef target="#act1"/><catRef target="nic:F."/><keywords><term>FARCE</term></keywords></textClass><particDesc><listPerson>
<person xml:id="L1388_M1">
<persName type="role">Mr FitzHoward</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">FITZHOWARD.</persName>

<persName type="spkr" n="149">Fitz.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1388_F2">
<persName type="role">Mrs Montgomery</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Mrs. Montgomery.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="137">Mrs. M.</persName>
</person>

<person xml:id="L1388_Misc">
<persName type="spkr" n="9">Voice.</persName>
</person>

</listPerson></particDesc></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change when="2026-01-11">Standardize header components</change><change when="2026-01-10">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change><change when="2025-11-02">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change>
   <change when="2025-09-07">Metadata updated from new catalogue</change>
   <change when="2025-03-19">Header enriched</change>
   <change when="2025-02-14">Hand edit</change>
   <change when="2025-01-14">Renumbering</change>
   <change when="2024-10-03">Header enriched</change>
   <change when="2024-08-13">Header confected</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text><pb n="1"/>
  <front>
   <titlePage><titlePart type="main">After the Party</titlePart><titlePart type="sub">A comedy, in one act.</titlePart><docImprint>London: Samuel French, Publisher 89, Strand. New York: Samuel French &amp; Son, •
     Publishers,  122, Nassau Street.</docImprint></titlePage>
   <pb n="2"/>
   <castList>
    <head>Characters</head>
    <castItem><role gender="M">Mr FitzHoward</role><roleDesc>(a Merchant)</roleDesc><actor sex="M">Mr. John Owen</actor></castItem>
    <castItem><role gender="F">Mrs Montgomery</role><roleDesc>(a Young Widow)</roleDesc><actor sex="F">Miss Clifford</actor></castItem>
   </castList>
   <set>
    <p>Scene: Boudoir in Mrs. Montgomery's house</p>
    <p>Time - Present Day</p>
   </set>
  </front>
  <pb n="3"/>
  <body>
   <head>After The Party,</head>
   <stage>Scene.— An octagonal Boudoir, furnished with extreme elegance;   R. 1 E., a couch and
    above it an oval mirror; door, R. 2 E.; door, L. 2 E.; L. 1 E., a fire-place, fire out; a
    window, hidden by large silken curtains, C. ; fauteuil and table, R. C.; lighted lamps—two upon
    the chimney-piece, one upon the table.</stage>
   <stage>Mrs. Montgomery is discovered seated in easy chair, and asleep, near table, R. C. , in
    ball dress, and a coronet of flowers on her head.</stage>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. Montgomery.</speaker>
    <p>No ; go away! Susan! Su— <stage>(awaking)</stage> Ah! Goodness ! What a dream!—I have been
     asleep —I see how it was. Wearied out, I—I fell asleep before having called Susan,
      <stage>(rising)</stage> I must ring for her at once., <stage>(looking at clock on chimney
      piece)</stage> Four o’clock! Impossible! Four o’clock! and my ball terminated at one! What! 1
     have slept three hours in that chair—and, only imagine—such a dream as I have had! That I
     should dream of Mr. Spitely—my opposite neighbour—he asked me to become his wife, and I
     refused. I did not dream that, for that was a reality which occurred some days ago! And only
     yesterday he wrote threatening to compromise me; and, at all hazards, to prevent my marriage
     with Augustus! Horrid man! He persecutes me and pursues me everywhere, even in my dreams! The
     very thought of it—but I must ring for Susan. <stage>(dugs bell beside fire-place)</stage> Poor
     girl! she has no doubt been here, and seeing me asleep, was afraid to awaken me.
      <stage>(listening)</stage> Not a soul—neither her nor Joseph ! They have followed my example,
     no doubt, and have fallen asleep in the ante­chamber. I will go and arouse them, and send them
     off at once to their rooms! <stage>(she takes lamp from table and goes off, door, L., leaving
      stage still lighted by lamps on chimney-piece after a moment, a loud snore is heard behind the
      window curtains)</stage>—</p>
    <pb n="4"/>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitzhoward.</speaker>
    <p> Who's that snoring in such a dreadful manner ? <stage>(he partly opens the window curtains,
      and is seen in a ball dress, and huddled in an easy chair)</stage> Nobody here! It must have
     been me! it’s just like me; I sleep so tumultuously that I awake myself! <stage>(rising and
      coming forward)</stage> The fact is that I needed those few moments of gentle repose!
     Yesterday evening, I left the small but highly respectable town of
      Dunsford—<stage>(stopping)</stage> May I venture to recite this to myself? Yes; everybody is
     in the ball room, dancing, and playing whist, and—well—<stage>(resuming)</stage> Yesterday
     evening, I left the small but highly respectable town of Dunsford, and arrived this morning in
     London, having travelled all night by railway. I took a cab from the station, and was driven to
     the residence of my nephew, number twenty-four, Tight Street. I tendered the cabman sixpence,
     which he indignantly—and with anything but classical language—declined to accept. His fare, he
     said, was half-a-crown. It might have been; I am not well up in it — and my nephew, he happened
     to be from home for a day and a night. This evening, I dined alone—and still at table—the
     dessert before me—one orange, two apples, and five nuts— when all at once, my old friend
     Buncombe walks in. “ Will you spend the evening with me," says he. " With great pleasure," says
     I. “ Then,” says he, " put on your dress coat and patent boots, and I will take you to a ball.”
     I take leave to inform Buncombe that I didn't come to London to dance; but he informs me that I
     shall meet at that ball a person—an important functionary—a chairman of our railway—of whom I
     have great need. So at ten o'clock we arrive at Mrs. Montgomery’s—a young widow—with whom I
     have no acquaintance. Being a widower myself, I am very partial to widows. To be a conqueror in
     that struggle till death, which is called marriage, proves a certain superiority. Buncombe
     presents me, and then we push through the crowd in search of my chairman. I get a great many
     digs in the ribs from a great many elbows, : and I dig a few myself. After about a quarter of
     an hour Of this liberal exchange, Buncombe says to me, “Your chairman can't have arrived yet; I
     shall go and have a game at whist. Do you go and pay your court to the mistress of the house.”
     Then I say, “Yes,” and I don’t go—for two reasons—the first, that I don’t like talking with
     women; it—always reminds me of the dear wife I have lost, who talked  great deal too much, and
     generally in a very loud voice; the second, that having been all night on the railway, I was
     tired. So, what did I do? I stole—no, slipped—pooh! I am alone. I stole into this boudoir; and
     here I have had a few minutes' sleep—-my chairman hadn’t arrived; and I hope now that i he
     isn’t gone. Some chairmen can’t rest two minutes in the
     <pb n="5"/> same place. I must put on my gloves again, and re-arrange my cravat, <stage>(places
      himself before looking glass, R.)</stage>— </p>
    <stage>Enter Mrs. Montgomery, door C. </stage>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Nobody ! They have not waited, it seems, for my orders to retire.
     Thought, no doubt, that I had forgotten them, <stage>(seeing Fitzhoward)</stage> Ah! some one
     here ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(aside)</stage> Oh ! the  mistress of—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Sir—who are you?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Fitzhoward—Alexander Fitzhoward. <stage>(gallantly taking the lamp from her hand and placing
      it on table, R. C. )</stage> Allow me, madam—introduced this evening by Buncombe—you know
     Buncombe—the man with the big nose.—.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(L. C. )</stage> But, sir, the ball is over.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Already, you are joking?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Joking! It is four o'clock in the morning!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Four o'clock! <stage>(hastily looking at his watch)</stage> So it is! twenty minutes past
     four. I have been put right by the Horse Guards.</p>
    <pb n="6"/>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> I’ll go and knock them up. I don’t mean the doors— the others. You know ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>You would not think of such a thing ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Servants are made to be knocked up. They don’t mind if they are paid, and I’ll give them a
     shilling amongst them. How many are they?—not above seven or eight, I daresay.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>It is impossible, sir! What would be said, should you be seen leaving my house, and three
     hours after every one else is gone ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> Well, but excuse me, you don’t intend to make me stop here, do you ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh, sir!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Then, madam, let us go to work systematically. The only way to leave a house, is by the
     door.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(timidly)</stage> Or—<stage>(crossing and pointing to it)</stage> Or by the
     window.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(R. C. )</stage> Yes, when we happen to be on the ground floor; but this is the second
     story.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(L. C. )</stage> The first, sir—the ground floor only is beneath us.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Well, the ground floor, that’s one, and this is two— the second story of course!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Sir—you are a gentleman ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Me? Oh, dear, no—I’m a churchwarden.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>You would not wish to render a lady the victim of a situation which you yourself have
     created—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>By falling asleep ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>That's true.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>You cannot, then, refuse me. <stage>(pointing to window)</stage></p>
    <p>Try—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>To jump out of window ? Excuse me, madam, but there are certain things which no one has the
     right to propose to a merchant, and especially a churchwarden, who is verging on fifty—to
     confess the truth, has actually passed it.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(still entreating)</stage> Sir, my honour is in question, you have compromised me—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(hesitating)</stage> I’m very sorry; and if we were on the ground floor certainly, I—I
     would jump—as a brave man, I would take the daring step!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(taking his hand and drawing him towards window)</stage> I entreat you—the night is
     dark, the street deserted.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>But are you asphalted ? <stage>(they have reached the window, Mrs. Montgomery half opens the
      curtains and drops them again immediately)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(frightened, and thrusting Fitzhoward from her)</stage> Ah! Withdraw!</p>
    <pb n="7"/>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(running and hiding behind door, L.)</stage> Eh—what ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(in a low tone)</stage> There is a light at the window opposite.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(behind door)</stage> Tell ’em to put it out and go to bed— ought to be ashamed to keep
     such dreadful hours 1</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Wretched spy !</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>You don’t mean me, I hope ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>No, no; a man who has sworn to destroy me.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>The murdering, thief ! I hope he hasn’t taken any oath on my account.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>He must not see you!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(advancing)</stage> So much the better, then I shan’t have to jump from the window—I’m
     out of that, <stage>(sits on couch)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(after a pause, C.)</stage> Ah, we are saved !</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(shocked)</stage> What! till to-morrow morning, oh! <stage>(jumps up and runs behind the
      couch)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>I mean till daybreak; at seven o’clock the servants will open the doors, and you may then
     leave unobserved.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(advancing towards her)</stage> Quite impossible!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh, sir—for the sake of my happiness! for it is necessary I should tell you all, I am on the
     point of entering into a second marriage with one whom I love—and—I have my reputation to
     preserve.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Well—and haven’t I got my reputation to preserve?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(smiling)</stage> Oh! a man’s reputation.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Yes, some men—but, I am a different sort of man— I am a highly moral man—I have reached,
     madam, the age of fifty-three, and am as innocent as a lamb!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(gently taking his hat from him)</stage> Do not refuse me. <stage>(indicating easy
      chair near fire-place)</stage> Seat yourself there. Besides, it is all your fault, you had no
     business to go to sleep in my boudoir.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(yielding, crossing over, and sitting, R.)</stage> You are settling it very nicely. If
     you had passed the night on a railway, with a fellow sitting opposite to you who kept on
     stretching out his long legs and kicking all the bark off your shins. </p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(R. C. )</stage> What a pity that the fire has gone out!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(seated, L.)</stage> A good example—I wish I could follow it.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p> You will be quite comfortable there! — </p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Shall I? I should prefer a feather bed though, for all that.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(getting a cushion from the couch and placing it
      <pb n="8"/> behind FitzHoward’s back)</stage> See, sir—let me place this cushion so —  at your
     back.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>That’s a little better.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(bringing a stool from before the easy chair near table)</stage> And this stool for your
     feet.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I am sure you are very good, but—<stage>(settling himself in the chair)</stage> for all that.
     I was a confounded fool to come to your ball.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>I am very sorry, I am sure—quite in despair.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>You don’t feel so miserable as I do, I know, <stage>(closes his eyes and turns round in
      chair)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>The glare of those lamps, perhaps? <stage>(lowers the two lamps on the chimney-piece)</stage>
     There, that's better, is it not ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(huddling himself in chair)</stage> Nothing’s better—it’s all worse.—.—.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(goes to table, R. C., and busies herself with her  jewel casket—a pause)</stage> You
     have not been in London, till now, for a long time ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(all of a heap, his eyes closed)</stage> No.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Do you like our city?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(louder)</stage> No.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Your home is in the country, I believe?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(slewing himself round, and opening his eyes)</stage> Excuse me, ma’am, are you like all
     the rest of your sex—must you talk or die ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh, no, sir, only I thought I might amuse you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Let me alone and I’ll amuse myself—I’ll go to sleep.—_</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh, sir, if you wish it——.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Retire to your own room, put on your nightcap, and go to bed.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh, sir!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>You needn’t mind me—bolt your door—I'm a moral churchwarden — aged fifty-three,
      <stage>(shutting his eyes)</stage>  Good night.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Good night, sir. <stage>(looking at him)</stage> Yes, the  best thing I can do is to let him
     sleep, <stage>(places herself before glass, R., and withdraws successively several pins from
      her hair - about to take off her wreath, finds that is still held)</stage>  Why it is not yet
     free!—,</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Pray don’t keep on tit-tit tap-tap—I can’t bear it; <stage>(slewing himself round towards
      her)</stage> Shall I come and help you?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Pray do not disturb yourself. I am removing my head-dress—but there are so many pins——.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(rising, going to her, and looking for the pin)</stage>  Yes I know a parcel of women
     with as many pins in their head as
     <pb n="9"/> they have got hairs on it. When I say a parcel of women- you will understand I
     don't mean you. <stage>(taking off tho wreath)</stage> There!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Thank you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> While I am about it, shall I unhook you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Sir!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(with indifference)</stage> Oh, I merely offered—I’d rather not have the trouble, I tell
     you. <stage>(beats up his cushion and re-seats himself in easy chair)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(taking up her jewel caskets and crown of flowers and lamp from table)</stage> Now 1
     will leave you. Good night, sir.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> Yes, go along—good night—bolt your door.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Why does he tell me that! <stage>(aloud)</stage> I will rouse you at
     seven o'clock.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Perhaps I shall disturb you before then.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(surprised—aside)</stage> Eh! It is really very strange. I have a presentiment that—I
     suspect some mystery, and am almost afraid—but I will say nothing now, and to-morrow—
      <stage>(aloud)</stage> Good night, sir.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Bolt the door. <stage>(Mrs. Montgomery goes off door R.)</stage> And this is what comes after
     the party. I hope she don't mean to bother me any more, <stage>(rising)</stage> I'll bolt the
     door my­self. <stage>(goes to door, R. )</stage> Ah! of course, no bolt on this side at all—and
     I have never clapt eyes on my chairman—shall be obliged to-go back home without having seen
     him—for what brings me to London, <stage>(confidentially)</stage> This is between ourselves, 1
     have told nobody but Buncombe, <stage>(pulls a staring cotton handkerchief from his pocket and
      ties it round his head)</stage> I am seeking to obtain authority to take the name of
     Fitzhoward— Alexander Fitzhoward—not that my real name is at all ridiculous, far from it.
      <stage>(looking around)</stage> There is nobody about, so-my real name is—it was originally a
     Russian name, I believe—is—Mizzleandcutof— yes, it's a Russian name, there's so doubt about
     that. Yes—promise you won't say a word—but Alexander Mizzleandcutoff, that's my real name. But
     my nephew don't like it—wants to change it—he's about to mix up in some financial matters,
     going to start a bank, I believe, and he says that Mizzleandcutof wouldn't do. I don't see that
     myself—I should think Mizzleandcutoff would do—but, I wrote to him," Renounce your marriage and
     I will change my name.” <stage>(arranging cushion, die., and again curling himself in
      chair)</stage> For he wants to get married—but I wouldn't hear of it—a London woman in my
     family?—never! <stage>(closing his eyes)</stage> He must marry a girl from the country!
      <stage>(closes his eyes, re-opens them after a moment and places his hands on his
      stomach)</stage> Oh! I’ve got the cramp in my stomach! <stage>(jumping up)</stage> I’m
     seriously ill— I can’t help it—I’m very sorry, but Mrs. Montgomery must
     <pb n="10"/> run for a doctor. Ah! I know now what it is, I’m hungry !— while the others were
     having supper, I was asleep I <stage>(taking lamp from mantel-piece)</stage> I must go and see
     if I can't find some­thing, if it’s only a turkey or so; a good strong application of that sort
     of would soon cure my complaint I</p>
   </sp>
   <stage>Goes off on tiptoe, door L.—as he is going out Mrs. Montgomery half opens door, R., and
    watches him)</stage>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(troubled)</stage> Where is he going ? Certainly there is something extraordinary in all
     this, just now he feigned to be fast asleep—insisted that I should go to my room—and now he is
     marching about the house ! The indifference that he affected while removing my wreath, and in
     his proposition to unhook me, and bis talk of his fifty-three years—all that is not natural!
     Have I fallen into a trap ? If he should be that wretch, Spitely! I do not know him—have but
     once, and scarcely, perceived him at his window—he appeared to me to be younger, but who shall
     say that be has not disguised himself in order that he might present himself here before me?
     People do not fall asleep in a boudoir on a ball night without —</p>
    <stage>Re-enter Fitzhoward, door C., carrying the lamp, with a small tray, plate, &amp;c. ., a
     partridge, and a bottle of wine.</stage>
    <p>There he is! <stage>(stands aside near the fire-place)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(not seeing Mrs. Montgomery, and placing the tray on table, R. C. )</stage> I have found
     a partridge. He's good company, and 1’11 talk to him directly.—-</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(aside)</stage> He is going to sup.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I shan't be sorry to recover a little strength.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Eh?</p>
   </sp>
   <stage>(Mrs. Montgomery goes towards back as Fitzhoward advances and places the lamp again on
    mantel-piece)</stage>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> Confound it! now I have disarranged my wig ! </p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside, at back)</stage> His wig. I suspected it.</p>
    <stage>(Fitzhoward goes over to R., and re-arranges his wig)</stage>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> Happily the young widow is not here to— She is comfortably sleeping.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> What shall I do? I must be calm. <stage>(approaches and arranges tray
      at table, R. C.)</stage> .</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(perceiving her in the glass turns quickly towards her)</stage> You, madam? you here? I
     thought you were fast asleep.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> And so I thought were you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(R. C., confused)</stage> Yes, so I am—only—I was so hungry—and this partridge—will you
     have a bit?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>No, thank you, I am not hungry.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I am—I have the appetite of an ostrich. </p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(pointedly)</stage> Or of a young man?</p>
    <pb n="11"/>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Yes, of half-a-dozen young men.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Well, sir, be seated.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>With great pleasure, <stage>(pointing to a chair)</stage> But first, if you would be good
     enough to —</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(sitting L. of table)</stage> Thank you, allow me to fill for you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(seated R. of table)</stage> As fast as you like, <stage>(eating)</stage> Confess that
     you think it is very unfortunate that I am not five and twenty, instead of fifty-three,
      <stage>(drinks)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Why so, sir?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Because a partridge—sparkling wine—and the society of a charming
      woman—<stage>(drinks)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Now we are coming to it!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Suppose for a moment that I am not fifty-three.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(quickly)</stage> You confess it?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>No, I don’t confess, I suppose—unfortunately I can only suppose—that’s all.
      <stage>(drinks)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Oh! I will compel him to betray himself.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>And behold us together at five o’clock in the morning. <stage>(looking at his watch)</stage>
     That’s the time—I’m right by the Horse Guards—you are seated beside me with no mistrust.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Oh, indeed! <stage>(aloud)</stage> Do you know, sir, what it is that
     renders women strong ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I have heard say that it’s what’s called calisthenics and gymnastics.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(boldly)</stage> It is their seeming weakness—they are not mistrusted—they advance
     boldly, and so they often triumph.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I don’t understand what you are talking about.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Shall I give you an example ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Yes, talk away now. I’ll listen to you while I’m eating —or rather, no—I’ll eat while I’m
     listening to you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>It is the history of what happened to a friend of mine—she was young.—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Like you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>A widow——</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Like you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>And, like me, on the point of contracting a second marriage.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>It is only for that purpose that women become widows. </p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>One evening, ’twas in the country, she was alone, when she received a visit from a gentleman
     of respectable appearance, of about fifty-two or fifty-three years of age-—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Like me in every particular.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p> Like you : he said he was a merchant.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>And a churchwarden, perhaps— .—,</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Perhaps so. The hours sped on, night had arrived,
     <pb n="12"/> and my friend felt compelled to ask this gentleman to stay dinner. Behold them,
     then, at table.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(eating)</stage> Like us.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(rising slowly and observing Fitzhoward)</stage> By certain signs—by the lightness of
     his manner—the vivacity of his eyes— my friend perceived that her guest was a young man
     disguised.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Bravo! <stage>(greatly delighted)</stage> I guess the denouement!— the elderly gentleman took
     off his wig, and threw it at the  lady's feet, <stage>(dashes his napkin on the tablet and is
      about to rise Mrs. Montgomery extends her hand to stop him)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>No.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(calmly)</stage> Ah! what then! <stage>(taking his glass)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(pointedly)</stage> He had not time; <stage>(pointing to his glass)</stage> for in the
     wine that he had drank, the lady had poured a deadly poison.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(rising quickly)</stage> Poison ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> It is he. <stage>(aloud)</stage> No, sir, have no fear; but
       <stage>(severely)</stage> do you think, really, that your conduct is that of a gentleman
     ?—-</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(confused)</stage> Well, I—I found the partridge on the side- board—-and I was
     hungry—and—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>I have refused you my hand. Is it my fault that I love another? Is that a reason why you
     should destroy me in the eyes of the world ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I ? I’ll take my solemn oath——</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>This disguise is useless. Your name is not Fitzhoward.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(aside)</stage> Eh!—she knows ! <stage>(aloud, greatly troubled)</stage> It is true,
     madam. That—that name—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Take off that wig.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(stunned)</stage> Eh?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Do not tell me again that you are fifty-three years of age, Mr. Spitely.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Who's Mr. Spitely—me?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p> Undoubtedly.—.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>It’s a mistake—a decided mistake. Certainly I am fifty-three—there’s no mistake there,
     unfortunately; and I have worn a wig for the last ten years, unfortunately.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(confused)</stage> Then I have been deceived.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Very likely.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>I beg your pardon; but I was so troubled that I was really so stupid as to mistake you for a
     young man.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>A very natural mistake, I flatter myself.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(graciously)</stage> Pray resume your supper.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(crosses  L. )</stage> Thank you—my appetite is gone.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(offering him a glass of wine and smiling)</stage> Fear nothing; I am not a Lucretia
     Borgia.</p>
    <pb n="13"/>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Then I’m not dead? Well, that is one comfort; but I am not thirsty now, thank you—that
     interesting history of yours—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(R. C., placing glass on table)</stage> Oh! a mere fancy sketch.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Never mind—it wasn’t good seasoning with my partridge, and I don’t feel comfortable at all.
      <stage>(sits in easy chair near fireplace)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Mercy on me!—you are ill!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Salts!—vinegar! Something—anything—everything!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Yes—yes. A moment—only a moment.</p>
    <stage>Hurries off, door R.</stage>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I shall be laid up —and perhaps I shall be laid out— and they call this going out into
     society! <stage>(rising)</stage> I believe a little fresh air would do me good; I can’t breathe
     here, <stage>(opens the window)</stage> Not daylight yet. <stage>(noise as of an opposite
      window being thrown violently open)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_Misc">
    <speaker>Voice.</speaker>
    <p>Sir!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(hastily retreating and letting the curtains fall)</stage> Oh I— the fellow over the
     way. <stage>(in a low tone)</stage> I suppose he never goes to bed.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_Misc">
    <speaker>Voice.</speaker>
    <p>You shall account to me for your conduct.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Means to challenge me, no doubt.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_Misc">
    <speaker>Voice.</speaker>
    <p>No use to conceal yourself. I know you, Mr. Mizzleandcutoff.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(greatly surprised)</stage> My name!—he knows my name!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_Misc">
    <speaker>Voice.</speaker>
    <p>I shall be with you at ten in the morning—number  twenty-four, Tight Street.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>My address! <stage>(rushing to the window)</stage> But, sir— </p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_Misc">
    <speaker>Voice.</speaker>
    <p>Good night, <stage>(the window is heard to close)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Stop—excuse me—</p>
    <stage>Enter Mrs. Montgomery, door R., a flagon in her hand.</stage>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Here, sir. What do I see ? That window open ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> Excuse me—I wanted some oxygen.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(frightened)</stage> And Mr. Spitely has seen you ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>It’s very strange—that fellow knows me.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Knows you ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Knows my address, number twenty-four, Tight Street.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(greatly astonished)</stage> How? You reside—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>At number twenty-four, Tight Street, with my nephew, Augustus Mizzleandcutoff—
     Fitzhoward.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Augustus ! Uncle !</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> Where has he seen me ? How did he know me ? I haven’t been in London before, for
     twenty-three years!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> He has mistaken him for his nephew.
     <pb n="14"/>
     <stage>(aloud)</stage> It is very simple—that gentleman was no doubt here this evening in the
     crowd—heard you named, and now would provoke you to—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(quickly)</stage> Oh! don’t be afraid, I know what I am about; I shan’t fight with him,
     I shall apologize.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Apologize ! what for ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I don’t know, but I shall apologise.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>And to-morrow I shall be the talk of the whole town—my marriage will be broken off, and it is
     you who— <stage>(pretending great distress)</stage> Oh, sir! why did you open that window ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Because I couldn’t do without a fresh supply of oxygen and carbon.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>What do you think will become of me ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(aside)</stage> She’s going to cry !</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>When the future lay before me so sweet and smiling—ah! I am lost! I have now only to die!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Allow me, madam—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh ! I know what you are going to do! You are about to propose to marry me!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I ? decidedly not I “ None wed the second, but who killed the first,” as Shakspeare says. I
     have taken a widower to remain a vow. <stage>(collecting himself)</stage> No ; I mean a vow to
     remain a——</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>And yet, sir, if I insisted—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Couldn’t do it, impossible! I should make you miserable. Sometimes my temper is awful!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>But then you have a son, of course ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Of course I haven’t, heaven has refused me that blessing, up to the present moment. I have no
     beloved son who is legitimately anxious to inherit my money and effects; and as I am a widower,
     it would be very improper if—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>You have perhaps a brother ?—a nephew ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>A nephew ? Yes, I have a nephew.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Then it is for him to repair the wrong which you have inflicted on my honour.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Well, he wishes to get married.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh! indeed?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>And I have opposed it. The best way to prevent him marrying his London lady, would be to
     compel him to marry you—it will be a good joke to play him.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>A joke!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>No, no—I mean, a good lark—he shall marry you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(aside)</stage> He is coming to it. <stage>(aloud)</stage> But should he refuse ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Then I’ll cut him off with nothing. Besides, why should he refuse? He is an elegant young
     man—so are you</p>
    <pb n="15"/>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p> Sir!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I mean, you are young.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Twenty-two.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Not bad-looking, rich—for you must be rich or—- </p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Twenty thousand pounds.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Twenty thousand! Charming—you, I mean—yes, you are charming, <stage>(aside)</stage> Twenty
     thousand pounds! <stage>(aloud)</stage> But let us see. Yes, I don’t see why, since it is I who
     have compromised you—<stage>(aside)</stage> Twenty thousand!—<stage>(aloud)</stage> I don’t see
     why I should force my poor nephew to marry you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Eh ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> Considering that I am here —for I am here.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p> You !—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Certainly. I have committed the fault, it is for me to repair it.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>But, sir, allow me.—'</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Not another word—I’ll marry you. Twenty thousand—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Eh ?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Twenty thousand times rather than—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>But I refuse. With respect to your nephew.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>My nephew, my nephew. I have deceived you—he is tremendously ugly—frightful!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> The wicked story-teller!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>He is three years older than I am—sixty-two if he is a day. His father was my elder brother
     by an early marriage with his first wife’s sister.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Well, it’s all settled, then, you accept me?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Never!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(crossing, R. )</stage> Then, madam, I shall be under the stern necessity of compelling
     you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(frightened)</stage> How?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>By completely and thoroughly compromising you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>But you have said that you should render me miserable—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>It would only be with too much love—<stage>(passionately)</stage> for I do love you, I adore
     you! And if you refuse me, I will open the doors, the windows—I will call, will shout, will
     fight—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh, this is terrible!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>When passion rules me, I am capable of everything, even of opening a window, <stage>(taking a
      step, she stops him)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Do not—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(joyfully)</stage> You consent?</p>
    <p>Mrs. M. <stage>(resignedly)</stage> I consent, <stage>(falls into a chair near
      fire­place)</stage></p>
    <pb n="16"/>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> Thank you, thank you! Ah! I have something to say that will delight you—I have told you that
     I was fifty-three, I give you my honour I am nothing of the sort—I am only fifty-two and eight
     months.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>What matters ? Only, sir, as we are now situated, allow me to charge you with a delicate
     mission.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Anything you please, madam! <stage>(with great joy)</stage> any­thing—anything!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(pointing to mantel-piece)</stage> You will find, in that coffer, letters and a
     portrait, presents that I have accepted. You will be good enough, sir, to restore them to the
     person from whom I have received them, <stage>(she rises)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(crossing L., and taking coffer from mantel-piece)</stage> Excuse me—but—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>As you are about to become my husband——</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Ah! that’s true ! <stage>(opening a letter)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p> Oh ! do not read, sir.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>As you are about to become my wife—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Ah! that’s true!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(running over the letter)</stage> Oh, oh ! I say—"a thousand burning kisses”—that’s too
     hot!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(vexed)</stage> Allow me—<stage>(aside)</stage> Twenty thousand pounds!
      <stage>(aloud)</stage> Your honour exacts it—I have compromised you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(smiling)</stage> Oh! an uncle of fifty-three.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> I beg your pardon, fifty-two—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>And eight months.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>No matter—a man may be a man at fifty-two and eight months.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>And besides, in what have you compromised me ? Is it not quite natural that an uncle who
     arrives in London should pay a visit to his niece ? Uncle—<stage>(pointing to door L.)</stage>
     that way you will find your chamber.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Ah! you have a chamber?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Which stays for you.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>And you didn’t tell me so! Bundled me into an arm chair, when all the while you had a feather
     bed—of course it is a feather bed.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(meekly)</stage> Yes, uncle</p>
    <pb n="17"/>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> Ah! it can’t be more downy than you are though.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>To-morrow your luggage shall be brought here, and you shall instal yourself as my guest.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>To be sure; nobody can have anything to say against  that.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(pointing towards window)</stage> Not even our opposite neighbour.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>He ? Wait a minute—<stage>(goes to and throws open window)</stage> wait a minute !</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>What would you do, uncle?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Wait, and you’ll see, niece, <stage>(calling)</stage> Hi—you—sir— mister, <stage>(window
      opposite heard to open violently)</stage> Sorry if I disturb you?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_Misc">
    <speaker>Voice.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(savagely)</stage> Well, what do you want?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>
     <stage>(taking Mrs. Montgomery’s hand, standing with her before the window)</stage> Merely to
     inform you that I have given my consent that my niece, Mrs. Henrietta Montgomery, whom, in your
     presence, I now and hereby kiss—<stage>(she shrinks)</stage> on the forehead, <stage>(she bends
      towards him, and he kisses her on the fore­head in an uncle-like way.</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_Misc">
    <speaker>Voice.</speaker>
    <p><stage> (shouting)</stage> Well?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Shall be immediately married to my nephew, Mr. Augustus Mizzleandcutoff Fitzhoward, whom I
     hereby kiss. <stage>(suddenly recollecting)</stage> No!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_Misc">
    <speaker>Voice.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(shouting)</stage> Well?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> And on the occasion of the wedding dinner, we respectfully hope—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Uncle?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Not to have your company!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_Misc">
    <speaker>Voice.</speaker>
    <p>Ugh! <stage>(the window is slammed down)</stage></p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>There ! I have done the polite, and now I’ll go to bed!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(gives him lamp from table, goes up with him, and opens door, L.)</stage> Good night,
     uncle ! You shall be called at noon.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Noon.? Say two o’clock; we require a good deal of sleep at fifty-two and eight months!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Very well. Good night, uncle.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Good night, niece ! Of course, I must kiss you again on the forehead! <stage>(he does so, and
      Mrs. Montgomery goes towards door, R.)</stage> The dignity of an uncle is rather difficult to
     maintain!</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(having opened door, R. )</stage> Good night!</p>
    <stage>Exit, door, R.—Fitzhoward going out door, L., suddenly stops, turns, and walks forward to
     footlights, lamp in hand)</stage>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Excuse me! <stage>(looking round to see that he is alone)</stage> I have a profound remark to
      make.<stage>(altering his mind)</stage> No,</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="18"/> I shall go to bed. <stage>(goes up to door, L., lamp in hand)</stage>  Eh?
     Well—yes—I will—<stage>(returns to footlights)</stage>—the fact is—</p>
    <stage>Re-enter Mrs. Montgomery, door, R.—advances and places herself beside him)</stage>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>What is the matter, uncle?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>Eh ? What do you want ? I kissed you, didn’t I—on the forehead—you surely don’t want me to
     give you the other nine hundred and ninety-eight burning kisses?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>I thought that you, perhaps, had something more to say to me.—. .</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>No ; but <stage>(gaping)</stage> before I go to bed, I fancied it would be only right if I
     should speak to—<stage>(indicating Audience)</stage>—:</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p>Oh! certainly, and in that I will assist you. <stage>(to Audience)</stage> My uncle wished to
     say that our happiness still depends on you, and that, if you refuse to ratify, with your
     favour——.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p>I didn’t wish to say anything of the sort! I merely wished to remark that I don’t like to
     lose my night’s rest, and, that they’re keeping me up now—</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_F2">
    <speaker>Mrs. M.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(reproachfully)</stage> Oh, uncle! was that all you had to say?</p>
   </sp>
   <sp who="#L1388_M1">
    <speaker>Fitz.</speaker>
    <p> No, it wasn’t— I wished to tell ’em too, that it will do ’em good the next time they catch
     me after a Party.</p>
   </sp>
   <stage>Mrs Montgomery: FitzHoward</stage>
   <stage>Curtain.</stage>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>