<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L1434">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Mazeppa; or, The Wild Horse of Tartary. TEI edition</title>
    <author>Milner, H.M.</author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>TEI conversion</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor>
    <idno type="LAE">L1434</idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives
      all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which is believed to be in the public
      domain. You may copy, modify, distribute and perform this work freely. </licence>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="origin" n="96.9"><author>Milner, H.M.</author><title type="main" n="mazeppa"
      >Mazeppa; or , The Wild Horse of Tartary</title><title type="sub">A Romantic Drama in three
      acts</title><title type="source" n="#EN">Dramatised from Lord Byron's Poem</title><extent>52
       pp<measure type="pp" quantity="51"/>
      <measure type="spCount" quantity="362"/>
      <measure type="spvCount" quantity="11"/>
      <measure type="txWords" quantity="14661"/>
      <measure type="spWords" quantity="10867"/>
      <measure type="stWords" quantity="3794"/>
     </extent>
     <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 96, No. 1434</title><idno type="nic"
      >N02530</idno></bibl>
    <bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref
      target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uiuo.ark:/13960/t6h183955">UIU from HT</ref></bibl>
    <listEvent>
     <event type="firstPerf" when="1831-04-04" source="textNic" where="Amphitheatre">
      <desc>Premiered at Royal Amphitheatre Easter Monday 1831</desc>
     </event>
    </listEvent>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>

  <profileDesc>
   <!--L 3 DramaDrama R.D. DRAMA-->
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#sizeL"/>
    <catRef target="#act3"/>
    <catRef target="nic:R.D."/>
    <keywords>
     <term>DRAMA</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
   <particDesc>
    <listPerson>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M1">
      <persName type="role">The Castellan of Laurinski</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="39">Cas.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="24">Cast.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M2">
      <persName type="role">Premislas, Count Palatine</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="21">Pre.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M3">
      <persName type="role">Rudzoloff, Chamberlain of the Household</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="18">Rud.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M4">
      <persName type="role">Drolinsko</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="52">Dro.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M5">
      <persName type="role">Officer</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Offi.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M6">
      <persName type="role">Sentinel</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Sen.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_F7">
      <persName type="role">Olinska, Daughter of the Castellan</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="32">Oli.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_F8">
      <persName type="role">Agatha, her Nurse</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="9">Aga.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_F9">
      <persName type="role">Zemila</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M10">
      <persName type="role">Knights, Officers, Guards, Heralds, Domestics, Ladies,
       &amp;c.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M11">
      <persName type="role">Abder Khan, King of Tartary</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="34">Abd.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M12">
      <persName type="role">Mazeppa, his son, under the name of Cassimer</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="28">Maz.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M13">
      <persName type="role">Thamar, a conspiring Chieftain</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="21">Tha.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M14">
      <persName type="role">Zemba</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="34">Zem.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M15">
      <persName type="role">Kadac</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="8">Kad.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M16">
      <persName type="role">Koscar</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Koscar.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="16">Kos.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_F17">
      <persName type="role">Oneima</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="9">One.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_F18">
      <persName type="role">Shepherdess</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Shepherdess.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_M19">
      <persName type="role">Chieftains, Warriors, Priests, Shepherds, &amp;c.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="3">First E.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="3">Second E.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Chief.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">First Shepherdess.</persName>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="L1434_Mult">
      <persName type="spkr" n="3">All.</persName>
      <persName type="spkr" n="1">Chorus.</persName>
     </person>
    </listPerson>
   </particDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2026-01-11">Standardize header components</change>
   <change when="2026-01-10">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change>
   <change when="2025-11-02">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change>
   <change when="2025-09-07">Fix @who values</change>
   <change when="2025-09-07">Metadata updated from new catalogue</change>
   <change when="2025-06-03">Header confected</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <pb n="1"/>

  <front>
   <pb n="3"/>
   <div type="liminal">
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/L1434-frontispiece.png"/>
     <head><hi>Mazeppa</hi>. Help! help! for heaven's sake release me! <hi>Act II. Scene
      III</hi>.</head>
    </figure>
   </div>
   <pb n="4"/>
   <titlePage>
    <titlePart type="main">Mazeppa; or, The Wild Horse of Tartary.</titlePart>
    <titlePart type="sub">A Romantic Drama, in Three Acts</titlePart>
    <byline>Dramatized from Lord Byron’s Poem, By <docAuthor>HENRY M. MILNER</docAuthor></byline>
    <titlePart type="desc">With an illustration and remarks, by D - G.</titlePart>
    <docImprint>Thomas Hailes Lacy, Theatrical publisher, London.</docImprint>
   </titlePage>
   <pb n="5"/>
   <div type="liminal">
    <head>Remarks</head>
    <head>Mazeppa.</head>
    <p> Lord Byron is a great and an original genius; he has a depth of thought and a force of
     expression that are truly admirable. In aiming at too much conciseness, he is often harsh and
     obscure, while his artificial pauses, his rapid and sometimes unnatural transitions, give to
     his poetry an air of pedantry and affectation. Upon many occasions he is exquisitely simple and
     pathetic ; his simile of the <hi>Kashmeer Butterfly</hi>, and that fine passage, "<hi>He who
      hath bent him o’er the dead,</hi>” cannot easily be paralleled. But it is in “<title>Childe
      Harold</title>” (the greatest of all his works), that the genius of Lord Byron shines most
     conspicuous—his lamentations over the ruins of Greece, his passionate exhortations to spare the
     last relics of her ancient grandeur, and his just and generous indignation against our modern
     vandal, for despoiling her of what the barbarians themselves held sacred, are the very soul of
     pathos and poetry. In proportion as we admire exalted genius, we lament its wanton
     prostitution: the mass of obscenity and profaneness which Lord Byron has bequeathed to
     posterity is now become a question between him and his Creator. He lived too long for his own
     fame—we cannot say “ He should have died hereafter,” unless (like <hi>Lord Rochester</hi>) it
     had been to leave on record his deep contrition for having poisoned the minds of future
     generations. The following character of Lord Byron as a poet, was written before he had
     inflicted upon the world that witty, but scandalously immoral work, "<title>Don Juan</title>
     :”—
     <l>“The town is pleas’d when Byron will rehearse, </l>
     <l>And finds a thousand beauties in his verse; </l>
     <l>So fix’d his fame, that write whate’er he will, </l>
     <l>The patient public most admire it still; </l>
     <l>Yes,—though bereft of half his force and fire, </l>
     <l>They still must read—and, dozing, must admire ; </l>
     <l>While you and I, who stick to common sense, </l>
     <l>To genius, taste, and wit, have no pretence.</l>
     <pb n="6"/>
     <l>Throughout the whole we toil to understand</l>
     <l> Where’er we tread—'tis strange, 'tis foreign land</l>
     <l> Nay, half the thoughts and language of the strain</l>
     <l> Require a glossary to make them plain.</l>
     <l> Beauties there are, which, candour bids me own,</l>
     <l> Atone for these—for more than these atone :</l>
     <l> Beauties, which e’en the coldest mast admire —</l>
     <l> Quick, high-wrought passion—true poetic fire—</l>
     <l> Bold, energetic language—thoughts sublime—</l>
     <l> And all the artful cadences of rhyme.”</l><note place="foot">"The Modern Dunciad"</note>
    </p>
    <p> The story of Mazeppa we learn from two sources— Voltaire’s History of Charles XII., and
     Lesur’s “<title>Histoire des Kosaques</title>.” Lord Byron has rendered it familiar to any
     reader of poetry—Mazeppa is introduced relating romantic adventures to the royal Swede, after
     the battle of Pultowa. The vanquished monarch, wounded and reclined at the foot of a tree,
     surrounded by his warriors, had singled out the brave Tartar and his steed as objects of
     peculiar admiration for their prowess in ‘‘ pricking over flood or field,’’ when Mazeppa,
     remembering the <hi>school</hi> in which he had acquired his skill in horsemanship, drops an
     expression that raises the curiosity of Charles, who puts to the ‘‘ old Hettman” a question
     that produces the recital. Lord Byron confines his narrative to Mazeppa’s intrigue with the
     beautiful young wife of a Polish count, the discovery of their amours, the revenge of the
     jealous husband, who sentences the Tartar to be lashed to the back of a wild horse, and left to
     his fate—the description of that perilous journey, his rescue by the Cossacks, and subsequent
     good fortune. All these are told in Lord Byron’s wonted strain of eloquence and passion. The
     story winds up with a versification of the ancient motto, ‘<hi>'nil desperandum.</hi>
    </p>
    <p>Mazeppa has found his way to the stage; with the accompaniments of appropriate scenery,
     alternately savage and splendid; gorgeous processions, dresses and decorations; gallant knights
     and ladies fair; banquets, tournaments, and real horses. The story has been considerably varied
     and amplified, to bring these powerful auxiliaries into full play ; and an imposing spectacle
     is the result. Olinska, daughter of the Castellan, is beloved by Mazeppa, who passes under the
     name of Cassimir. Her father has, however, provided a more substantial suitor, in the person of
     the Count Palatine ; who, being too magnificent a potentate to leave his palace
     <pb n="7"/> and lay his coronet at her feet, until his proposals be duly accepted, despatches
     an envoy to propitiate her by proxy. The lady reluctantly consents—the diadem is placed on her
     head—she ascends the nuptial car, when the delighted Count, drawing aside the curtains,
     welcomes his beautiful intended, and in flattering terms explains the cause of his appearance,
     at once so unexpected and gallant. On the eve of the marriage, Mazeppa secretly enters the
     chamber of the Count, defies him to single combat—a battle ensues—the Count is wounded, Mazeppa
     retreats, an alarm is given, he is taken, and the Castellan determines to make him an example
     of signal vengeance. He orders the vile Tartar to be stripped, the fiery untamed steed is led
     forth, Mazeppa is fast bound to his back, Olinska implores pity for him, but in vain; and the
     wild horse, amidst the glare of torches, savage shouts, and beacon-fires, is suddenly released.
     He dashes up mountains, down precipices, fords rivers, devoting his unhappy rider to scorching
     suns, piercing blasts, devouring hunger, and parching thirst. Savage wolves follow in quick
     pursuit and threaten to rend him piecemeal—and a vulture hovers over his head, impatient for
     its expected prey. After an accumulation of horrors, they reach Tartary. The affrighted
     peasants, beholding the wild horse furiously pursuing its course, take it fur the Volpas,
     which, according to a popular superstition, is a demon form that whirls across the wilds of
     Tartary, foreboding death and desolation. A thunderbolt strikes a tree, which falls to the
     ground—at this moment the fiery steed sinks down exhausted—Mazeppa, apparently lifeless,
     extended on its body. Abder Khan, against whom a plot exists, headed by Thamar, a rebel chief,
     to drive him from his throne, enters, and beholds the wounded stranger. What signs and
     characters meet his sight! a miracle has been wrought! the jewelled star, the badge and emblem
     of the tribe— tis Mazeppa, his lost son! This discovery is fatal to the scheme of Thamar, who
     (the Khan being old and childless) had aspired to the regal sway. His dagger must remove this
     obstacle to his anticipated greatness—he successively attempts the life of both father and son,
     but is foiled in his attempts. Mazeppa recovers—recognises his father, whom he has miraculously
     rescued from the dagger of the assassin and is hailed King of Tartary. But he cannot be
     <pb n="8"/> without Olinska—to Poland he must repair. for his mistress, and his majesty
     resolves to accompany his son on. his amorous crusade. Mazeppa remounts the wild horse, which,
     after his late heat, is surprisingly tame, and no longer the terror of grooms and rough-riders.
     Ounce the instrument of torture, it is now the messenger of vengeance. The warlike expedition
     moves off in triumph--reaches Poland, when the king, Mazeppa, and a faithful chief, disguised
     as Tartar peasants, repair to the palace of the Castellan, and are engaged by Drolinski, an
     officious officer of the household, to perform sundry grotesque dances and dextrous feats,
     after the manner of their country, in celebration of the long-delayed nuptials between the
     Count Palatine (who has recovered from his wound) and Olinska, who is brought forth like a lamb
     to the slaughter, her heart being with the horse and his rider. The king contrives to wheedle
     Drolinsko (a huge feeder, a little fellow, and a great fool), out of the keys of the great
     gates of the castle; and a chosen band of warriors, who lie concealed in a neighbouring forest,
     are secretly introduced. The nuptial procession advances with due solemnity ; a barbarous
     ballet is performed; when Mazeppa, rushing forward, forbids the banns. <hi>Who</hi> is the
     daring intruder ?—He throws off his disguise, proclaims his titles—the Poles and Tartars go at
     it pell-mell—Mazeppa wins his bride by force of arms, and the piece concludes amidst
     conflagration and rejoicings. This splendid drama was first produced at the Royal Amphitheatre,
     Westminster, under the management of Messrs. Ducrow and West, Easter, 1831; and is written by
     Mr. Milner, the author of Massaniello. </p>
    <p> It is but common justice to remark how effectively every piece is got up at this theatre.
     The equestrian performances are without parallel in the annals of horsemanship; and the scenery
     and decorations may vie with the proudest metropolitan, </p>
    <signed>D --- G</signed>
   </div>
   <pb n="9"/>
   <div type="costume">
    <head>Costume</head>
    <list>
     <head>POLES</head>
     <item><label>THE CASTELLAN.</label>—Rich dress of the reign of Louis XIV ; —A full-skirted
      tunic of dark blue cloth, superbly embroidered with gold—full trunks of the same, edged with
      lace—russet boots—broad embroidered scarf—orange-coloured belt—high srowned, broad-brimmed
      hat, turned up in front, with brilliant rosette, and profusely trimmed with red
      feathers—yellow gauntlets. </item>
     <item>
      <label>PREMISLAS, COUNT PALATINE</label>.—Similar dress of light blue, embroidered with
      silver—white feathers, silk stockings— white shoes. </item>
     <item>
      <label>CASSIMER.</label>—(Mazeppa, as the page.) White tunic, half full sleeve, puffed,
      slashed with crimson and black velvet, the tunic entirely trimmed with crimson and black
      velvet—white tight pantaloons—white shoes, with crimson rosettes—sbort mantillo worn over the
      left arm, of crimson cloth, trimmed with ermine —octagonal cap of crimson, with hanging pouch. </item>
     <item>
      <label>RUDZOLOFF</label>.—Green embroidered tunic, with scarlet mantillo—tight green
      pantaloons—black short boots—lancer’s cap. </item>
     <item><label> DROLINSKO</label>.—Tight vest of green cloth, trimmed with gold face—enormously
      full breeches of ditto—red stockings—black shoes—red rosettes. </item>
     <item>
      <label>POLISH NOBLES</label>.—Various-coloured tunics, embroidered, and trimmed with
      fur—mantillos, also trimmed with fur—tall chimney-pot caps, with pouches covered with yellow
      cloth, and embroidered and trimmed with fur—tight pantaloons, embroidered boots. </item>
     <item>
      <label>FOR THE TOURNAMENT</label>.—Knights in full and in half armour—Heralds, with heraldic
      coats—the Servants in tunics —Pages, exactly the same as Cassimer—the Pages of Premislas,
      similar, but the colours light blue and green, with white fur. </item>
     <item>
      <label>SOLDIERS.</label>—Tunic-coats trimmed with fur—tall chimney- pot hats, trimmed with
      ditto—modern arms. </item>
     <item>
      <label>OLINSKA.</label>—{First Dress}: A short Polish pelisse of green Velvet, superbly
      trimmed and embroidered with gold, and edged with white fur over a short white dress—Polish
      octagonal cap of the same, with hanging pouch. {Second Dress}: A train-dress of white satin,
      embroidered with deep trimming of fur—brilliant coronet, from which hangs a spacious veil. </item>
     <item>
      <label>AGATHA</label>.—Old-fashioned dress—tight body—full skirt of slate-coloured cloth,
      trimmed with black velvet—white handkerchief over the neck—round cap of black velvet, coming
      with a point over the forehead, and ornamented in the front with jewels, </item>
     <item>
      <label>ZEMILA</label>.—Tight body of scarlet cloth, edged with black fur, and trimmed with
      black——yellow buttons—light blue shirt, with broad red stripe at bottom —blue stockings—square
      topped Polish cap of scarlet, edged with black fur—black tassels. </item>
     <item>
      <label>POLISH LADIES.—</label>As Olinska’s first dress, varying the eolour. </item>
    </list>
    <list>
     <head>TARTARS.</head>
     <item> MAZEPPA.—{First Dress}: Black robe, entirely enveloping the person—black
      helmet—black-red plume. {Second Dress}: Flesh legs,: arms and body—short tight trunks—half
      body of brown cloth. {Third Dress}: White Turkish shirt and trowsers, embroidered and
      spangled—vest, with long broad tabs of pale blue velvet, richly spangled and embroidered with
      silver— shawl-scarf of orange, embroidered and fringed with silver— red boots—full Tartar
      helmet—cap of gold, surmounted with a diadem, and bird of Paradise plumes. {Fourth Dress} :
      Long plain Turkish robe bound round with a sash—plain turban.</item>
     <pb n="10"/>
     <item>
      <label>ABDER KHAN</label>.—First dress: Long shirt of white, hanging full, with embroidery at
      the bottom—green and gold vest, with long broad tabs of dark green velvet, richly embroidered
      in gold— very spacious flowing mantle of white cloth, with a border of green and golf
      embroidery, and gold fringe—very large high turban in white, finished at bottom by a
      laurel-wreath in green foil. {Second dress}: Same as Mazeppa’s last dress. </item>
     <item>
      <label>THAMAR AND CHIEFS</label>. —Vest and fly of black cloth, trimmed with red and
      gold—short full Turkish trunks of black and red stripe, taken up with gold studs—Tartar helmet
      cap, with red crape hanging from it, over the shoulders —red scarf—red sandals—round shield of
      black, with gold edge and bosses. </item>
     <item>
      <label>ELDERS.</label> —Long white robes and turbans. </item>
     <item>
      <label>KOSCAR, KADAC, AND SHEPHERDS.</label>—Fresh legs and arms —sheepskin vests—short trunks
      —conical caps of the same. </item>
     <item>
      <label>ONEIZA AND SHEPHERDESSES.</label>—Skirts of striped and various-coloured linens—capes
      of sheepskin—large conical hats covered with leaves, weeds, &amp;c </item>
    </list>

   </div>

   <performance>
    <head>Cast of the Characters</head>
    <p>As Performed at the Royal Amphitheatre Westminster Bridge, under the Management of Messrs.
     Ducrow and West, on Easter Monday, 1831.</p>

    <castList>
     <head>Poles</head>
     <castItem><role gender="M">The Castellan of Laurinski</role>
      <actor>Mr. Hart</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Premislas, Count Palatine</role>
      <actor>Mr. S Foster</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Rudzoloff, Chamberlain of the Household</role><actor>Mr.
       Lawrence</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Drolinsko</role><actor>Mr. Herring</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Officer</role><actor>Mr. J Smith</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Sentinel</role><actor>Mr. Taylor</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="F">Olinska, Daughter of the Castellan</role><actor>Mrs
      Pope</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="F">Agatha, her Nurse</role><actor>Mrs. Bradley</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="F">Zemila</role><actor>Mrs.Yates</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Knights, Officers, Guards, Heralds, Domestics, Ladies, &amp;c.
      </role>
     </castItem>
    </castList>
    <castList>
     <head>TARTARS.</head>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Abder Khan, King of Tartary</role>
      <actor>Mr. Gomersal</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Mazeppa, his son, under the name of Cassimer</role>
      <actor>Mr. Cartlitch</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Thamar, a conspiring Chieftain</role><actor>Mr. S.
      Smith</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Zemba</role><actor>Mr. Taylor</actor></castItem>
     <castGroup>
      <roleDesc>Tartar Shepherds</roleDesc>
      <castItem><role gender="M">Kadac</role><actor>Mr. Fillingham</actor></castItem>
      <castItem><role gender="M">Koscar</role><actor>Mr. W. West</actor></castItem>
     </castGroup>
     <castGroup>
      <roleDesc>Elders of the People:</roleDesc>
      <castItem>
       <actor>Gough, Montgomery, and Yates</actor></castItem>
     </castGroup>

     <castItem><role gender="F">Oneima</role>
      <actor>Mrs. J. Ducrow</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="F">Shepherdess</role>
      <actor>Mrs. Dawson</actor></castItem>
     <castItem>
      <role gender="M">Chieftains, Warriors, Priests, Shepherds, &amp;c.</role>
     </castItem>
    </castList>
   </performance>
  </front>
  <pb n="11"/>
  <body>
   <head>Mazeppa</head>
   <div type="act">
    <head>Act I.</head>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE I. - <hi>The Court- Yard of the Castle of Laurinski, bounded by the buildings of
       the castle, its moat, and adjacent lake - it is approached by a series of drawbridges, over
       the moat and branches of the lake - in the background, the distant country - castle gates, L.
       3rd E. - two large windows, L., the nearest of which has a practicable balcony, L. S. E. -
       the moon seen to set - lights are observable in the castle windows, which are gradually
       extinguished as the morning advances</hi></head>

     <stage>A Sentinel discovered, pacing the drawbridge, which leads across from R. to L. </stage>
     <stage>Enter Cassimir, cautiously, R. U. E., and crossing to the window, L. S. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Calling softly]</stage> Olinska.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M6">
      <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
      <p><stage>[Halting on the drawbridge, C.]</stage> Ha! who goes there? - No answer?
        <stage>[Cassimir conceals himself behind a buttress, L.]</stage> By the uncertain glimpses
       of the moon, I can distinguish no one -all is silent - it could have been but the wind
       sighing amongst these ancient battlements; whistling along them, as it does through my ribs,
       which (by the time they keep me on the watch) I suppose they think as tough and as
       weatherproof as the walls themselves. I shall take the liberty of making free with the
       porter’s fire, in the hall, for a few moments.</p>
      <stage>[Music. - Exit into the portal, L. U. E.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Advancing from the buttress.]</stage> Olinska! dear Olinska! ‘ere yet the envious
       daylight robs my soul of this sweet privilege, of drinking from thine eyes deep draughts of
       the bright liquid fire, which, as from twin stars of love, streams through my enraptured
       heart, appear, dear life! raise me to that throne of glory monarchs might envy me, Olinska’s
       love.</p>
      <stage>[Olinska appears in the balcony, L. S. E.</stage>
      <pb n="12"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Cassimir! thou here? Hence, hence! wert thou discovered, think how fearfully my father’s
       wrath would fall on the clandestine suitor to his child.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> What can Cassimir dread, ennobled and emboldened by thy love?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> It cannot be a noble or a worthy love, that thus, beneath the mask of night, must steal to
       lay its homage on the shrine.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Dost thou reproach my rash presumption?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> No; but my own unworthy cowardice. Cassimir, I will no more of this; no longer stoop to
       tremblingly conceal affections, in which my soul should glory: no! at my father’s feet, I
       will avow it all - will plead thy gallant services - thy exalted deeds - charge him, as he
       values my happiness or peace, to grant Olinska’s hand where her fond heart is pledged, and
       gain a son who’ll be an honour to his name.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> To thee and to thy love I do commit me! but, rather than see thee sacrificed to another,
       or brook a rival in thy much-prized love, -</p>
      <l>A thousand tyrant fathers I would brave</l>
      <l>From all their wrath my lov’d Olinska save,</l>
      <l>Or earn an early, but an honoured grave.</l>

     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> But see, the dawn advances; the moon has sunk behind yon hoary hills; the glimmering
       lights are one by one expiring; and the hum of busy menials speaks approaching day. Away, my
       love, away!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> May all propitious powers smile down upon the pleadings of thy virtuous love, waft thy
       soft breathings deep to thy father’s heart, and win him to our cause; then should thy doating
       Cassimir, in the broad blaze of day, boast of his bliss, and be all Poland’s envy.</p>
      <stage>[The drum of the guard is heard - Cassimir climbs a buttress and passionately kisses
       Olinska’s hand, then effects his escape, R. S. E. - sound approaches.</stage>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter Sentinel, L. U. E., on the drawbridge - Olinska, after watching Cassimir,
      retires from the balcony.</stage>
     <stage>Enter a Patrol, R. U. E., who crosses the drawbridge to L. U. E., and relieves the
      guard.</stage>
     <stage>Enter Rudzoloff, Drolinsko, and other domestics, from the castle, L, 3rd E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.)</stage> Come; bustle, bustle, you lazy-pated
       <pb n="13"/>varlets! Why, it’s day! broad day! - and is not today to be a remarkable day - a
       glorious day - a day of festivity? - Is there not to be a grand tournament? - are not all the
       neighbouring knights, ladies, esquires, and gentry invited? - Is not an envoy from the Count
       Palatine Premislas expected? - And an’t I expected to take a leading part in all the
       games?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> But what an odd freak of our Lord Castellan to choose such a day as this for the attempt
       to subdue the unbreakable, fiery, wild Tartarian horse, so long the terror of all our grooms,
       and the executioner of so many rough-riders.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Cassimer, softly, R. 3rd E., and listens at the back, C.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Let the Castellan waste no more time, labour, nor life about him; but send the devil on
       all fours back to his native Tartary. I tell you what, godfather, there never was a native of
       that country, whether walking on one pair of legs or two, that ever came to any good by being
       in a better. Look, now, at that young Tartar fellow, Cassimir, picked up, as I have heard, in
       a wood, some eighteen years ago, after one of their barbarous incursions –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> A living contradiction to your assertion; risen by his good qualities to be the favourite
       page, the idol of all the women, and the envy of all the men.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Not of all the men, godfather; for my part, I think his brother, the wild horse, the more
       amiable barbarian of the two. Let my lady beware, or she may find, too late, that she has
       caught a Tartar.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Rushing forward and giving Drolinsko a violent slap on the shoulder.]</stage> What
       means the slave?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Aside]</stage> By all that’s terrible, the Tartar has caught me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> No muttering, sirrah: you spoke of me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(L.) </stage>Did I? - Well, then, I’m sure you must have been delighted to hear the
       complimentary things I said of you. You can’t think, how prodigiously we all shall regret (I
       speak of myself in particular), that your duty must presently take you from us.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> What says the slave?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Why, as you know that my Lady Olinska is going to be married to the Count Palatine
       Premislas, one of the richest and most powerful noblemen in Poland –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> How said you? married, married to another?</p>
      <pb n="14"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Another! what other? - Why, she was never married before, was she?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> A despatch late last night, conveyed to the Castellan’s chamber after he had retired - ay,
       ay, it’s we folks of consequence in the establishment that come at the earliest intelligence
       - bless your heart, the envoy is expected to-day, to make the formal proposal to my lady.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Against this blow support me, heaven! She never will, she never shall be his!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Sha’nt she, though? - There, I think, you’ll find yourself mistaken, young fellow; not
       that you need to put yourself into such a taking about it, for 1 dare say, as you are her
       favourite page, she will prevail on the Palatine to make you one of his esquires.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p><stage>[Seizing Drolinsko by the throat, C.]</stage> Wretch! how dare you thus insult me? -
       But no, reptile, thou art not worth my anger. [<stage>Rushes out, R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> I thank you for appreciating me so justly. Godfather, mark my words, that man will never
       come to any good. Oh, that the Castellan would clap him on the back of his brother devil, the
       Tartarian horse, and send them off to Tartary, or Tartarus.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Tush, fool! the Lady Olinska approaches - away, to speed the preparations for the
       festival. -</p>
      <stage>[Music. Rudzoloff drives Drolinsko out, who has hardly recovered from the effects of
       his shaking, L, S. E.</stage>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Olinska, with Agatha, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_F8">
      <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
      <p><stage> (L.)</stage> Why, how is it my pretty bird has left her nest so early this morning?
       - And, oh! those downcast eyes and colourless cheeks assure me she must have passed a
       sleepless night.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.)</stage> Oh, I am deeply to be pitied.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F8">
      <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
      <p> Pitied! you, you to be pitied! when there’s nothing talked of through all the castle, but
       your approaching nuptials with a young nobleman so rich and so –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">

      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>Those nuptials never can take place. My heart, my soul, each energy of my existence - all,
       all is Cassimir’s.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F8">
      <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
      <p> Cassimir’s! heavens! a friendless youth, an orphan boy, a foundling Tartar.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> The idol of my fond affections! This very morning, yielding to the prayer of Cassimir, I
       went to make
       <pb n="15"/> an avowal to my father, but judge of my astonishment, my agony, when he
       announced to me that he had solemnly engaged my hand to the Count Palatine, who in the recent
       war had rescued him in battle. You know my cruel situation - judge, condemn me, if you can,
       but you must at least pity the unhappy Olinska. </p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F8">
      <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
      <p> I condemn you! oh, my dear young lady, my bosom can harbour none but the tenderest
       sentiments towards you, nor entertain any wish except to do you service. <stage>[A noise of
        hurried footsteps is heard without, R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Some one approaches - ah, ‘tis he, ‘tis Cassimir! Great heaven, how agitated!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter Cassimir, suddenly, R. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[With suppressed anger.]</stage> Noble lady –</p>
      <stage>[Agatha retires up, R., watching.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(R.C.)</stage> Speak without reserve, Cassimir; my second mother here knows all.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">

      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>Before her, then, pronounce my fate.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Your fate!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Yes: on you, and on this moment, depend the destinies of my life.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> What mean you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> We must fly: the deserts of Tartary, where I first drew breath, offer us an assured
       retreat. Here, where the bonds that unite us are to be torn asunder, have I not the right to
       require of Olinska, who has chosen me for her husband, that she should seek with me, in my
       own country, that happiness which is denied us here?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> How, with barbarians? sworn foes of my country - never, never!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Then let this hated rival tremble.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Listen to me, Cassimir.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> I care not for life; I am ready to sacrifice it but 1 will not perish alone.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F8">
      <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Advancing , R.]</stage> Your father comes; for both your sakes, hide from him your
       tears - Cassimir, away!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - Enter the Castellan, with his suite, including Rudzoloff, from the castle-gate,
      L. 3rd E. - he seems surprised at observing the embarrassment his presence occasions, and
      testifies his astonishment on beholding Cassimir.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Aside, L.]</stage> Cassimir! <stage>[Aloud]</stage> What do you here, Cassimir?</p>
      <pb n="16"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Confused, R.]</stage> My Lord Castellan -</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F8">
      <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Fearing he may betray himself, hastens between him and the Castellan, C.]</stage> My
       lord, Cassimir was just come to - to - to - to request my influence with the Lady Olinska, to
       obtain for him the situation of first esquire with her intended husband.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[The Castellan, with a scrutinizing glance, surveys the lovers, who remain abashed and
      confused.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p><stage> (L.)</stage> This young man’s intrusion on my lady’s privacy –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> It would be your duty to punish, but I am willing to excuse. I call to mind his uniform
       good conduct, his courage, and fidelity, which deserve reward: - I name him officer of
       men-at-arms, whom I am sending to Warsaw, to be incorporated in the royal guard. He will
       depart to-morrow at daybreak.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> My lord, permit me –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Rudzoloff, I rely on you to see my wishes fulfilled. Away, now; and prepare for your
       appearance at the approaching fête.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Enough, my lord.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Exit Cassimir L. S. E., with gestures of submission to the Castellan, and darting
      glances of piercing scrutiny on Olinska - Rudzoloff following.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> I find, by the Count Palatine’s despatch, that this proposed marriage is likewise
       sanctioned by the sovereign himself.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Aside.]</stage> Support me, oh! support me!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> The Count Premislas wished to come, even on the instant, and present to thee his homage;
       but an ancient custom does not permit a Palatine of Poland to offer his vows in person, till
       after a solemn ceremony. The countess’s coronet must be presented to the intended, and she
       return her ring in exchange. From that moment, she is his affianced bride. The envoy of the
       count this day will come on the important mission.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> How, my father! this very day?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Even so. Prepare for his reception, my daughter; obedience should be easy, when honours
       and fortune are its reward.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - Enter an Officer, R. 4th E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M5">
      <speaker>Offi.</speaker>
      <p> My lord, a splendid cavalcade of knights and warriors even now is discerned from the
       battlements
       <pb n="17"/> approaching the castle. By the bearings on the banners, we perceive it is an
       envoy from Count Premislas.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Let him be conducted hither, with all the honour due to his noble master. Bid my pages and
       officers of my household attend me here. Olinska, be mindful of your duty.</p>
      <stage>[Olinska bends in submission - the Officer retires, R. 4th. E.</stage>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Rudzoloff - Pages, including Cassimir, Ladies, and Guards from the castle, at the
      gales, L. 3rd E., and form round the Castellan, Olinska, and Agatha, who advance near the
      front, L.</stage>
     <stage>Enter a Guard of Honour, from the Castle, crossing the back drawbridge from R. U. E. to
      L. U. E.</stage>
     <stage>The Grand Procession</stage>
     <stage>Moves on, from R. 4th E., consisting of Soldiers, Knights, Officers. Ladies, and
      Attendants, who form on the E. side and across the back - a small ornamental car is drawn on
      L. 3rd. E., under the canopy of which is a cushion with a countess’s coronet - the Envoy
      advances, C. - the Castellan leads forward his daughter, and with her takes a position, R. -
      two ladies place a cushion, C., on which Olinska kneels - the Envoy brings forward the
      coronet, and presents it to Olinska - it is received by her attendants, and placed on her head
      - Cassimir anxiously beholds the ceremony - he passes round the back, and takes a situation
      behind Agatha, R. - on Olinska’s receiving the coronet, he expresses rage and despair - the
      Castellan now reminds her to present her ring - with trembling agitation she draws it from her
      finger, and approaches the canopy, Cassimir watching with a degree of intentness wrought up to
      agony - as she drops the ring on the cushion, Count Premislas bursts from the drapery of the
      car, seizes the ring, and advances to the front, C. </stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Starting.]</stage> What do I see?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> The Count Premislas!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Aside.]</stage>
       <stage>(L.)</stage> Down, rebel nature, down!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.)</stage> Pardon me, beautiful Olinska, for not awaiting the sentence which was to
       decide my fate. Had my homage been rejected, I should have quitted the castle without
       intruding upon your presence; but, on seeing you accept the diadem, I hastened to receive,
       myself, this precious pledge of happiness. <stage>[Showing the ring.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="18"/>
     <stage>[Music. He takes the hand of Olinska, and kisses it - Cassimir makes a movement, as if,
      in his jealous fury, he would spring upon his happy rival, but is restrained by a sudden
      thought of more effectual vengeance.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Aside, and earnestly to Olinska]</stage> This very night! - vengeance! - death!
        <stage>[Exit, R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Deign to accompany me, count: every thing is prepared to receive you with the honours due
       to him who, becoming my son, will presently have a right to command, where now he is a guest.
       Never could your arrival have been better timed. This day I had prepared a solemn tourney, in
       which the pages of my household and friendly knights will contend in those manly sports which
       form the warrior’s earliest lesson. To this festivity your presence will add a tenfold
       brilliance. Forward, and prepare the arena.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> Count, with the utmost joy, I shall attend you. <stage>[To Olinska.]</stage> Lady, may I
       be honoured with your hand?</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music - He offers his hand to Olinska, who with diffident reluctance yields hers, - The
      procession moves on towards the castle, and the scene closes.</stage>
    </div>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE II. - <hi>A Gothic Apartment in the Castle</hi>.</head>
     <stage>Music. Enter Zemila, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Well; so, my Lady Olinska is going to be married - I wish I was going to be married; for
       then I should no longer be a maid: no, indeed, I’d be a mistress, as my husband would be
       pretty quickly convinced. There’s that lout, Drolinsko, has been casting sheep’s eyes at me
       for months past; but the dolt scarcely knows his own mind, I fancy. There’s but one reason I
       can conceive for having any thing to say to such a numskull: if I married him, he’d save me
       the trouble of making a fool of him, for he’s ready made to my hand. Give me a dashing
       spirited fellow, I say, who would run away with you in spite of fathers, uncles, cousins -
       ay, for the matter of that, in spite of yourself.</p>
      <stage>Song. - Zemila.</stage>
      <l>A lady was woo’d by a knight, it is said.</l>
      <l>Who courted her under a tree;</l>
      <l>And he constantly sighed on her bosom, “Fair Maid,</l>
      <l>Ah! wilt thou be faithful to me?</l>
      <pb n="19"/>
      <l>She sighed back again, as her bosom soft heaved,</l>
      <l>“Sir knight, I must yield to despair, -</l>
      <l>I’d fly to thy arms, as my truth is believ’d,</l>
      <l>Yes, I’d fly with my love, did I dare.”</l>
      <l>Ah! lady love, lady love! quick he return’d,</l>
      <l>“Is it fear only keeps us apart?”</l>
      <l>With tenderest passion his manly breast burn’d.</l>
      <l>Whilst courage and hope swelled his heart.</l>
      <l>His courser was ready; he snatch’d her fair form.</l>
      <l>Away o’er the wild heath to bear,</l>
      <l>And sang, as he gallop’d amidst the loud storm,</l>
      <l>“I not only love thee, but dare!”</l>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Drolinsko, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Meeting Zemila, C.]</stage> Ah! pretty Mistress Zemila, what may you be seeking in
       such a bustle?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p><stage> (L. C.)</stage> No such trash as you; so mind your own business, and let me
       pass.</p>

     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Well, now, for my part, I don’t know what a likely young woman, such as you, can meet more
       suited to her wants and inclinations than a tidy husband.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> A husband! <stage>[Laughing]</stage> Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha! As if, were I inclined for a
       husband, I should for a moment dream of such a thing as you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Such a thing as me! what the devil do you mean by that? Why, what’s the matter with me?
       I’m all right and tight, snug and comfortable, as any young woman could desire.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> No, Drolinsko, you want one very material article to make a man of you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> No, you don’t say so.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Not that it’s so essential to a husband.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Well, I’m glad to hear that, at any rate.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Touching his head.]</stage> You want it here, my poor fellow; empty as a scooped-out
       cocoa-nut shell.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Want it there, do I? Now it strikes me very forcibly, that if I were your husband, you
       would furnish me with something more than I should want there.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Now, if you were anything like such a person as the Tartar, Cassimir –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> The Tartar, Cassimir! Only to hear the women talk. Well, St. Ignatius help their taste, I
       say. He’s a sort of a wild beast; and all the women are weaving nets and meshes to catch him;
       and if they can’t tame him, he’s a wild devil indeed. But I’ve stopped Mr. Cassimir’s pranks
       for a while.</p>
      <pb n="20"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> You stop him, Drolinsko? <stage>[Laughing.]</stage> Ha, ha, ha! that’s an excellent
       joke.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> I don’t think he’ll find it so. The slave had the presumption to intrude on the Lady
       Olinska’s privacy, whilst taking a walk on the terrace of the castle, and even to touch her
       hand.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Like a spirited young fellow, as he is.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> There I caught him - so did her father.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Sneering]</stage> Well?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> The father did not seem inclined to say much; but I gave Mr. Tartar pretty plainly to
       understand, that if ever he attempted the like liberty again, he would incur a pretty
       considerable portion of my displeasure.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Derisively.]</stage> Your displeasure! Poor, poor Drolinsko.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> I’d a good mind to give him a bit of a shaking, then.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> You give Cassimir a shaking! why, you’d shake in your shoes if he did but raise a
       finger.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> I say, Zemila, how provokingly beautiful you do look, to be sure. Do you know, I should so
       like to –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Well, then, why don’t you take courage and try.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Egad! that’s a pretty fair invitation, and here I go.</p>
      <stage>[He attempts to kiss her, she slaps his face.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Smack for smack, my fine fellow, all over the world, is fair play, you know.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> That’s what you call giving a modest young man proper encouragement, I suppose.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Recollect, Drolinsko, that till a recruit has learned to stand fire, he’s never fit for
       the field of action.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Rudzoloff, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(R. C.)</stage> Come, come, none of your billing and cooing here; all should be bustle
       and activity. The tournament is about to take place; the Lady Olinska is to crown the
       conqueror, and the presence of Count Premislas inclines my lord to wish the entertainment
       more brilliant even than he had intended.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(L. C.)</stage> Lovely mistress Zemila, were it your task to crown the conqueror, I
       feel that I should overthrow all before me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> (C.) Then it must be with a crown of thistle and dandelion, ornamented with a pair of
       ass’s ears.</p>
      <stage>[A trumpet heard without</stage>
      <pb n="21"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Hark, that’s the first signal; hasten to take your place.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> My soul’s in arms, and eager for –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> The encounter?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> No; for the sumptuous banquet that is to take place afterwards.</p>
     </sp>
     <spGrp>
      <head>Trio - Zemila, Drolinsko, and Rudzoloff</head>
      <sp who="#L1434_M14">
       <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
       <l>Oh! ‘midst the clash of war’s alarms.</l>
       <l>Delightful hurry scurry,</l>
       <l>Where ‘midst of trophies, plumes, and arms, </l>
       <l>The men each other worry.</l>
       <l>How high each damsel’s bosom beats, </l>
       <l>How beam her sparklers bright.</l>
       <l>To think, with all their gallant feats, </l>
       <l>For her the heroes fight.</l>
      </sp>
      <sp who="#L1434_M4">
       <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
       <l>No doubt, for those who get the best, </l>
       <l>‘Tis very pretty fun,</l>
       <l>But, ah! the thought that fills my breast, </l>
       <l>Is care of number one.</l>
       <l>What silly sport for fighting elves.</l>
       <l>Into each other pitching, -</l>
       <l>They’d better pitch into themselves</l>
       <l>The comforts of the kitchen.</l>
      </sp>
      <sp who="#L1434_M3">
       <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
       <l>Oh, the thought of martial glory</l>
       <l>Warms the breast and fires the heart.</l>
       <l>Though my war-worn locks are hoary</l>
       <l>I could play a soldier’s part.</l>
       <l>Still the falchion could I wield,</l>
       <l>Still enjoy the trumpet’s clang;</l>
       <l>Still my heart to beauty yield.</l>
       <l>And each haughty rival bang.</l>
      </sp>

      <stage>All together.</stage>
      <sp who="#L1434_M14">
       <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
       <l>Ever still must martial glory</l>
       <l>Tend a woman’s heart to win:</l>
       <l>Still they love a warrior’s story</l>
       <l>Though they dread the battle’s din.</l>
      </sp>
      <sp who="#L1434_M4">
       <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
       <l>It’s very well to talk of glory,</l>
       <l>Something better I would win.</l>
       <l>With a jovial feast before me</l>
       <l>I but wish a good tuck in.</l>
      </sp>
      <sp who="#L1434_M3">
       <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
       <l>Still my heart beats high for glory</l>
       <l>Fresher laurels yet I’d win;</l>
       <l>As I tell each martial story.</l>
       <l>Fight the battle o’er again.</l>
      </sp>

     </spGrp>
     <stage>[Exeunt, L.</stage>
    </div>
    <pb n="22"/>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE III: <stage>The Grand Arena, prepared for the Tournament, surrounded on three sides
       by an elevated gallery - an arched entrance, C. F. under the gallery - near the front, L., a
       canopied couch.</stage></head>
     <stage>[Music - The galleries are filled with spectators - the limits of the arena are
      maintained by Heralds and mounted Men at arms - in the centre are drawn up the Pages and
      Knights, proposed combatants - Cassimir is amongst them - the couch is occupied by the
      Castellan, his daughter, and Count Premislas, surrounded by their Attendants.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> My friends, display before us your address and courage - these noble sports are the image
       of war - learn from them to defend your prince and country. My daughter will crown the
       conqueror - let the signal be given for the games to begin.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music. - The Castellan sits - Rudzoloff makes a signal, on which a trumpet sounds, and
      the respective champions take their stations - first, a small sword combat, between two of the
      Pages - then a tilt of mounted and armed Knights, with spear and battle-axe, of whom Cassimir
      is one -then a sword combat on horseback, between Cassimir and his opponent - in both of these
      Cassimir is successful - then a broadsword combat of four, in which Cassimir is also the
      victor - the conquerors advance towards the Castellan.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Cassimir , it is with pleasure I behold you the victor: I have before remarked your
       courage and address; I have distinguished you from the crowd of my pages: merit always thus
       my favour, and new rewards will be the result. The evening’s shadows, now gathering o’er the
       valley, remind us to conclude our sports, and taste the banquet’s joys. Now let the trumpet
       speak the contest o’er, and, in the joyous goblet’s cheering draught, let each pledge his
       antagonist in sincerity and friendship.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[The Victors are crowned by Olinska with laurel - Cassimir receives also a scarf - they
      then approach a small table, which has been prepared - each takes a goblet of wine, and as
      they are in the act of drinking, the scene closes.</stage>
    </div>
    <pb n="23"/>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE IV: <stage>A Gallery of the Castle, conducting to the sleeping-rooms - an entrance
       from the armoury, L.</stage></head>
     <stage>Music. - Enter Count Premislas, L., preceded and followed by his pages and Gentlemen of
      his household, some of whom bear flambeaux - one takes his hat, another his mantle, which he
      lays over the back of a chair - a third places his sword on a small table.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p><stage> (C.)</stage> You may now retire - I dispense with all further service for the
       evening. <stage>[Pages, &amp;c. retire, R., the Count sits on a chair, R.C.]</stage> I shall
       presently be united to Olinska - called by my sovereign to one of the first offices of the
       state, love and fortune unite to crown my wishes; still the extraordinary emotion of Olinska
       haunts me; her disturbed looks, her eyes moistened with tears - what would be her hand
       without her heart? - Perhaps some knight more blessed than I – <stage>[Rises and advances,
        C.]</stage> But no, Olinska has been brought up in retirement: her <gap/> will be thoroughly
       her husband’s.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - Enter Cassimir, C. F., disguised in a black helmet and black plumes, the vizor
      closed, and a long black mantle - he stands before Premislas, as he is turning towards his
      chamber.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Seizing his sword.]</stage> Who art thou?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.) </stage>Thine enemy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p><stage> (C.) </stage>How entered you this castle?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> What matter’s that to thee?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> What is thy will?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Thy death.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> Wouldst thou be my murderer?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> No; I would meet thee in equal encounter of man to man.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Haughtily.]</stage> Thy name?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">

      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Thou shalt know that when thou art conquered.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> This arrogance –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Befits a jealous and offended man.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> What can you be?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Your rival.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[With anxiety.]</stage> Beloved?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Till yesterday I believed so.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Exultingly.]</stage> But to-day thou findest that the beautiful Olinska accords to me
       the preference.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> Not to thee, but to thy honours and thy titles.</p>
      <pb n="24"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> Dar’st thou insult me?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> I have told thee but the truth; my sword shall do the rest.</p>

     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> Rash intruder! Think’st thou a Palatine will deign to measure swords with an unknown,
       doubtless unworthy of that honour.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p> My sword shall teach thee whether I be worthy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> Hence, or my servants shall chastise thy boldness. <stage>[Proceeds to ring a bell,
        L.]</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Presenting two pistols, C.]</stage> One word, one gesture, and I stretch thee at my
       feet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> Coward! were our arms but equal –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Laying aside his pistols, and drawing a sword.]</stage> They are so. Behold,
        <stage>[Throws open the mantle.]</stage> my bosom is unarmed - I wear this helmet for
       concealment, not protection. Aim at my heart - it has no defence but courage and this good
       sword.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music. - Pressed by the attack of Cassimir, Premislas places himself on his defence, R.
      C., and a combat ensues - unable to resist the vigour of Cassimir’s onset, Premislas is
      wounded, and falls.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p> I yield.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Resuming his mantle.]</stage> I am revenged.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music. - A tumult is heard without - a crowd of the Count’s attendants and other of the
      Castellan household rush on, headed by Drolinsko, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> I tell you, the unknown, who stole the armour, is in that gallery - see, behold him -
       there, there he is.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Those of the Count’s household perceiving him fainting in the chair, R. C., rush to his
      assistance – the others are about to rush on Cassimir, who stands near the entrance to the
      armoury, but are kept in check by his presenting his pistols – he rushes off by the passage
      leading to the armoury, L. S. E., and they follow him.</stage>
     <stage>Enter the Castellan, Rudzoloff, and other Attendants, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Great heaven! The Palatine assassinated. <stage>[Goes to him.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p><stage>[Partially reviving] </stage> A rival - vengeance!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> You shall obtain it; and whoever the murderer may prove, it shall be terrible.</p>
      <stage>[Music. - Two discharges of pistols heard without, L. S.</stage>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Drolinsko, running, L.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> We’ve got him! he’s taken! he’s taken!</p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="25"/>
     <stage>The other Servants now come in, L. S. E. surrounding Cassimir, still concealed by the
      vizor and mantle - he shakes them off, and quietly takes his station, L. C., the Servants
      behind him.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Pointing to Cassimir.]</stage> That is the assassin.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Remove the mantle that conceals the wretch.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music. - As the Servants are about to do so, Cassimir casts off both the mantle and the
      helmet.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_Mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p>Cassimir!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> My suspicions were, then, true - let him die <stage>[The Servants of Count Premislas are
        about to spring on Cassimir.]</stage> Hold! reserve him for the punishment inflicted on
       rebel slaves. Lead in the Count - let every aid be lavished to restore him.
        <stage>[Approaching the Count, and grasping his hand.]</stage> End as it may, of this, at
       least, be sure, such vengeance shall expiate the outrage, as my indignant soul in fury
       dictates, in lamentation o'er its dearest friend. <stage>[The Count’s Followers support him
        off, R.]</stage> Tremble, ungrateful miscreant, at the punishment reserved for outraged
       hospitality. Lead the vile Tartar hence - strip him of that garb he has degraded - let not
       the arms of my house be sullied by adorning a traitor who raises his assassin arm against my
       friend, under the very roof that gives him shelter. Lead out the fiery untamed steed -
       prepare strong hempen lashings round the villain’s loins - let every beacon-fire on the
       mountain’s top be lighted, and torches, like a blazing forest, cast their glare across the
       night. This moment let my vengeance be accomplished - away. <stage>[Music. - Exit the
        Castellan, followed by his principal Officers, R, - Cassimir is dragged out by the servants,
        L.</stage>
      </p>
     </sp>
    </div>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE V: Part of the Gardens of the Castellan.</head>
     <stage>Music. - Enter Rudzoloff and Zemila, R., meeting - Enter Drolinsko, L., running, and his
      clothes in great disorder.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Well, Drolinsko, what dismal fate has happened to you now?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Dismal fate, indeed! the dismal fate has not happened to me; but it might have done - I am
       perpetually led into predicaments by my unquenchable courage.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Or your unquenchable thirst, which, Drolinsko?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> There, his lordship has ordered them to bring out the wild Tartar horse, and strap
       Cassimir to his back. Lord love you, there stood the poor wretches
       <pb n="26"/>about him, - not one of them had courage to approach him; but my eagerness for
       difficult adventures inspired me - I approached the infuriated monster, and seized him by the
       mane, when he turned round, and savagely tore –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Tore! my poor dear fellow, are you seriously hurt? what did he tear?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Why, he tore what I won’t venture to mention. <stage>[Turns round and discovers his
        small-clothes torn.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music - Enter two Servants who cross from L. to R. - one of them appears
      wounded.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Hasten to my lord, entreat him to forego his purpose, ere half his household is
       destroyed.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Why, truly, it seems as if the wild horse would make the castle an hospital. His
       countryman, Mr. Cassimir, began that game; but, thank heaven, we are likely to get rid of
       them both, now. I’ve often said the best thing our Lord Castellan could do, would be to bind
       them back to back, and set them off to their own country together. Egad! if we don’t run, we
       shall miss the sight, and the opportunity of wishing our Tartar friends good- by for
       ever.</p>
      <stage>[Music. - Exeunt running, L.</stage>
     </sp>
    </div>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE VI. - <stage>The Outer Terrace of the Castle, overlooking a tract of desolate
       country, composed of precipitous mountain ridges, abounding with cataracts - the rocky
       pathway crosses a stupendous waterfall, by a slight rustic bridge, and is finally lost in a
       chain of lofty eminences stretching into the distance.</stage></head>
     <stage>Music. - Enter the Castellan, Rudzeloff, Drolinsko, and several of his suite, male and
      female, R. S. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(R.C.) </stage>Is my will obeyed, and the wild horse secured?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> All is as my lord commanded.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Bring forth the miscreant.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - Olinska rushes in, R. S. E., followed by all the females of her household, and
      approaches the Castellan, R. - at the same time Cassimir is dragged on by several of the
      household, L. 3rd E.- Cassimir stands L. C., the Servants stretching semi-circularly from the
      centre to L. corner.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Throwing herself at her father’s feet, L. C.]</stage> Oh! my father, pardon for him
       who saved your daughter’s life.</p>
      <pb n="27"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> (C.) Unworthy girl! all power on earth were ineffectual to assuage my vengeance.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - Enter Count Premislas, followed by his Officers, L., - Olinska and the females
      instantly surround him, kneeling at his feet, as if entreating his interference, C.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Approaching the Castellan.]</stage> Hold, my lord: from vengeance such as this, even
       my indignant bosom shrinks with horror.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> You plead in vain. - Bring forth the untamed steed. <stage>[Music. - The horse is brought
        forward, L. 3rd E., by three or four Grooms, who, with difficulty restrain him - he is led
        to the centre - Cassimir indignantly bursts from those who hold him, and, advancing to the
        front, C., surveys the horse - the spectators, in alarm, run to the corners, front.]</stage>
       Now bind the traitor on his back; let scorching suns and piercing blasts, devouring hunger,
       and parching thirst, with frequent bruises and ceaseless motion, rend the vile Tartar
       piecemeal.</p>
      <stage>[Music. - Cassimir is now bound to the horse’s back, C.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Yet, dearest father, in mercy hear me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[On the horse C.]</stage>, Plead not for me, Olinska, perish as I may, it is
       sufficient glory that I die for thee.</p>

     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Now launch the traitor forth, and let the story of his fate strike terror throughout
       Poland!</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - The horse is released, and immediately rushes off with Cassimir, R., 3rd E. -
      he presently reappears on the first range of hills, from L. to R., all the spectators rushing
      to the L., and as he crosses again from R. to L., they take the opposite side - when he has
      reached the third range of hills, they commence pursuing him up the hills, and as he
      progresses, they follow - when he has disappeared in the extensive distance, the whole range
      of hills is covered by the Servants, Females, Guards, and Attendants, shouting, waving their
      arms and torches, forming an animated tableau - Olinska, who has fainted, is supported by
      Agatha and Premislas in the front, whilst the Castellan expresses exultation, completing the
      picture, lighted by the glare of torches and the red beacon-fires, on which the drop
      falls.</stage>
    </div>
    <trailer>END OF ACT I.</trailer>
   </div>
   <pb n="28"/>
   <div type="act">

    <head>ACT II.</head>

    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE I: <hi>Moving panorama of the course of the Dneiper River, running from L. U. E, to
       R. U. E. - on the flat is seen its banks, with a tract of wild country - a tremendous storm
       of thunder and lightning, hail and rain.</hi></head>

     <stage>Music. Mazeppa discovered, L. S. E., on the wild horse, stopping a few moments,
      apparently from exhaustion, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Exhausted nature for a moment stays his furious course. Eternal heaven! where will these
       horrors end? Oh! would I were released from suffering, if but in the endless calm of death.
       Ah! again he urges on his wild career. <stage>[The wild horse gallops off with Mazeppa, R. -
        Music, - The storm abates, the sun rises, and the panorama begins to move - the horse, still
        bearing Mazeppa fastened to his back, is seen wading up the stream, from R. to L.]</stage>
       Ah! how refreshing is the cool stream to my racked, fevered limbs. Ah! could my parched lips
       but catch its moisture, it would sooth the burning thirst that preys upon me. But here, like
       Tantalus, I feel the limpid luxury wash past my mouth, whilst my arid throat is denied the
       sweet relief. <stage>[Music. - A group of wolves is seen on the opposite- banks, as if
        watching and pursuing the horse and Mazeppa.]</stage> Though nigh exhausted by the strong
       exertion, yon group of ravening wolves scare the affrighted beast from off the bank - already
       have their gnashing teeth been buried in my flesh; and I could almost wish again to feel
       their horrid grip - if perchance it might free me from the cruel thongs that eat into my
       flesh, and squeeze my swollen veins almost to bursting. - Surely, the power of the maddened
       brute must be well-nigh exhausted. Though my dim sight imperfectly distinguishes, it seems as
       if the current was so strong as to impede his course - these waters, then, shall be my
       welcome and see <stage>[Music - An enormous vulture is seen hovering above him.]</stage> Yon
       horrid bird of prey, now hovering over its destined victim, forewarns me that my torments
       soon shall end. - It brings me, too, the sacred consolation that I have reached my native
       Tartary, to which its form and plumage are peculiar, and so shall perish where I first drew
       breath - welcome, eternal rest! Olinska! dear Olinska! thy well-loved name the last that
       murmurs
       <pb n="29"/> from my expiring lips, and may thy angel prayers waft my racked soul to regions
       of repose and peace.</p>
      <stage>[Music. - The wild horse bears off Mazeppa, L. U. E.</stage>
     </sp>
    </div>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE II: <hi>A Rude Tartar Landscape - a marshy thicket interspersed with shepherds’
       huts.</hi></head>
     <stage>Enter Oneiza, through the wood, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_F17">
      <speaker>One.</speaker>
      <p> What, ho! Koscar! Koscar! The sun mounts high in the heavens, and chides thy
       sluggishness.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Koscar.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Without.]</stage> Hilloa! here.</p>
      <stage>Enter Koscar, R.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> Ah! my sweet sister, thou abroad so early?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F17">
      <speaker>One.</speaker>
      <p> Our gods preserve thee. Some hours since I led my herd to a secluded track amidst the
       mountain heights that look towards Poland – <stage>[Looking off, R.]</stage> but here comes
       Kadac.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Kadac, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_F17">
      <speaker>One.</speaker>
      <p>What has raised thee, friend, from thy couch, so soon?</p>
     </sp>

     <sp who="#L1434_M15">
      <speaker>Kad.</speaker>
      <p> Oh! I have been to pay my morning tribute to our prophet king; to beg his paternal
       blessing, and ask the assistance of his potent prayers.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> Prophet-king! well, it’s a strange mixture of trades. Most kings, I reckon, find enough to
       do without wandering out at nights upon the mountain tops, counting the stars, and seeking
       wondrous visions.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F17">
      <speaker>One.</speaker>
      <p> Fie, Koscar! fie! how can you suffer your rude tongue to speak thus irreverently of him,
       whom all our tribes revere. Ever was AbderKhan a mild and gracious monarch; but since that
       fatal time, when on the fields of Poland he lost his only son, his mind has taken a strange
       and solemn turn - he is inspired by the gods of Tartary - in wondrous visions, its future
       destiny’s unfolded to his view.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.)</stage> Visions, say you? Oh! I, too, see visions, if it come to that. - This
       very morn, I have beheld a warning vision - horrible! most horrible!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F17">
      <speaker>One.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(R.C.)</stage> Heavens! what do you mean, Koscar?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> Why, if my two eyes have the slightest knowledge of the business attached to their
       situation in my head, I have this very morning seen the Volpas.</p>
      <pb n="30"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F17">
      <speaker>One.</speaker>
      <p> You terrify me out of my senses Koscar - what can you mean?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> I saw him sitting, or rather lying, on a furious wild horse, that bore him with more than
       lightning speed from rock to rock, o’er precipice, through stream, and plunged with him into
       the deep and foaming torrent of the Dnieper.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M15">
      <speaker>Kad.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(L. C.)</stage> Let us hasten to the Khan, and ask his counsel; for, by our old
       traditions, the appearance of the Volpas has ever been the harbinger of wretchedness to our
       Tartar tribes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F17">
      <speaker>One.</speaker>
      <p> Hark, hark! What mean those sounds?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M15">
      <speaker>Kad.</speaker>
      <p> It is the trampling of a furious steed.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Looking off, L. S. E.]</stage> Ay, with more than mortal vigour. It is himself - the
       Volpas, the awful, the accursed Volpas, who this way wings his flight. - Hence, sister,
       hence! The Volpas! The Volpas! <stage>[Exeunt, in the utmost terror R.</stage></p>
      <stage>Music. - Enter the Wild Horse at full gallop, with Mazeppa, L. S. E, - he rushes
       across, and exit, R. S. E.</stage>
      <stage>Enter Thamar, with Tartar Chiefs and Soldiers, R.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> I came to seek our king: knowest thou where I may find him, gallant Zemba?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Our king? Our prophet, rather say, my chief.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Ay, doating driveller; when he must needs take up one character, ‘twere well he had laid
       down the other - a warlike people are not to be ruled by a seer of visions.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> At least they get little by it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> From a race of warriors we are descended to a nation of vile shepherds; living upon the
       scanty sustenance our herds afford, or labour can extort from our rude sterile soil. When has
       the spoil of any neighbouring people yielded glory to our arms, or booty to our soldiers? Oh!
       for the days when Polish and Hungarian wealth was the just prey of those whose valour best
       deserved it!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> No, ever since he lost his infant son, he dreads the very name of Poland.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> And spends his time in idle reveries, and superstitious dreams of inspiration. Not content
       to be obeyed, he likewise would be worshipped.</p>
      <pb n="31"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> So he is almost, by the poor simple shepherds; but for us warriors –</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> You cannot but despise such driveling imposture - you shall not longer be the victims of a
       cheat to whom your judgment never could be dupe. The hour is at hand when the Tartarian
       sceptre shall be snatched by an arm that’s bold enough to seize, and strong enough to wield
       it. This very day I will, in the name of our assembled tribes, demand that he proclaim his
       successor. There is but one he dare to name, and once pronounced his heir, he soon shall find
       I will not tardily await the enjoyment of the power already dropping from his doating
       hand.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter hastily Koscar and Kadac, R.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p><stage> (R. C.)</stage> Help! help! save me! save me!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.)</stage> How, now? What ails the man?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> I’ve seen him! I’ve seen him! I am sure I have.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Whom have you seen, idiot?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> Why, the Volpas, to be sure, the dreaded Volpas.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Driveller! what mean you?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> I mean, my lord, that I believe the evidence of my own two eyes: I saw him on a horse
       about twice as big as an elephant, who leaped from one rock to another, a league apart - the
       whirlwind of dust that he kicked up reached to the skies - </p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Dolt! weary not thus my patience; but assemble your shepherd tribes here in the valley:
       our aged Khan has a revelation to make of the utmost importance - obey me quickly, and await
       your monarch’s bidding.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> We shall do so, my lord - he is our friend and our protector; and if anything can oppose
       the fury of the persecuting demon,’twill be the efficacy of his prayers.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Ha! I see he approaches. Haste you to bring your comrades, whilst I assemble our choicest
       warriors to hear from his inspired lips the future destiny of Tartary.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music - Exeunt Thamar and Soldiers, L., Koscar and Kadac, R.</stage>
    </div>
    <pb n="32"/>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE III: <hi>The Plains or Steppes of Tartary, bounded by rocky eminences, the last of
       a chain that separates it from Poland - rocky pathways, broken by cataracts, over which are
       thrown rude alpine bridges - and in the foreground are marshy plants, brushwood, and a few
       scattered trees</hi>.</head>

     <stage>Music. - Shepherds discovered reposing, whilst their steeds are grazing.</stage>
     <stage>Enter AbderKhan, R. U. E., attended by Three Elders.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Stopping on one of the mountain eminences, R. C.]</stage> Hail, glorious orb of day,
       that slowly rising from wide ocean’s bosom, sheddest thy bright beams over animated nature,
       awaking all its creatures into life, and chasing night’s dark shadows far away: what fearful
       scenes those shadows have portrayed to my inspired vision. Portentous horrors hanging thick
       around, menacing this devoted land with blood - yet, even in my dream, a better star rose
       o’er our clouded fortunes, and, like the blessed sun, dispersed the gloom of horror, and
       spread light and peace around.</p>
      <stage>Music, - He advances to the front, C., attended by the Elders.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M19">
      <speaker>First E.</speaker>
      <p> How fares our honoured master? What anxious cares have occupied his thoughts through the
       past night, and from his tent led his adventurous steps?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Deep thoughts for my loved people’s welfare: and, oh! in those wild regions 1 have
       visited, such mighty revelations from the skies have on my wrapped soul descended -</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M19">
      <speaker>Second E.</speaker>
      <p> What means my honoured lord?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Methought I saw a fair and lovely bird, the very type of innocence and peace, wing its
       swift light through the expanse of heaven a dark and ravenous eagle darted forth, and quick
       pursued the affrighted helpless wanderer, with eager haste and threatening talons. In its
       distress and woe, the persecuted warbler sought shelter in my bosom, which readily was open
       to receive it; but the destroyer even there assailed its destined prey, and struck its talons
       deep into my heart.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M19">
      <speaker>First E.</speaker>
      <p> Yet be not cast down; for threatened evils often pass away, nor shed one drop of
       bitterness on our protected heads.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Not for myself, I fear, but for my people; for hope and fear to me have been denied since
       my loved
       <pb n="33"/> child was lost. For Tartary alone I live, and would it win her happiness, for
       Tartary with eager joy I’d die.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M19">
      <speaker>Second E.</speaker>
      <p> No, sire, no: yet live to bless thy people.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> But in one hope I live, a hope thou’lt say akin to madness, but which the gods have
       planted in my sorrowing heart, and nourish still with those soft whisperings, breathed from
       the heavens above. Thou sawest me in that hour, Olgar - thou sawest my gleaming scimetar hew
       down myriads of Polish foes, who had surprised our little camp; when my infant was held
       within their grasp, how like a maddened lion my eager rage sought access to their phalanx’s
       centre - once, once, I saw an uplifted dagger gleam against his throat. Gods! how my steel,
       like the fell lightning’s flash, struck through opposing numbers to that monster’s heart. At
       once I saved and lost him - hurried back by overpowered and retreating hosts, I never saw my
       angel babe again.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M19">
      <speaker>Second E.</speaker>
      <p> You yet believe he lives?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> I do, I do! in hallowed visions constantly I see him, my diadem encircling his brow - like
       a celestial halo does that blessed thought shed a bright gleam of comfort o’er my soul - with
       patience I await the hour, assured that I shall see it - Mazeppa shall return, shall be the
       joy of his long- sorrowing sire, and the glory of his rescued people.</p>
      <stage>[Rural Music heard at a distance.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M19">
      <speaker>First E.</speaker>
      <p> See, sire, where the shepherd tribes approach, to lay their morning homage at your
       honoured feet.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Be their humble repast prepared; their simple wants, at least, their king can yet supply,
       and to avert each threatened danger, they shall not need his prayers.</p>

      <stage>[Music. - From a tent, R. S. E., the Elders set out bowls of milk - the rural Music
       approaches.</stage>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter a body of Shepherds, at the back, whilst Thamar and his Warriors advance in the
      front, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p>Sovereign of Tartary, thy people, deeply sympathizing with thy childless loneliness, have
       yet a care for their own future peace and happiness; and, lest the sceptre, which in the
       course of nature must soon drop from thy enfeebled grasp, should prove a source of discord
       and disaster, they expect that thou wilt name one of thy chiefs whom thou deemest worthy to
       succeed thee on the throne.</p>
     </sp>

     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Doubt not I shall do my people justice - a solemn
       <pb n="34"/> warning from above was last night whispered to my soul - yes, yes, I feel this
       very day the will of heaven shall be declared, the name of my successor be breathed even from
       the skies - again I will entreat the gods in prayer - in yonder tent for a few moments beg
       again their blessing - do thou and all thy chiefs and people await me here - anon I will join
       you and proclaim my will. Doubt not, good Thamar, the successor I shall proclaim will be one
       who will meet thine and all my people’s approbation. <stage>[Retires among the rocks.</stage>
      </p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Aside.]</stage> Ha! then the glorious prize, indeed, is mine – he dares not name
       another. Now to assemble all the chiefs and forces who are favourable to my views and, should
       the robber dare to murmur aught of discontent, we may crush all idle opposition, and awe them
       to obedience.</p>
      <stage>[Music. - Exeunt Thamar and Warriors, R. S. E.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M15">
      <speaker>Kad.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(L. C.)</stage> Well, as I have heard that music after meals is good for digestion,
       suppose old Zelos here gives us the song of the Volpas, whilst you, Koscar, accompany him on
       your pipe.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.)</stage> What, that song of the Wild Genius of the Desert? - The very thought of
       it gives me an indigestion.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M15">
      <speaker>Kad.</speaker>
      <p> Psha! childrens’ tales! you can’t believe what they say of the Volpas - I thought you had
       more sense.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> Believe! I don’t believe, but I know it. It never appears but at the forewarning of
       wonderful events. The very mention of the terrible Volpas turns all the milk I have been
       drinking into vinegar. The ravager! the destroyer! - Come, come, no more talk, but the song
       of the Volpas.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music. - The pastoral groups form - Koscar mounts a hillock, C., and plays upon his
      pandean pipes - three Shepherds sing the song with chorus during which all the Men and Women
      figure a heavy dance, almost without stirring from their places, with extravagant movements of
      their heads and arms, terminating every time in grotesque and varied groups.</stage>
     <spGrp>
      <head>Tartar song:</head>
      <sp who="#L1434_Mult">
       <l>Across the wilds of Tartary there whirls a demon form, -</l>
       <l>His voice is not of this world, and mingles with the storm;</l>
       <l>Through blasts of forked lightning his snorting courser dashes.</l>
       <l>And death and terror, as his guides, smile grimly with the flashes.</l>
       <l>Let the lovely shepherd maid,</l>
       <l>Most of all, his side evade.</l>
       <pb n="35"/>
       <l>Haste! haste! to your tents hasten back,</l>
       <l>A pursuer is in your track.</l>
       <l>Fly! fly!</l>
       <l>Tis the Volpas that’s coming, the Volpas is nigh.</l>
       <l>His black and fiery courser’s mane stands bristled by the blast.</l>
       <l>And from his feet the dust in air is up in whirlwinds cast;</l>
       <l>His wide and smoking nostrils dart before him fires of wrath.</l>
       <l>And nothing that’s of mortal born can live upon his path.</l>
       <stage>Chorus and dance.</stage>
       <l>Let the lovely shepherd maid, &amp;c.</l>
       <l>Oh, when that horse and rider come, the astonish’d earth and ocean </l>
       <l>Shake and shrink with terror at the martial commotion.</l>
       <l>Nature, as if she writh'd her last, heaves with the horrid pang.</l>
       <l>And trumpets shriek in the troubled air their war denouncing clang.</l>
       <l>Let the lovely shepherd maid, &amp;c.</l>
      </sp>
     </spGrp>
     <stage>At the conclusion of the song, a storm comes on with immense fury.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_F18">
      <speaker>Shepherdess.</speaker>
      <p> There! see now! I thought what would come of such profane ditties: the devil is no person
       to be jested with. You have sung a song in his honour, and he is now coming to thank you for
       it - yes, yes, sure enough, the Volpas is at hand this time.</p>
      <stage>[Music. - An universal scream of horror runs through the assembled multitude.</stage>
      <stage>Re-enter AbderKhan, L.S.E.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> What means this wild alarm, my children? These screams of abject terror?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M19">
      <speaker>First Shepherdess.</speaker>
      <p> Ah, sire, save us, save us! An awful visitation - the Volpas, the Volpas is at hand.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Dismiss this idle fear, and dread no fiend but that which vice has planted in the human
       heart. The voice of heaven now surely speaks in the thunder of the elements; its awful
       secrets shall this day be known; its pleasure and your future fate by my voice be declared;
       Chiefs and Elders, attend me to assist me in my prayers; do you, my children, secure your
       steeds from the fury of the elements. Sound now your shells, and call them around you - let
       the seats of our armed tribes spread beneath the palm-grove, where I, with our chosen guests
       and elders, may consult the messenger of heaven. <stage>[Aside.]</stage> Oh, if I dared
       believe the portentous throbbings of this heaving breast - but, oh! the peace I’d fain
       inspire in them is stranger to my soul.</p>
      <stage>[Exit with the Elders, L.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M15">
      <speaker>Kad.</speaker>
      <p> Koscar, call up the steeds affrighted and dispersed by the storm; your sounding-shells,
       pealing along the echoes will bring them quickly around us.
       <pb n="36"/> My friends, ascend to the mountain -pastures and draw our flocks homewards to
       the valleys, for see, the storm increases.</p>
      <stage>Music. - The Shepherds sound their horns - their horses rush on from the adjacent
       pastures - they mount them, and proceed in various directions - a large body of them on foot
       ascend the mountain-eminence - as they ascend the rocky the storm redoubles. When they reach
       the summit, L., the heavens pour forth a continuous stream of fire - the Shepherds, with a
       shriek of alarm, exclaim, “The Volpas! the Volpas!” and rush forward and throw themselves on
       their faces, - The Wild Horse, with Mazeppa, is seen furiously pursuing his course among the
       mountains, crossing first from L. to R., backwards and forwards over the range of hills, till
       he reaches the front, and, as he is crossing from R. S. E. to L. S. E., a thunderbolt falls
       and strikes a fir-tree, L., which falls amongst the brush wood, and hides him from view, -
       The Shepherds all rise up and rush off in horror, R.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Heard feebly exclaiming.]</stage> Helo! help! for heaven’s sake, release me!</p>
      <stage>Music. - Enter Oneiza, R., rushing forward in dreadful alarm.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F17">
      <speaker>One.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(L. C.)</stage> Ha, what a dreadful conflict of the elements! Whither shall I seek for
       shelter? Ah! in this thicket I may find, perhaps, a momentary refuge from the storm.
        <stage>[Music. - She turns aside some of the brushwood and the branches of the fallen tree,
        L., which presents to view Mazeppa, extended motionless and apparently lifeless, upon the
        body of the exhausted horse,]</stage> What do I behold! - A human being, apparently
       lifeless, yet bleeding, and bound by cruel thongs upon the body of a steed, exhausted, dead
       or dying. <stage>[Leaning over Mazeppa,]</stage> He moves! he breathes! Oh, may I, under
       heaven, be the happy means of affording him relief. <stage>[Loosening the cords which bind
        him.]</stage> I will unbind those blood-soaked cords, and plants of soothing virtues shall
       allay the anguish of their wounds. <stage>[Rises, and gathers leaves.]</stage> From this
       flask the cool refreshing stream shall shoot new vigour through his wearied frame.</p>
      <stage>[Giving him drink from her water-bottle, and binding his wounds with leaves.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Rising up a little.]</stage> Ah! have the cords that bound my aching limbs at length
       bursted? Save - save me or I die! <stage>[He sinks back, from exhaustion.</stage></p>
      <pb n="37"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F17">
      <speaker>One.</speaker>
      <p> Ah! He is not one of our tribes. Let me hasten to our Prophet-Khan, whose mild benignant
       spirit will lavish more effectual succour than my weak aid can offer. <stage>[Music. - Exit
        hastily,L.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Re-enter some of the Shepherds, cautiously, R. S. E. and L. S. E.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M15">
      <speaker>Kad.</speaker>
      <p> What meant that strange and fearful vision which, amidst the dashes of the storm, gleamed
       on our affrighted view?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(L. C.)</stage> Why, what should it be but the Volpas, as I told you. Ah! what do I
       behold? There lies the wild horse sunk in death, and on his back a form that seems like
       mortal.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M15">
      <speaker>Kad.</speaker>
      <p> Perhaps it is a fellow creature.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> It must be the Volpas; he’s only taking a nap, and will wake up more savage than ever.
       I’ll take care how I go nigh him. Back, the Khan approaches.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - Enter AbderKhan, attended by Oneiza, and followed by Thamar and suite,
      L.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Where is the wounded and exhausted stranger? Why stand ye idle and indifferent, when,
       perhaps, your cares might succour human woe?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M16">
      <speaker>Kos.</speaker>
      <p> Human woe! Oh, no, please your highness, it’s no human woe, but that horrid inhuman beast,
       the Volpas.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Assist me, friends, to raise the object of our pity, and convey him to a timely shelter.
        <stage>[Music. - The Shepherds remove the tree - the Khan advances, and bends over the body
        of Mazeppa, L.C.]</stage> Ah! what signs and characters now meet my sight? Like the bright
       lightning’s blaze, it flashes on my soul. <stage>[Rising, and advancing to Thamar.]</stage>
       Thamar, my friend, behold, and join with me in gratitude to heaven. A miracle has been
       wrought! Read, read, brave chief, those words of gladdening power, - Mazeppa! Yes, mark thou
       that honoured word; - it is my son! my son! my long-lost child. <stage>[Kneeling.]</stage>
       Eternal heaven, receive an old man’s thanks, nor suffer the full tide of joy to overwhelm my
       soul.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Approaching Mazeppa.]</stage> I mark the characters, my liege. May they not be the
       work of an impostor?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Approaching Mazeppa.]</stage> Saidst thou an impostor? - This the triumphant answer:
       behold this jewelled star, the badge and emblem of our noble tribe; myself affixed it there;
       and, glittering now upon his bosom, it
       <pb n="38"/> flashes sweet conviction on my soul. It is indeed my child. See, he revives - he
       moves!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Loose those dreadful cords, I say. See, see the gushing stream that mingles with the flood
       is draining from my heart! Why do those gnarling wolves howl on so hideously? They are upon
       us! - their ravening tusks tear off my flesh! Ha! that precipice, - that must be swift
       destruction! We reach its brink! - Lost! lost for ever?</p>
      <stage>[He again sinks back in exhaustion.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Methinks this wild delirium speaks ill for his recovery.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Peace, thou malignant fiend, whose withering breath would blast my new-born hopes! See,
       the pallid hue of death now brightens into health. Raise him with care, and be he to yon
       foremost tent conveyed, henceforth the seat of royalty.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Aside, whilst the Assistants are raising Mazeppa on a litter.]</stage> Make not too
       sure of that. Delusion! miracle! Imposture! - what it will, my hopes and high ambition are
       not to be o’erthrown thus by a single blow</p>
      <stage>[Music. - Mazeppa is raised on a bier.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Pointing to the Wild Horse, which still lies extended on the earth,]</stage> That
       noble steed claims our assistance, too. Of mortal mould it cannot be, but the choice
       instrument of heaven to restore to Tartary a sovereign, to a doting sire a long-lost son
        <stage>[The Shepherds raise the horse.]</stage> Ye priests and people, raise aloud your
       voices, - implore of heaven it will not leave its glorious work unaccomplished, but that,
       restored to vigour, my son may bless alike his father and his people.</p>
      <stage>[The Priests and People join in the chorus - the Khan, with a mixture of anxiety,
       tenderness, and exultation, watches his son while Thamar, with his associates, aside, evince
       their rage and disappointment,</stage>

     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_Mult">
      <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
      <p/>
      <l>Powers benignant, now look down,</l>
      <l>A father’s hopes with mercy crown;</l>
      <l>Listen to a people’s prayer, -</l>
      <l>Bless, oh, bless our tender care!</l>
      <l>Gracious powers, whom we adore</l>
      <l>Our future monarch now restore;</l>
      <l>That our triumphant shouts may raise</l>
      <l>In songs of gratitude and praise.</l>
     </sp>
     <stage>The scene closes.</stage>
    </div>
    <pb n="39"/>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE IV: <hi>A Tartarian Landscape adjacent to the great Encampment, which is seen in
       the distance.</hi></head>
     <stage>Music. - Enter Thamar and Warriors, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> In vain does yonder hoary dotard dream his new-found fondling shall defeat my purpose and
       enjoy the throne. Too long have we been slaves, the groveling slaves of superstition. You all
       have sworn to see your leader on the throne, nor can I fear the firm determination of such
       gallant warriors can be diverted by so poor an artifice. Will you uphold me still?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_Mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p> We will! we will!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Then am I still the sovereign of Tartary. For this poor impostor, - my dagger shall
       quickly remove that trivial obstacle. To me the guard of the royal tent has been confided.
       Soon will I teach the Prophet- Khan to know that his weak delusions can never turn from his
       affirmed resolve the unshrinking soul of Thamar. On to our purpose, warriors. [<stage>Exeunt,
        R.</stage></p>
     </sp>
    </div>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE V: <hi>The Interior of a rude Tartar Tent, hung with characteristic arms and armour
       - on the flat, R. C., hangs a large metal Shield, used to strike signals on.</hi></head>
     <stage>Music. - Mazeppa discovered sleeping on a low pallet, the Khan watching over him with
      intense anxiety, L. C.- Officer in attendance, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Let all our armed tribes, at earliest dawn, be assembled around my tent, that of the
       prince’s first returning sense I may apprise them, and proclaim him to my people.
        <stage>[Exit Officer through the tent, R. C. F.] </stage>Sleep on, my boy, and oh! may the
       repose which now envelopes thy faculties in death-like calm, like heaven-descended dews,
       revive thy energies in vigour and in health. The camp is silence all, save where the trusty
       sentinel paces his little round. The tent is guarded by my choicest warriors, but here thy
       father shall maintain his post, and, till thy slumber breaks, thy foremost safeguard be thy
       father’s heart.</p>
      <stage>[He lies down on a couch, L. C., near Mazeppa, and shortly falls asleep.</stage>
     </sp>
     <stage> Enter Thamar and two Conspirators, cautiously, R. C. F.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Thanks to the guard I chose for their protection, our entrance hither has been easy and
       noiseless. Fate
       <pb n="40"/>favours our design. They sleep. Myself will strike the blow; my dagger’s thirsty
       for the stripling’s blood.</p>
      <stage>[He approaches the couch of Mazeppa.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p><stage>[In his sleep.]</stage> Off, tyrant, off! thy bonds shall not withhold me; the
       energies of such a soul as mine shall burst thy puny cords, and, in the power of vengeance, I
       shall stand terribly before thee.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> He raves - he wakes - back, back: delay our purpose, till returning slumber render it
       secure from all alarm.</p>
      <stage>[Music, - Thamar and Conspirators retire, R.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Awaking.]</stage> Still do those cruel lashings press upon my flesh, and eat into my
       bone - ah! this limb is free - so are all. <stage>[He rises and advances to the front,
        C.]</stage> Again I stand erect, again assume the godlike attitude of freedom and of man.
       Though weak and tottering, still these limbs are freed from galling bonds, and own no
       tyrant’s chain - where can I be? My confused ideas and broken memory serve not to recall the
       incidents of the past hour - something I do remember of a venerable form, that hung in pity
       o’er my prostrate wretchedness, and with compassion’s tears did wash my wounds. <stage>[He
        traverses the tent and looks out at the opening, R. C.]</stage> The canopy of heaven,
       studded with glittering fires, spreads its broad expanse around; and, by their light, long
       avenues of tented habitations show that I am treading on the field of war - Ah! at that
       bless’d idea, my soul swells high, my energies are strung with new-recovered vigour, and I
       feel sufficient yet to conquer my own glory. - Let me observe; and lest around this friendly
       shelter malice should lurk, or any hostile arm, <stage>[Seeing a shield and sword hanging
        up]</stage> thou friendly steel. I’ll borrow thy assistance.</p>
      <stage>[Music, - He takes down a sword and shield, and goes out at the back of the tent, R. C.
       F. - Thamar and the Conspirators advance from R.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Another, and a surer plan has glanced across my mind. The Khan himself shall perish; the
       crime, charged on this new-found stranger, hurls him at once to irretrievable ruin, and who
       can then dispute the throne with Thamar?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Awaking.]</stage> My boy! my child! where art thou? Misery and despair! sure, treason
       is abroad. <stage>[Rises and comes forward.]</stage> Thou here, Thamar, at this unwonted
       hour? The truth at once flashes upon my horror-stricken soul Pernicious miscreant! Thou hast
       destroyed my child, </p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="41"/>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Thy child, fond dotard! The easy dupe thou art to yonder rash impostor, proves thee unfit
       to reign. Think not the destiny of Tartary is thus to be surrendered to thy childishness, or
       yon adventurer’s audacity - the chiefs of Tartary would have a warrior king!’tis me they have
       selected. And, ere I snatch, somewhat too rudely, perhaps, the tottering crown that trembles
       on thy aged brow, wisely surrender it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> To thee, insidious monster? Never! I have now an heir to prop the drooping glories of my
       house; and ere 1 would surrender one tittle of his just rights, traitor, thou shouldst hew me
       piecemeal! Least of all would I abandon my beloved people to the ambitious fury of such a
       wretch as thou art.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Yet, ere our daggers drain thy aged veins of all their poor remains of life, be wise and
       yield - affix thy seal to this parchment, renouncing all title to the throne, and stamping
       him thou callest thy son, a foul impostor: this do and live - and oh! be sure thy death is
       but the prelude to that foundling boy’s, who never shall dispute with me the crown.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Your threats I scorn. The spirit that has often led me on to victory, shall nerve me
       still, nor do I dread to meet a host of coward traitors, such as Thamar.</p>
      <stage>[Snatches up a sword, and places himself in an attitude of defence, L. C.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Thou hast pronounced thy doom. <stage>[Music. - The Khan rushes towards the entrance of
        the tent, as if to strike the shield - as he does so, on a signal from Thamar, two other
        Conspirators rush forward, meet him, and drive him back.]</stage> Each sword that gleams
       around is sworn to do my bidding.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Thy king defies thee, still; I strike for my own right and for my boy’s, and heaven will
       assist my arm.</p>
      <stage>[Music. - Thamar and one other Conspirator rush on him, the other two guarding the
       entrance to the tent, and keeping the curtain down - after a short contest, the Khan is
       overpowered, and falls - Thamar and his confederates stand over him with uplifted weapons -
       during this, a sort of struggle has been perceived at the entrance of the tent, as of some
       one endeavouring to force their way in, which is successfully resisted by the two Tartars
       placed there - at the moment when Thamar and the Conspirators are on the point of striking
       their weapons to the heart of the Khan, the tent is slit up in another place by a sword, and
       Mazeppa
       <pb n="42"/>darts through the opening with his sword and shield and stands in a protecting
       attitude over the prostrate Khan.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Cowards and villains! the garb of Tartar warriors, and two of you against an aged feeble
       man! he, too, whose kindness rescued me from death, and soothed my sufferings.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music. - The four Conspirators now forcibly attack the Khan and Mazeppa - in the course
      of the conflict several interesting pictures are formed by the mutual efforts of father and
      son to save each other - they overpower the conspirators.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M13">
      <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
      <p> Yet do I laugh thy power to scorn, for hundreds now without await but my nod to shed their
       life-blood in my cause.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Millions will strike in mine. <stage>[Strikes the shield with his sword - the curtains of
        the tent are drawn up, and the whole Tartar army is discovered in battle array.]</stage>
       Tartars, behold the traitor who has sought your sovereign’s life. <stage>[A party of Guards
        seize Thamar and his confederates,]</stage> Away with them to punishment. <stage>[They are
        taken back.]</stage> And now, young hero, in the aged man you have preserved, embrace and
       own a fond, a doating father.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> A father! ha! does that sacred sound, like heaven descended dews, speak comfort to my
       heart! <stage>[Embraces the Khan]</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> No longer must the glad, the important task be now delayed. Assembled Tartars, priests,
       warriors, people - behold and mark me: in this brave youth, who has even now saved your
       sovereign’s life, know and revere Mazeppa, my long lost, only son, your sovereign prince -
       hail my boy, Mazeppa, King of Tartary.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[All kneel before Mazeppa - general shout. - Music. - Mazeppa is conducted off, L. - the
      curtains of the tent fall - the Khan motions his officers to assemble the people - they go out
      in various directions - the elders bring him his shield and staff of office. - Exeunt
      AbderKhan and Attendants, exultingly, L.</stage>
    </div>
    <div type="scene">
     <pb n="43"/>
     <head>SCENE VI: <hi>Extensive Tartar Encampment.</hi></head>
     <stage>Music. - The whole Tartar army, with their Chiefs, assembled.</stage>
     <stage>Enter the Khan, L., leading on Mazeppa, to C. - the People kneel and receive him with
      acclamations.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Whose surprise has been momentarily increasing.]</stage> I King of Tartary! where am
       I? - what has happened? - After a doom beyond expression awful - bound to a wild horse -
       whirled o’er torrents, deserts, precipices - on all sides, danger and destruction - I ceased
       to feel. - Have I then passed the realm of death? and do I wake to new life and other being?
       - I find myself free, beneath a strange sky, a prostrate people hailing me their king - say,
       say, do I dream - do I still exist?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(L. C.)</stage> Heaven has restored thee to thy native land, and to the throne which
       thou wast born to fill. Reign o’er thy land, which welcomes thee, Mazeppa; be powerful, and
       be happy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.)</stage> Happy! I happy without my loved Olinska, never, ah! never. - I renounce
       glory Olinska shares not. If it indeed be true that heaven, by some unwonted miracle, has
       brought me back to my native land, amid my brethren - that it has called me to rule o’er
       them, too, I but accept the sovereign sway to right their wrongs and mine - to retrieve the
       honour of the nation, wrecked on the fields of Poland - to hurl swift vengeance on our foes,
       and rescue my dear Olinska.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> If thy love be worthy of your love, then head our tribes and tear her from thy rival - a
       long arrear of vengeance does my soul count against Polish foes; and to the dread amount, how
       awful an increase thy wrongs, my child, inspire. For thee and for thy cause again I’ll
       strike; this aged arm shall bear the warrior’s steel, and perhaps I yet may fall in shielding
       thee.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Thou shalt behold and share my joyous triumph - I fight for my Olinska and my love.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> I, for my much-loved child and my revenge. Behold the steed, fated by heaven to bring you
       to your native land and throne, again awaits you; he bore you to my arms - let him now bear
       you to your triumph.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> He was the instrument of torture, - let him now be the messenger of vengeance. On to the
       Polish frontier; I cannot know repose whilst my Olinska’s fate’s uncertain - I can feel no
       glory till from a rival’s I’ve conquered her.</p>
      <pb n="44"/>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Then, with to-morrow’s dawn the march begins. Drive all our cattle within the lines - be
       every soldier ready at his post; for ere two suns have set behind those Polish mountains, our
       force shall beneath the tyrant’s wall make him to tremble in his strong hold of power and rue
       the day he injured child of mine. - </p>
      <l>Away! away!</l>
      <l> Eager we seek the foe at dawn of day.</l>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music, - A superbly caparisoned steed has been led on far Mazeppa, another for the Khan
      - they mount - a general parade and movement of the army takes place, on which the drop
      falls.</stage>
    </div>
    <trailer>END OF ACT II.</trailer>
   </div>
   <div type="act">
    <head>ACT III</head>
    <div type="scene">

     <head>SCENE I: <hi>A Gothic Chamber in the Castle of the Castellan, in Poland.</hi></head>

     <stage>Music. Olinska discovered, pale and dejected, seated at a rich toilet, attended by a
      female.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Bid my nurse come to me. <stage>[Exit Attendant]</stage> The victim’s adorned not for the
       altar, but the tomb. <stage>[Rises and advances.]</stage> This day is the last whose light
       will shine on the poor Olinska. <stage>[She approaches the toilet and moves a little casket,
        concealed beneath the drapery, opens it, and takes out a portrait, on which she gazes with
        the liveliest emotion.]</stage> Cassimir, my beloved - murdered - mangled, can I, ought I to
       survive thy horrid death? <stage>[Takes from the casket a dagger, which she pushes from her
        with a shudder.]</stage> Oh, my father! oh, my father! your threaten’d curse! - Father, I
       have given.you my oath to be the bride of Premislas; my oath shall not be broken - the honour
       of our house exacts the sacrifice. <stage>[Takes the dagger and hides it in her
        dress.]</stage> One awful means is left of obedience and fidelity - yes, this night, this
       very night, restores me to my lover, in the tomb. <stage>[Placing her hand upon the
        dagger.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Agatha, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_F8">
      <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
      <p> See, lady, where your father comes.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Quickly conceal that packet, and wonder, nurse, at thy Olinska’s fortitude - her apathy;
       that she who loved, and as I did Cassimir, can yield obedience to his
       <pb n="45"/> ruthless murderer - can yield my hand unto his haughty rival.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - Enter the Castellan, L. - Agatha conceals the casket.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Olinska, your imprudence might have caused the ruin of your father: but Count Premislas,
       restored to life, has deemed the act of Cassimir merely a presumptuous vassal’s crime,
       without your sanction. But the pretender has been punished. And now, Olinska, I trust I may
       confide in your entire submission.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Implicitly!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> That pledge disarms my wrath - my child, the past is all forgiven, forgotten - come to thy
       father’s arms, who now can call thee once again his daughter.</p>
      <stage>[As she is dropping on her knees, he catches her to his bosom.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Father!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> My child, my dearest child, may heaven’s peace attend thee.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">

      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>May thy prayer be heard, my father: ‘ere long, thy child will cease to suffer.</p>
      <stage>[Trumpets heard without, L.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Hark thee, my child; yon trumpets speak the bridegroom ready, the cortege prepared.
       Throughout my castle’s precincts, this day all wears one universal face of joy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.) </stage>All except one - that one whose feelings lie too deep for utterance. My
       father, once again extend thy arm in blessing o’er thy child. I leave thee, my sole parent,
       perhaps for ever - oh! in the journey I’m about to take, gloomy and dark it may be, let me
       receive the sacred consolation that a father’s blessing shall attend his child.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> Heaven for ever bless thee, sweet Olinska! Come, come, my child, away with thoughts of
       gloom; share thou the triumph which on every side courts thy acceptance.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Father, again thou’st bless’d me; I can bear it all.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music. - They embrace and exeunt, Olinska, R., Castellan L.</stage>
    </div>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE II: <hi>A Hall of the Castle of Laurinski.</hi></head>
     <stage>Music. - Enter Drolinsko, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> I am clean an altered man. I feel myself already puffed up and swelling with my new
       dignity, even as 1 hope ere long my body shall be stuffed and swelled with the perquisites of
       office. I was a huntsman - I am a
       <pb n="46"/> cook. - I’ll never look another live head of game in the face again – I’ll
       commit no murder on hares, pheasants, bears, stags, and partridges more. - No; I’ll leave off
       executioner, and be a kind of an undertaker - that is. I’ll dress them up in a proper manner
       to be sent to their graves, the throats of gormandizers.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Zemila, L.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Ah! Mr. Drolinsko, you look quite a different person from what you used to be.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> And I am a different person, too, Mrs. Zemila: know that I am placed at the head of the
       victualling department - that I am chief officer of the mouth, and general purveyor for the
       belly - I’ve got you all under my thumb, now; only look as I would not have you, and I clap
       you all on short allowance - offend me, and the soup’s all turned over - insult my dignity,
       and all the fat’s in the fire. I shall astonish you all.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">

      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> No absurdity that you can commit can possibly astonish me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Oh! I’m a clever fellow at noseing out a good thing. There was I, early this morning,
       wandering out into the wood beyond the castle; my teeming brain on fire with the grand
       devices which this day shall produce - what should I meet with, but a group of wandering
       Tartars; I’ve engaged them to come to the festival - what do you think of that, now?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Why, that my lord will break your head, and have you kicked out of the place - you know he
       hates the very name of Tartar.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> These are jovial fellows, innocent as lambs; for a mouthful of broken victuals they’ll
       dance such dances, and show us such singular manœuvres and evolutions - I mean it to be the
       principal feature of the whole festival. And now what do you think of me in my new robe of
       office?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Why, I’ve heard that fine feathers make fine birds; but, my poor Drolinsko, though decked
       out with all the plumage of the peacock, you can’t prevent us from finding out that you are
       but a sorry jackdaw.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Well, miss, at any rate, you’re a pretty good re- semblance of a magpie. - Come, I think
       that wasn’t so much amiss of me - she’ll find that it’s awkward playing with edged tools.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> Edged tools, indeed! - tool thou art, my poor
       <pb n="47"/> fellow, to any one who thinks it worth while to handle thee; but as to edge -
       bless thy harmlessness - thy wit, Drolinsko, is quite as blunt as thy manners. - But I must
       away, to attend my lady’s toilet, and prepare her for the ceremony - and now, my good
       Drolinsko, let me beg of thee one thing?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Any thing in life, lovely Mrs. Zemila: is it that I shall reserve a good place for you to
       see the sports?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M14">
      <speaker>Zem.</speaker>
      <p> No:’tis simply this, Drolinsko, that thou wilt not, if thou canst help it, make thyself so
       monstrously ridiculous as to occasion me to die with laughing. <stage>[Exit, L.]</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> That young woman has some good points about her, but she is marvelously deficient in
       politeness.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - Enter AbderKhan, Mazeppa and a Tartar Chief, in close disguise as Tartar
      peasants, L.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Well, now you’ve filled your bellies, I hope it has relieved your imaginations.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Trust us, sir, we do not need excitement.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Well, now, I suppose you’ve made up your minds to do something a little out of the way on
       this occasion?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Be sure, we shall astonish you.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Well, so do, I like to be astonished; and on this occasion I wish every thing to be new
       and uncommon.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> You shall witness one of the strangest sights that has for many a long day regaled your
       curiosity.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> I should like the very walls to caper.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M19">
      <speaker>Chief.</speaker>
      <p> Caper! they shall fly.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Come, come, none of your nonsense now, you are going too far - I’m not so soft as all that
       comes to.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> ‘Tis necessary you should furnish me with the key of the great gates - my two comrades
       here I leave with you - I will hasten to rejoin the rest - hold ourselves in readiness,
       adjacent to the castle, and on your signal rush forward to effect the grand tableau.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> I’ll go and fetch you the key; you’re a jolly old blade, you are, too - no chicken - but
       there seems stuff in you yet. I’ll be with you again in the spitting of a part- ridge.
        <stage>[Exit, R.]</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.) </stage>Haste thou to our bands, good father - marshal them in yonder forest, and
       when I give the signal, let them, like a mountain torrent, rush, o’erwhelming all resistance,
       to the aid of those that are within. I will be on the spot; and, at the moment when the
       perjured fair would offer her unhallowed vows upon
       <pb n="48"/> the sacred altar, my steel shall drink the life-blood of them both, and their
       mingled gore proclaim the vengeance of my outraged love. [<stage>Music heard
       without</stage>,] See, see, where the traitress comes - down, down, struggling spirit - the
       moment of thy triumph is not yet arrived.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Enter Drolinsko, R.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Back, fellows, back - see where the bride approaches.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>Music. - Enter Olinska, attended by Agatha, preceded by Rudzoloff, and followed by
      Attendants, R.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_F8">
      <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
      <p><stage> (R. C.)</stage> Cheerly, cheerly, lady; this is not the countenance you should
       exhibit on your bridal morn.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p><stage> (C.)</stage> It well befits a bridal such as mine; my hopes are buried in another’s
       tomb - soon, soon may I go seek him there.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F8">
      <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
      <p> But this dejection scarce fulfils your promise to your father - all was to be
       submission.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> It is submission, nurse – submission I have learned by trampling on every feeling of my
       heart. I shall obey my father - let him not require more than I can perform.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> [<stage>Approaching Olinska.</stage> ] Lord love your beautiful ladyship, you’ll be
       delighted when you see the preparations for the fete, solely contrived by me, Drolinsko. Why,
       it’s worth while being married, if only to see such a tasty set-out - you’ll be half inclined
       to love me for the cultivated fancy I have displayed.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(L. C.)</stage> Who are those strangers?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Ah! that’s another of my contrivances, that you’d never suspect, godfather. Those, why
       those, bless you, are wandering Tartars, introduced by me.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Tartars! introduce Tartars here! why, it’s more than your head’s worth - let but the
       Castellan know it.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Ay, it’s plain to see you’re a fellow of no pith and enterprise. He may think what he
       likes about Tartars, but if these fellows don’t caper him into good-humour, he’s a sulkier
       dog than I take him for.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Doubt not that we will overcome all his displeasure.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Approaching Olinska, C.]</stage> Deign you, fair lady, to cast an eye of approbation
       and encouragement. <stage>[He is close to her - she turns to look at him - he throws aside
        part of his disguise, so that she recognizes him.]</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[With a scream of astonishment]</stage> Cassimir! <stage>[All start,
        <pb n="49"/> surprised - he hastily resumes his disguise, and Olinska, by a great effort, an
        appearance of composure.]</stage> Cassimir, some time a page of this household, was a
       countryman of yours, I believe.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Belike, fair lady, I do bethink me of a tale of a poor Tartar lad, bred up in Polish
       climes, who rashly loved a noble lady – ‘twas a fault in him, but oh! who ever looked upon
       that fair one’s beauty and her worth, must have forgiven him, knowing that to see and not to
       love was scarcely possible. Her father found it in him a crime not to be pardoned, and
       sentenced him to a most cruel death.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Muttering.]</stage> It was, indeed, most horrible.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> By miracle he was saved, and, like the Polar needle, true to his first affection, back he
       rushed, impatient still to lay his homage at the adored one’s feet. But, oh! death-blow to
       his hopes! torture more cruel than all before he’d suffered, he found her perjured,
       faithless, voluntarily about to give her hand unto another.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Ah! had he known her tears, her anguish, the silent calm despair with which, unable to
       resist, she yielded to her parent’s harsh commands, enforced under the penalty of his awful
       curse - how like a victim to the sacrifice she did approach the altar, - he would not, could
       not, dare not, to condemn her.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Had she, then, no remedy to save herself from such accursed pollution?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> Yes, and a noble one: which, rather than betray her first fond vows, she’s resolute to
       clutch at -</p>
      <stage>[Draws a dagger from her bosom, and shows it to Mazeppa.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[With a burst of triumph.]</stage> Ha! she was a heroine worthy a sovereign’s
       love.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[The attention of the bystanders is excited - Mazeppa and Olinska are compelled to
      control their feelings.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Zounds! This Tartar gipsy has contrived to astonish my lady already.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> The tales of our country have a wild and wondrous force, well calculated to awake the
       feelings thus.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M3">
      <speaker>Rud.</speaker>
      <p> Your pardon, lady, - had we not better on?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_F7">
      <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
      <p> I attend you, Rudzoloff.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Aside to Olinska.]</stage> Doubt not, fair lady, all shall be accomplished: your
       smallest wish most scrupulously obeyed.</p>
      <pb n="50"/>
      <stage>[Music, - Exit Olinska, preceded by Rudzoloff and supported Agatha, L., exchanging
       significant glances with Mazeppa.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M4">
      <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
      <p> Now, mind, you fellows, be at your posts.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> The dearest feelings of our hearts are pledged to be so. <stage>[Exit Drolinsko,
        L.]</stage> Ah, father, what a weight’s removed from off my heart: Olinska yet is mine -
       your son shall yet be happy.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> He shall, he shall! Oh, to attain that end, how joyfully thy father would shed his latest
       crimson drop -</p>
      <stage>[They embrace and exeunt, Abdar Khan R., Mazeppa L.</stage>
     </sp>
    </div>
    <div type="scene">
     <head>SCENE III: <hi>The Gardens of Laurinski, closed in the back by terraces, the last of
       which is entered, L. through a spacious gate of golden bars - its other end communicates with
       a wood - the whole extent is bounded on the L. by the buildings of the castle - from the
       topmost terrace, near the great gate, a spacious flight of steps, L., which leads down to the
       stage.</hi></head>
     <stage>Music. - Mazeppa L. - he advances cautiously, ascends the steps, and beckons on
      AbderKhan, who advances from the building, L. U. E.</stage>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Now, honoured father, how speeds the glorious work?</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Even as should the deed on which depends thy happiness. Our troops are all at hand, and
       eager for the attack. Yes, my son, thy triumph is assured - here, on the haughty despot’s
       battlements, he shall surrender thee thy love, or thou shalt tear her from his arms, amidst
       their blackened ruins.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> All is prepared for the ceremony - I will be on the spot. Do thou, with our bands, at the
       signal, like the whirlwind’s blast, sweep opposition into dust. <stage>[The music of the
        procession is heard.]</stage> They come, they come! - Oh, father! On this hour, on which my
       more than life depends, my anxious soul, fluttering within my breast, almost denies me
       utterance, and eager expectation swells my heart to bursting.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Thy father and thy people shall not fail thee; -
       <l> But whether weal or woe attend our plan, </l>
       <l>Thou’rt a sovereign, - show, too, thou art a man.</l></p>
     </sp>
     <pb n="51"/>
     <stage>[Music. - AbderKhan retires up the steps and along the terrace, R. 6th E. - the nuptial
      procession advances from the building, L., through the great gate and down the steps - it is
      composed of the entire household of the Castellan, headed by Drolinsko - Rudzoloff immediately
      precedes Olinska, who is led by the Castellan and Premislas, and followed by Agatha - they
      come down, C. - the Guards, banners, &amp;c. countermarch, and form on the R. side and on the
      terraces - the nuptial party sit on a throne, L., surrounded by their Attendants - on a signal
      from Drolinsko, a tribe of Tartar Youths and Maidens appear on the upper terrace and descend
      the staircase, L.</stage>
     <stage>MILITARY CHARACTERISTIC BALLET</stage>
     <stage>[At the conclusion of the ballet, a small altar is placed on the lower terrace, C. - the
      Priest advances from 3rd E, L, to C. - Olinska, led by Premislas and the Castellan, approaches
      the altar - the Priest commences the ceremony, when Mazeppa, still disguised, appears suddenly
      on the terrace, and thrusts the Priest aside.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.)</stage> Hold! I forbid such sacrilegious vows! they are offensive in the sight of
       heaven. This maid, in heart and spirit, and by long previous vows, breathed from the very
       bottom of her soul, is mine; and any other union, by tyranny accomplished, is perjury,
       pollution.</p>
      <stage>[Castellan, Olinska, and Premislas, are all C.</stage>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p> What insolent intruder dares thus to break, with barbarous scoffings, on our solemnity?
      </p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(C.)</stage> One whom thou shouldst remember. Tyrant, behold thy victim.
        <stage>[Throws off his disguise.</stage></p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_Mult">
      <speaker>All.</speaker>
      <p> Cassimir!</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Cassimir, Mazeppa, one - thy vengeful tyranny but doomed me to my glory: the wild horse
       bore me to the throne of Tartary: and now, Mazeppa, King of Tartary, proudly returns to claim
       his early love.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M1">
      <speaker>Cast.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>(R. C.)</stage> Impostor! barbarian! traitor! wert thou the king of half the eastern
       world, the scorn in which I hold thee were not lessened. Bear him away! a death more certain
       this time punishes his presumption.</p>
     </sp>
     <stage>[Music, - Some of the household advance to seize Cassimir - the Tartar Youths and
      Maidens form a rampart in front of him, and the Khan, followed by Tartar Soldiery, who occupy
      the upper terrace, appears at the head of the staircase.</stage>

     <sp who="#L1434_M11">
      <speaker>Abd.</speaker>
      <p> Stay, monsters! stay your uplifted hands! - Let
       <pb n="52"/> but one hair of his head be injured, and your castle quickly is a heap of ruins,
       soaked in your blood, for every soul shall perish. Your castle is invested - on every tower,
       buttress, and pinnacle, clings a Tartar, awaiting but my word, when havoc is let loose, and
       fierce destruction ravages half Poland. Speak but one word, and let Olinska be the pledge of
       peace.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M2">
      <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
      <p>
       <stage>[Advancing from L. to C.]</stage> I will not wait to hear the Castellan’s answer -
       Olinska is my bride - in sight of heaven, my wife; my troops now man these walls, and to my
       last red drop I will defend her.</p>
     </sp>
     <sp who="#L1434_M12">
      <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
      <p> Then be revenge and slaughter our word! and let devastated Poland speak Mazeppa mounted to
       the throne of Tartary!</p>
     </sp>

     <stage>[The Polish troops in the garden fire at the Tartars on the terraces - the latter charge
      down the steps - a general conflict ensues - a charge of Tartar cavalry is made along the
      upper terrace - they are met by the Poles, issuing from the principal portal - the attendants
      endeavour to force Olinska through the tumult into the castle - the cavalry appear in front,
      and after skirmishing off on both sides, a charge in line, from L. to R., is executed by the
      Tartars - the front then becomes occupied by pairs of combatants - Ahder Khan is on the point
      of cutting down the Castellan, when Olinska rushes in and interposes - she is followed by
      Mazeppa, to whom the Castellan resigns her, which is the pledge of peace - Premislas has been
      meantime overcome by a Tartar warrior, and the Poles altogether vanquished - AbderKhan,
      Mazeppa, the Castellan, and Olinska hasten to mount the steps, to stop the slaughter, and on
      the top form a group - the females line the terraces - subdued Poles and triumphant Tartars
      fill the scene, which is lighted by the conflagration of the forest - and on the general
      picture the curtain falls.</stage>
     <trailer>THE END</trailer>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
