<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L0106">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt><title>The Prima Donna.: TEI edition</title><author>Boucicault, Dion</author><respStmt><resp>TEI conversion</resp><name>Lou Burnard</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt><distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor><idno type="LAE">L0106</idno><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which is believed to be in the public domain. You may copy, modify, distribute and perform this work freely. </licence></availability></publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc><bibl type="origin" n="8.1"><author>Boucicault, Dion</author><title type="main" n="theprimadonna">The Prima Donna</title><title type="sub">A Comedy in two
       acts</title><extent>23 pp (UM copy: 10 - 33)<measure type="pp" quantity="22"/>
  <measure type="spCount" quantity="459"/>
  <measure type="spvCount" quantity="0"/>
  <measure type="txWords" quantity="8627"/>
  <measure type="spWords" quantity="7297"/>
  <measure type="stWords" quantity="1330"/>
  </extent>
      <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 8, No. 0106</title><idno type="nic">N09535</idno><idno type="vpp">Vol08iPrima</idno></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/Source/VPP/L0106-vpp.pdf">LoB from VPP</ref><ref target="local:Vol08/L0106/L0106-vpp.pdf"/><ref target="local:Vol08/L0106/Vol08iPrima.pdf"/></bibl><bibl type="surrogate"><ref target="https://archive.org/details/primadonnacomedy0000bouc">UW from IA</ref><ref target="local:Vol08/L0106/L0106-uw.pdf"/></bibl><bibl type="surrogate"><ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453061&amp;seq=10 ">UM from
       HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol08/L0106/L0106-um.pdf"/></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="TEI"><ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/L0106.html">TEI</ref></bibl><listEvent>
      <event type="firstPerf" when="1852-09-18" source="textNic" where="Princess's">
       <desc>Premiered at Royal Princess's Theatre 18 Sept. 1852</desc>
      </event>
     </listEvent></sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc><!--S 2 Comedy F. FARCE--><textClass><catRef target="#sizeS"/><catRef target="#act2"/><catRef target="nic:F."/><keywords><term>FARCE</term></keywords></textClass><particDesc><listPerson><person xml:id="L0106_F1"><persName type="role">Stella</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="178">Stel.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Stel. </persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0106_F2"><persName type="role">Margaret</persName><persName type="spkr" n="75">Mar.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0106_M3"><persName type="role">Rouble</persName><persName type="spkr" n="91">Rou.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0106_M4"><persName type="role">Eric</persName><persName type="spkr" n="63">Eric.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0106_M5"><persName type="role">Holbein</persName><persName type="spkr" n="50">Hol.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0106_F6"><persName type="role">[Maid]</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Maid.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Serv.</persName>
</person>
</listPerson></particDesc></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change when="2026-01-11">Standardize header components</change><change when="2026-01-10">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change><change when="2025-11-02">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change><change when="2025-09-07">Metadata updated from new catalogue</change><change when="2024-10-03">Header enriched</change>
   <change when="2023-12-02">Header confected</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text><pb n="1"/>
  <front>
   <titlePage><titlePart type="main">The Prima Donna.</titlePart><titlePart type="sub">A comedy in two acts.</titlePart><byline>By <docAuthor>Dion Boucicault</docAuthor>, author of <title>London Assurance</title>,
     <title>Old Heads and Young Hearts</title>, <title>Love in a Maze</title>, &amp;c. &amp;c.
     &amp;c.</byline><docImprint>Thomas Hailes Lacy, Wellington Street, Strand, London</docImprint></titlePage>
   <pb n="2"/>
   <div type="liminal">
    <head>Prefatory Note.</head>
    <p>I had been often told by my literary friends, that the sentimental Comedies, so popular at
     the <hi>Gymnase Theatre</hi> in Paris, were unsuited to the taste of a London Public. In spite
     of this opinion, I wrote <title>The Prima Donna.</title> I think I may conscientiously say,
     that I offered it to every manager in London, by whom it was particularly admired, and returned
     to me with thanks. </p>
    <p>At last I induced Mr, Kean to allow me to read it to him; he accepted it at once, and
     pronounced his faith in its success: (although I must do him the justice to say I read him to
     sleep).</p>
    <p>The question, then, is settled, and the London Public will accept this class of Drama; and
     what is more, we have artists who can render it with spirit and finesse-</p>
    <p>Some six months ago, I went to the Soho Theatre to witness some Amateur Theatricals. I saw
     there a young lady, in whose performance I detected so much excellence, that I told her so. I
     gave the same opinion to Mr. Kean, who having satisfied himself that I was right, instantly
     engaged her; and any reader who may wish to share this opinion may do so, as this lady, Miss
     Heath, made her debut in <title>The Prima Donna.</title></p>
    <p>On the character of Margaret in this piece, I had lavished all my care: there was at once my
     only hope and only fear, the character was dangerous and difficult. It was realized by Miss
     Robertson, with so deep a sense of its tenderness, with so much elegance and poetry, that I
     congratulated myself that every manager in London had refused the Comedy, since to that fact I
     owe the admiration bestowed on her performance. </p>
    <trailer>Dion Boucicault.</trailer>
   </div>

   <performance>
    <p>First performed at the Royal Princess's Theatre, on Saturday, September 18th, 1852.</p>
    <castList>
     <head>Characters</head>
     <castItem><role gender="F">Stella</role><actor sex="F">Miss Heath.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="F">Margaret</role><actor sex="F">Miss Robertson.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Rouble</role><actor sex="M">Mr. Walter Law.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Eric</role> <actor sex="M">Mr. Cathcart.</actor></castItem>
     <castItem><role gender="M">Holbein</role><actor sex="M">Mr. Addison.</actor></castItem>
    </castList>
   </performance>
   <set>
    <p>The scene is laid in Switzerland during the First Act. And in Milan during the Second.</p>
    <p>Time in Representation—1 hour and 15 minutes.</p>
   </set>

   <div type="costume">
    <head>Costumes.</head>
    <list type="gloss">
     <label>Margaret.</label>
     <item>- First dress, white muslin wrapper.Second dress, neat Swiss dress, green silk skirt,
      white chemisette, black velvet open Swiss body.</item>
     <label>Stella.</label>
     <item>-First dress, lilac silk travelling dress, white bonnet, and cashmere shawl. Second
      dress, white silk morning dress.</item>
     <label>Eric</label>
     <item>—Austrian uniform, cap, short white frock coat, and blue trowsers with scarlet stripe
      down side, sword, and cap.</item>
     <label>Holbein.</label>
     <item>—First dress, grey hair, black body coat, waistcoat, breeches, and stockings, Second dress,
      brown coat, and scarlet spencer.</item>
     <label>Rouble.</label>
     <item>—First dress, grey overcoat, or wrapper, black trowsers, and black gloves. Second dress,
      bottle green fall-skirted French body cost, gilt buttons, light long waistcoat, hat, and
      cane.</item>
    </list>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <head>The Prima Donna.</head>
   <div type="act">
    <head>Act I.</head>
    <stage>Scene I —An Apartment in Holbein's House a door at the back opens on the Lawn. Table and
     chair L. on the right a sofa, and a sofa table, tastefully arranged with books flowers and a
     French clock. Fire-place R., doors L 2 E and C. </stage>
    <stage> Enter Stella, followed by Rouble both in travelling costume, C. from L. </stage>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Mr Rouble you compel me to tell you that you pass all endurance.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>I am prepared for all you can say.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>When I quitted Milan so suddenly, under an assumed name, delicacy might have suggested to you 
     that I desired to travel alone.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Ah signora ! the idea of your travelling alone—you who are besieged by lovers.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Sir!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Oh in the most honourable sense of the word, reproach has never looked upon you —
     no — amongst the roses that have strewn your path there has been no thorn.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Pardon me I feel one now.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(bowing)</stage> Eh ? Oh I thank you—you the Prima Donna, who have turned Milan into a
      lunatic asylum—the syren, on whose notes the intrigues of courts and the calculations of
      commerce have hung suspended—you, whose actions are the business and livelihood of a hundred
      spies.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Spies!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>I have kept a dozen myself in constant pay.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>And you have the assurance to confess it ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Could I otherwise have discovered your intention to quit Milan?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>And you followed me ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>No, I preceded you—I ordered your relays of horses and stimulated the heels of the
     postillions.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Then it was to you I owed my fright and that fearful speed in spite of my entreaties when at
     every instant I expected my carriage would have been dashed to pieces.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Oh I wish it had!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>How?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Then you must have accepted mine.</p>
    </sp><pb n="5"/><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>I beg sir that this folly may end and that you will inform me what insane project animates
      your pursuit—what brings you here? <stage>(she takes off her bonnet and shawl, gloves Rouble
      assists her and subsequently manages to secrete one of the gloves)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>To see you—since your footmen and your principles deny me your door ; but I solace my love
      with the knowledge that you distribute misery alike to all your adorers. In my quality of
      Court Jeweller, I know the amount of diamonds purchased for and refused by you and in my
      capacity of banker, I calculated the settlements you have disdained —my admiration mounted
      with the sum total, until—</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Mr. Rouble, one word—I can guess your errand. I am an actress—as such I know I am
      defenceless, and the offer you would blush to make another you deem an honour to me;  but I
      appeal to your generosity—this is my father's house— my home. <stage>(crosses R.)</stage> Now,
      go on. <stage>(sits down)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(pauses)</stage> Signora ! had my father taught me more than my trade, I might have
      been spared your reproach—pardon me if I turn the phrase badly—I am neither elegant nor
      handsome, I know it; nor have I wit or talent and therefore I seek for all these qualities in
      a wife, and have found them in you.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Your wife!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>I offer you my fortune and my hand. <stage>(she turns)</stage> I trust the one will excuse
      the other.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Mr Rouble, <stage>(pause--rises)</stage> I thank you. <stage>(gives him her hand)</stage> It
      may be that you are neither handsome, elegant, talented or witty, but your heart is a good
      one.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Or would I offer it to you?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>And it is in the right place.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Being in your possession.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>If compelled to decline the offer, you deserve that I should afford you my reason.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Having deprived me of mine, it is but restitution.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>I am an orphan—a foundling without a name.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Accept of mine.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>I never knew my relations. I have none.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Relations! Is that all ? When you marry my fortune, you will find your relations
      forthwith.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>My earliest recollections picture a poor, famished, ragged child, begging her bread from
      house to house; singing our Swiss melodies to gain a breakfast. It was on my journey from a
      neighbouring mountain village to this town that I was overtaken by a snowstorm, in which I had
      perished, but for timely assistance. I was carried to this house—a fever ensued and ere I
      recovered, I was the adopted child of my preserver—the companion of his only daughter.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Heaven will bless the house that sheltered you.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>You are now in that house; here I have lived my life— loved—caressed—</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Here, <stage>(looks around)</stage> I'll buy the building, if it costs me half my
      fortune.</p>
    </sp><pb n="6"/><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>My benefactor was a physician; but the income he derived from his patients he spent in
      medicines for the poor—he was verging on ruin, when a means of escape from that calamity
      suggested itself—my voice, hitherto valued only as a solace to my father, I reflected that it
      might save us.  In a word, I quitted this house as I entered it— on foot.  I walked to Milan
      where under the name of Stella, I appeared at the Scala, you know the rest.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>But this does not account for your mysterious elopement ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>I hastened hither to beg the consent of my only relatives to—to—my marriage.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>With me? Oh!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>With another whom I love</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>You love another? Impossible! Where is he?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>He is here.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Here and might I ask his name ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>If you did I should decline to give it.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>I thought so , but I have his description.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Indeed!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Young, elegant, handsome, these lucky lovers are all the same—stereotyped
      <stage>(aside)</stage> I will watch the door of this house and the first fellow that answers
      the description—oh—they think a tradesman cannot fight—we shall see <stage>(aloud)</stage>
      Signora, I have the honour <stage>(bows and makes a movement to withdraw)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>You are agitated—have I wounded you?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>No Signora! that pleasure is reserved perhaps for another. I have the honour--- <stage>(bows—retires)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Mr Rouble!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Signora you have already made me a fool ; if I remain you will very probably make me a
      coward. I have the honour--- <stage>(bows and exits C and L )</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>What a strange creature it is; and if I can return his sincere love with nothing but pity,
      'tis your fault, dear Eric, yours alone. <stage>(the French clock strikes nine)</stage> Nine
      o'clock and the house appears asleep—no one risen, for I penetrated unobserved to this room.
      Ha ! I shall enjoy their surprise—my father and Margaret, dear Margaret. Hush ! I hear a step!
      they are coming <stage>(goes up L. C. playfully, and stands so that when Holbein enters from
      L., he does not see her;  he is very pale ; walking to the centre, he hesitates a moment, and
      then advancing to the clock, stops the pendulum. Stella clasps her hands, and following his
      movements with a painful transition of countenance)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Alone - And how pale!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(vacantly)</stage> Why can I not arrest the steps of Time as easily as the pendulum of
     this clock.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(advancing close to him)</stage> My father!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(turning)</stage> Stella! Stella! <stage>(embraces her)</stage> At last, at last! Oh!
     my child, you arrive too late why did you not reply to my letters?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Your letters ? For three months I have received none ! </p></sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker><p>and I have written many—many.</p>
    </sp><pb n="7"/><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Ah I see—they were intercepted by order of the Grand Duke.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>My letters intercepted! Wherefore?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>No matter—I will explain: but speak, where is my sister Margaret?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Margaret—</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>You tremble : why do you gaze on me, my father?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Be—because— soon—very soon—none will call me by that name but you.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(whispering terrified)</stage> She—she is ill.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(looking slowly towards the clock)</stage> In a few hours I shall be childless—and
      those hours— <stage>(points to clock)</stage> I could not bear to hear them told. <stage>(the
      manner and voice of Holbein are very subdued and gentle, indicative of despair)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Grief and watching have unnerved you, father; but I am here to share with you. She will
      live—oh she must: youth clings hard to life, father—your skill will revive her.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(bitterly)</stage> My skill —oh my skill! <stage>(he endeavours to control his
      feelings, sits down by the table, leans his head on his hand , weeping--pause: she follows
      him)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Trust, then, to my love. But tell me what malady has seized her?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>I cannot tell ; but about three months ago, a rich English patient of mine, Mrs. Dacre, who
      remained here under my care, took a great liking to Margaret, and on leaving us invited her to
      accompany their party to Como: the idea pleased my child, and she left me. After a months
      absence she returned—</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>In good health?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Yes—but changed ; and from that hour I saw my poor child yielding slowly to some fearful
      invisible malady—without pain, with a smile always on her livid lip. You appeal to my
      skill—well ! I flew to it—and—do you know its value ? It endowed me with the anguish of
      watching my beautiful, my adored, my only one, wither under my very eyes! It enabled me to
      calculate the hours of her fleeting life with terrible exactitude.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>And there is no hope ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>None. When she awakes from the stupor in which my art has plunged her, she will exhibit every
      sign of health, except strength ; she will thank heaven for her happiness—and then—she will
      leave us !</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Lead me to her.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Stay! I will watch until her eyes unclose, and then she shall know of your arrival.
     <stage>Exit, L door</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>My sister dying, and Eric who was to have met me here-</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(without)</stage> The Signora Stella !</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>'Tis his voice.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(without)</stage> The Count Eric Mansfeldt!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Eric!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>Stella! dearest Stella! have I not faithfully obeyed you ?</p>
     <pb n="8"/> <stage>Servant appears at door at back: enter Eric, C. from L.; Servant retires, C. and L.</stage>
    <p><stage>(embraces her)</stage> The preparations for our marriage are complete.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Hush! Do not speak of our marriage—at least, not now!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>Stella, reflect that delay is ruin! I have just escaped from the prison to which my father
     consigned me when he heard of my intention to wed you; my father—an Austrian minister—can
     pursue me even here into Switzerland, and demand of the Canton to give me up.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Were my life at stake, I could not leave this house at such a moment. My sister is dying.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>Dying!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>To speak of love—while she breathes her last ! Oh ! leave me—leave me, Eric!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>I will not whisper a word of love—I will not intrude a look upon your sorrows, Oh ! I prize
     every gentle impulse of that heart too much. See—I go—but one word. I have learned that my
     father, in consequence of my escape from prison, has disinherited me, and petitioned the
     Emperor to deprive me of my rank and my commission. I will write to him, saying that I expect—I
     wish for nothing at his hands—not even his consent</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Write nothing of the kind. Say, that in spite of his injustice we await in hope and
     submission the moment when he will forgive. But go. <stage>(she looks off)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>May I see you again to-day?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Yes, bring me the letter !</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>Farewell ! <stage>(kisses her hand)</stage> Farewell !</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>They come ! 'tis she ! <stage>(waves her hand to Eric, who hurries out, C. and
     L.)</stage></p>
    <stage> Enter Holbein, leading Margaret, L. door. </stage>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Gently, gently!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(advancing to her)</stage> Margaret!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Stella! shall I reproach you with your cruel absence ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Do—but gently—you promised to be calm.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>You hear how he goes on—always thus—the least emotion on my part terrifies him. One would
     imagine that I was in some mortal peril.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Oh—the—the idea!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Do I look ill, Stella?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>More beautiful than ever.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>And I feel strong—very, <stage>(leans on Holbein)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>I said you would wake refreshed.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Thank heaven I am so—and so happy! <stage>(Holbein and Stella exchange looks)</stage>.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>You must be fatigued now?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Fatigued! <stage>(to Stella)</stage> You hear him! I am scarcely risen-but I am
     fatigued—provoking! <stage>(sits on the couch, and is attracted by the sight of Stella's shawl,
      which Rouble has previously <pb n="9"/> thrown over the back of his couch)</stage> Oh! what a love of a
     shawl!- Cashmere? <stage>(examines it)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(to Stella)</stage> Spare her the least emotion; let her dream on. Nurse her delusion,
     <stage>(crosses to Margaret ; Stella goes L.— kissing her)</stage> Farewell
     !—<stage>(aside)</stage> and it may be the last—it may be --<stage>(aloud)</stage> I shall not
     be long. <stage>(aside to Stella)</stage> Remember!  <stage>Exit,C. and L.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Stella! at last we are alone—oh! Stella, how I have longed—longed for this moment !
     <stage>(embracing her and smiling)</stage> You are the dear Esculapius, who alone could "minister to a mind diseased."</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Margaret—you are not happy ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>I do not know—but you shall tell me—what I am. Three months ago I visited Como.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>With Mrs. Dacre— I heard so.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>We were staying is a large hotel, built on the very verge of the lovely lake. One night,
     after we had retired to rest, I was roused from sleep by a dreadful sensation of oppression,
     the room was filled with a dense smoke—confused cries, mingled with the roar of flame,
     bewildered my senses. I flew to the window and shrieked for help—I remember the look of the
     upturned faces of the mob—presently I distinguished an Austrian officer rush from the crowd and
     plunge into the sea of flame—my senses fled. When I awoke, I found myself in the arms of this
     stranger—he had saved my life. My first sensation was one of shame—so burning, so bitter, that
     I almost hated him. The next day he visited Mrs. Dacre; how I received him I cannot tell; he
     left us —</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>You have not seen him since ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>No ; but his noble countenance and gentle voice are never absent from my imagination.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Your hate turned into love ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Love! oh, yes—love! but so dreamy, so wild, and so hopeless—fed by my own fancy, it grew and
     grew until it filled my whole existence; it seemed as if I had swallowed a sweet poison that
     gave me power to assemble all the days of my life—their hopes and fears—to mass them into one
     confusion, and gamble them away!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Be calm!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Oh! Stella—see—to speak of him revives me!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>It does—then tell me, have you not even heard of him since then ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>No ; I fear my manner so discouraged him, and yet he might have known—do not laugh at my
     folly, Stella, when I tell you the mad hope which animates me—Each day I expect him to appear
     before me—I know not how—and each day sees that hope expire,—but only to be renewed by the
     visions of the night !</p>
    <stage> Enter Eric, with a letter in his hand, C. from, L. down L. </stage>
    <p>I imagine even now that he has discovered my name—my retreat— <stage>(becoming
     excited)</stage> that he will appear before me—here—as in my dreams, and pour out his love at
     my feet, and claim me ! <stage>(sees Eric <pb n="10"/>and utters a stifled exclamation; rises, and fixes a
     look of extacy on him, then raises her arm and points)</stage> He! <stage>(she endeavours to
     articulate, but falls on the sofa, R. C.)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Margaret! my sister !—she faints ! <stage>(she hurriedly searches for her flacon, with which
     she endeavours to revive her)</stage> Oh! why did you come ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>You desired to see this letter.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Not now—not now! Leave it.</p>
    <p><stage>(Eric places the letter on the table)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Await me there! <stage>(points to door, L.—exit Eric)</stage> She revives— she
     breathes—Margaret!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(reviving)</stage> Oh, what joy!—my life !—I feel it here again— <stage>(places her
     hand on her heart)</stage> it rushes back—free—free</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>My sister—dearest—be calm !</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(raising herself)</stage> I saw him—I saw him—there!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Whom?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>My preserver—him!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Heaven!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Did not you see ? He came in at that door—a letter was in his hand.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Eric!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Where—where is he? Speak! 'Twas not my disordered brain ?—say it was not! <stage>(looks round
     and sees letter on the table)</stage> No, no—'twas true: see the letter on the table—he left
     it—ah!</p>
    <p><stage>(she rises, and faltering steps attempts to reach the table)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Margaret! <stage>(interposing her arm; Margaret availing herself of Stella's arm for support,
      reaches the table; seizes the letter, and then falls from weakness on her knees, clasping the
      letter to her breast with childish glee)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>I have it—ha, ha! I have it!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> I am lost.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Let me read and then die—let me read! <stage>(opens letter and looks at it)</stage> I
     cannot—I—no—nothing—a cloud passes over my sight.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Let me read!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Do—yes—quick—there <stage>(gives Stella the letter)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Heaven inspire me!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Now, now!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>A moment to—to—the writing is—is strange to me.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>How tedious you are!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(appears to peruse the letter, but by her manner intimating that she is inventing what
      she pretends to read)</stage> "Since the hour— when fortune enabled me to save a life,—which
      has since proved so—precious to me—I have loved you —"</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>He loves—he loves me !</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(still pretending to read)</stage> " If I have not till now pleaded my passion, it was
     that your manner so discouraged me—I dared not risk the confession—"</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>'Twas that—I said so—did I not ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>" I dared not risk the confession, but unable to endure my misery, I determined to discover
     your retreat, and. to learn my  <pb n="11"/>fate, but until I hear it from your own lips—let this avowal, I beseech you, be a secret from
     all—Your devoted "</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Well, well——</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>"Eric."</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(clasping her hands on her heart)</stage> Eric!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Again you faint—your forces abandon you.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>No, Stella, no—they come—they come—flocking round my heart, from which, like the arid rock
     struck by the prophet's rod, there gushes out a stream of life ! Let me drink deep—-deep; I
     quench the thirst of death.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>You are happy, then?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Very—very happy ! Not as before—but calm—</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>My poor Margaret!</p>
    <stage> Enter Holbein, C.from L. </stage>
    <p>My father! <stage>(tears letter)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>What do you do?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside)</stage> He desired it should be a secret—hush! <stage>(goes up and throws the
     fragments into the fire)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(following her with her eyes)</stage> Still—to—to lose it—I wished—<stage>(makes a
     gesture as if she would have kissed it)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(advancing—aside)</stage> I could not conquer my anxiety— <stage>(aloud)</stage> There
      is fever on your cheek—you feel an oppression.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(rising)</stage> I do: there is no air here. Let us walk into the garden; I would see
     the flowers, and feel the sun. <stage>(leans on Holbein)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>The fatigue—</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>And besides <stage>(to Stella)</stage> we may meet him.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Him-whom?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Ah ! I must not say—It is a secret yet—is it not Stella?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>A secret?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Yes, father; the secret of my life.</p>

    </sp>    <stage rend="alignRight">[Exit Holbein, leading Margaret out slowly, C. and R.</stage><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Oh, what fatal—fatal chance has thus entangled my love and hers. Oh, had I not deceived
     her—had I read the letter, the real one, it would have killed her. No—I have at least cheered
     the last moments of her existence—she will not live to discover the fraud. <stage>(goes to
     door)</stage> Eric !</p>
    <stage> Enter Eric, L. </stage>
    <p>You must instantly escape from this house.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>Escape!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Margaret, did you not recognize in her the lady you rescued from the flames of Como?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>'Twas she!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Love for her preserver—for you—has preyed upon her life —this is her malady.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>Stella, it cannot be.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>It is—she confessed it to me—her rival; her heart has wasted with this passion; she lives but
     from hour to hour. I chose that her last moments should be happy, and so—so I deceived her. I
     told her you loved her—she believed me, poor child; and  <pb n="12"/>when I saw her life almost restored—oh,
     could I have made a dearer sacrifice at that moment, I would not have hesitated—so—go—go
     —Eric—quit this house—the town—now at once, <stage>(taking his hand)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>I cannot.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(drops his hand)</stage> You refuse me ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>I have just received a challenge, <stage>(produces letter)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>Some paltry foe.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>Pardon me ! it is a name of some value—commercially speaking—Rouble, the banker, at
     Milan,</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>A madman!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>By an oversight, or a commercial habit, the letter is signed Rouble &amp; Co., but the
     contents surpass the signature in singularity, <stage>(reads)</stage> "Sir, I have seen you
     enter the house of Dr. Holbein twice within the hour; you are young and handsome—I demand
     satisfaction; for which purpose I beg you will await me, where you are, for a few
     minutes.—Your obedient servant, Rouble &amp; Co-"</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>No address!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>None.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>He does not know your name—remain, concealed here— he shall be denied admittance.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>You ask me to remain ! remember, should I meet her </p></sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1"><speaker>Stel. </speaker><p>Ah! I forgot—no—go—go but for my
     sake.</p>
    <stage> Enter Holbein and Margaret, L. C. </stage>
    <p>Ah ! too late. "Tis she. <stage>(goes up R. round to L. C.)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>I told you the fatigue would be too much.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(seeing Eric)</stage> Ah!—'tis he!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>What means this strange re-animation? <stage>(sees Eric)</stage> A stranger! Pardon me, sir—I
     did not see you. Whom may I have the honour to address ?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>The Count Eric, son of the Duke Von Mansfeldt, Austrian Minister at Milan.</p>
    <stage> Enter Rouble, C. from L. </stage>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Many thanks, Signora, for these particulars.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Sir! This intrusion !</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>I believe I have the pleasure of addressing Dr. Holbein.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>The same, sir.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Your attendance is required, Dr. Holbein.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> On whom, sir?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>That is impossible to say—but it will be on this gentleman if I have any luck—if not, on
     me.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>You mean that you wish me to attend a duel about to take place between yourself and Count
     Eric.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Your intelligence is equal to your skill <stage>(bows)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(who has risen on the word "duel!")</stage> A duel! What does he mean?</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>You see, sir, you alarm my child.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p>Father, it must not be !</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M3">
    <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
    <p>Excuse me, madam, he has but one alternative ; and that is, to explain to me the motive of
     his presence here.</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p>The tone you assume, sir, precludes any reply but one.</p>
    </sp> <pb n="13"/><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p>No, no, I—I will tell you—this gentleman is here in my father's house to claim my sister's
     hand in marriage. <stage>(Margaret sinks back exhausted on a chair; movement of surprise. Eric
     and Stella exchange looks of confusion)</stage></p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Marriage!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(aside to Eric)</stage> Speak—Eric—oh spare the last hours of my poor dying sister;
     she will not survive to discover the deceit. Speak, I implore</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M4">
    <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(L. embarrassed)</stage> Dr. Holbein, if the moment be ill chosen, this gentleman must
     furnish my excuse; and, however strange or sudden the proceeding may appear, I trust my
     position, more painfully embarrassing than you. are aware, will excuse me. Yes, sir— I—I—I came
     to ask you to bestow on me the hand of your daughter, she permits me <stage>(looking at
     Stella)</stage> to demand it-</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_M5">
    <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
    <p>Margaret!</p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F2">
    <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(embracing Holbein)</stage>. There is my secret, father. </p>
    </sp><sp who="#L0106_F1">
    <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
    <p><stage>(L. C. clasping Eric'S hand aside)</stage> Oh, thanks, dear Eric— thanks! </p></sp>
    <trailer> Tableau, and end of Act I.</trailer>
  </div><div type="act">
    <head>Act II.</head>
    <stage>Scene II.—An elegantly furnished Boudoir in the house of Stella, at Milan; vases of
     flowers, pedestals, statues, C. doors, doors R., chimney L., cabinet R., under window, chair,
     small round table R.C., writing table in front R. C., two chairs, sofa L. C., square table L.,
     with wreaths, bouquets, &amp;c, square table L. under window, two chairs L., four pedestals,
     two statues, two vases of flowers, square table at back, with. clock, candelabra, &amp;c. A
     Servant, in livery, arranging the room.</stage>
    <stage> Enter Rouble, C. doors from L. </stage>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>The Signora is not visible! <stage>(Servant takes hat and stick)</stage> True. Last night,
      she surpassed herself in Norma—she requires rest, <stage>(remarks the bouquets and
      wreaths)</stage> All the trophies of her triumphs—there is my wreath. I distinguish, my
      bouquet, <stage>(takes up an enormous bouquet)</stage> Hum! <stage>(looks at his
      watch)</stage> She will not emerge from the arms of Morpheus for an hour. Ah ! lucky Morpheus
      ! I wish I was Morpheus. <stage>(to the Servant)</stage> I will leave a note for the Signora.
      <stage>(gives the, Servant a piece of gold; he arranges writing table quickly) </stage> How
      fond they are of me in this house—all, except—Ah ! well ! <stage>(to the Servant)</stage>
      Leave me ! <stage rend="alignRight">[Exit Servant C. and L. </stage><stage>(Rouble sits at the table R. H., cogitates ; then,
      suddenly, as if struck by an idea)</stage> Ah ! <stage>(writes and repeats)</stage> " I
      respect your repose, although you have ruined mine." (that's neat) " I would have seen you for
      a moment—perhaps for the last time;  for Heaven knows if I should survive an appointment which
      I have accepted for this morning—see how you have transformed  the most pacific of human
      bankers." (too true—I have become
      <pb n="14"/>a nuisance to society!) "Last night, at the Scala, I sat beside a wretched maniac,
      who began to criticise your talents, your appearance. I expostulated, he replied, and I threw
      him over into the pit. This morning we meet; and if I fall, he kind enough to apply, post
      paid, to Signori Massi and Kaub, my notaries, who hold my will—it bequeaths to you my fortune.
      Office hours between 10 and 4. Your faithful servants, Rouble &amp; Co." <stage>(rings bell,
      folds and seals letter. Servant re-enters down C.)</stage> Listen! you will give this letter
      to the Signora when she awakes, no—it might give her a disagreeable emotion, place it on the
      salver, with her chocolate—she takes chocolate? <stage>(Servant bows)</stage> then with her
      chocolate <stage>(rises, gives another piece of gold; Servant brings his hat and stick, takes
      letter from table, and exit, C.)</stage> That fellow little knows he is likely to lose an
      excellent customer—farewell, Stella, farewell—no—she comes.</p>
     <stage> Enter Stella, followed by Maid, R. 3 E. </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, yes, I will sing at their concert; and stay, on my dressing table you will find a
      rouleau of gold—send it to them with my best wishes.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F6">
     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, madam. <stage rend="alignRight">[Exit,R.door.]</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(advancing, L. C.)</stage> Brava, bravissima !"</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(impatiently)</stage> Mr. Rouble—already ? really this is too bad.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>This concert is for the benefit of the Foundlings; and, in spite of your fatigue, you
      consent.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Enough, enough—a foundling myself, I feel as if such unfortunates are my only relatives.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>The concert begins at twelve, if I could only get there in time.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(gladly)</stage> You will not be there then ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>An affair of—of importance, <stage>(aside)</stage> Life and death <stage>(aloud)</stage>
      which may detain me some time.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>I hope so.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Eh ? You hope ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Now tell me, what good fortune procured me the—the <stage>(impatiently)</stage> pleasure of
      your early visit?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>First, I wished to see you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(yielding to a comic despair)</stage> Ah ! Oh !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>And then to give you, news from Switzerland.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Of my sister—of Margaret?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>My head clerk was obliged to go to Venice last week on business of the house. I desired him
      to call on his road at Geneva.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>But that is nearly in the opposite direction.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>It is exactly; but I knew you would be glad to hear from home. I saw, when you quitted them,
      how unwillingly you returned to fulfil your engagement at the Scala—I was delighted.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Delighted that I was furious. I remember I felt as if I could have done your radiant face a
      mischief.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Precisely; it is only when you are out of temper that I engage your attention.</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="15"/>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(C. smiling)</stage> Poor fellow—!tis true, <stage>(gives him her hand)</stage>
      Pardon me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R.C. kissing her hand delighted)</stage> Don't mention it. Yes, when I see you
      smiling, and wrapped in happy thoughts, I am wretched. I know you are thinking of some
      handsome rival; but when your eyes flash, and your brow thunders, ah, I am in my element.
      <stage>(with the supremest satisfaction)</stage> I know you are thinking of me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(stamping)</stage> Mr. Rouble, you are intolerable.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Ah ! you are going to accord me a thought ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Will you tell me the news of Margaret? You will drive me mad.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Here it is—her health improved from day to day, and at last she became restored so
      wonderfully, that the good old doctor made a bonfire of his library in commemoration of what
      he calls his second birthday.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>But-but Count Eric ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>My head clerk says the young Count looks pale and low- spirited.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Poor Eric—what a situation I left him in.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Now that your sister is recovered, they wish to fix -the happy day.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>The hap—happy—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Of course; but the young Count's father positively refuses his consent.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Good—good !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>So the unhappy young man proposes to return to Milan this week. Now I may be of use, for, in
      my quality of banker, I take a large portion of the new loan—my interest is above par at Court
      just now. I will speak for the young couple.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>What business is it of yours, I beg to know? <stage>(crossing to R. aside)</stage> It is
      fated that this man should be my evil genius.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>True, and besides—my appointment, <stage>(looks at his watch)</stage> Eh ? I have not one
      minute to spare. <stage>(goes up—stops)</stage> A word, and I am gone—you remember you told me
      that I had a rival; well excuse the candour of my avowal—but I don't believe it.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>No.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>No; for since your return to Milan, no such person has appeared—now, confess, that all this
      was done to tease me, and that this terrible rival is—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Whom?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Myself.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>You !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Rouble &amp; Co.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>This is too much! Then let me dispel your doubts, since you will assume that air of stupid
      fatuity. I tell you that this very night I will become the wife of—.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Twenty minutes past, Signora: I tear myself away—but I see—I leave you occupied with my
      image. Ah, Signora—<stage>(sighs)</stage> I have the honour</p>
     <stage>(bows reverentially, and Exit C. and L. </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>There ! <stage>(walks about)</stage> He leaves me now—the only time I
      <pb n="16"/>wished him to remain—the provoking wretch. I was just about to bring his castle in
      the air about those ears I could have boxed for their length. Yet, poor man, his unfortunate
      love is his only fault. <stage>(flings herself on the sofa, taking up her bouquet)</stage> Oh!
      if he did not love me, how fond of him I could be! But beside Eric <stage>(throws bouquet
      away)</stage> all men look so mean—so poor.</p>
     <stage> {Eric appears at the back.} </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Stella !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Eric! dear Eric! <stage>(runs to him; they advance together)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Your sister is out of danger.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> I knew it, but not from you. What letters you wrote me ! how
      short—how cold !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>What could I do ? She was there—ever speaking—dreaming of you—leaning over my shoulder as I
      wrote. Could I have escaped—but no—you—you compelled me to remain.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>I condemned you, my dear Eric, to a sad and wretched time. And now, tell me—when you
      left—when danger no longer threatened her, and she was able to hear the intelligence—how did
      yon manage to convey it to her.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Convey it? I—I—I cannot conceal it—Stella—I had not the courage to make the avowal, and I
      flew to you for help. When I determined to declare myself, the image of the old man rose up
      before me—his pale face and trembling up—his agony. And Margaret!—to avow to her that for two
      months I had made her the dupe of an imposture—unwind her arms from round my neck, and thrust
      her love aside—Stella, I could not do it !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>I have heard of your embarrassment: I alone could understand the painful trial which you
      endured for my sake.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>If absent from you, Stella, I was in the presence of your noble deeds- I know all: that you
      have been the support of your benefactor and his daughter—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Let us not speak of this, but of yourself. You look pale, dearest!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>No, no—I am free—now. In that house I could not breathe freely—oh ! if I could describe what
      I suffered—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>I can conceive it. To see that poor girl, and pursue a feigned passion ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Yes; a—a—as you say—a feigned—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>To fear lest a word, a look might betray you, and condemn her again to death!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>And then the confidence— the faith—the simplicity of her love! And her father,—that was
      almost the worst—his gratitude, his affection, it stifled me. I was his divinity ! his prodigy
      ! his son! I had saved his child—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Eric ! you exaggerate. To encourage in pity a love you cannot return, is false feeling.</p>
     <stage> Enter Servant, C. from L., with a salver, cup of chocolate, and the letter on it that
      Rouble wrote—she takes the letter—he places the salver on table and retires) </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F6">
     <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
     <p>This letter, Signora, was left for you by Monsieur Rouble,</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="17"/>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(C.)</stage> Well, read! Have I any secrets from you ? and this, above all. It comes
      from a lover.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(L. C, opens and reads)</stage> Ah!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>I told him I was on the point of marriage; doubtless it is a tirade of reproaches, and the
      usual ejaculations of despair.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>No, not one; he is going to fight with some person who, it appears, insulted you in his
      estimation ; and in the event of his death, he has bequeathed you his fortune. What a noble
      fellow— how he must love you ! <stage>(gives her the letter)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Eric ! you seem to advocate his cause.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>No ; but one cannot help sympathizing with a feeling so noble and sincere.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Enough of this folly! My return to Milan, and your continued absence, has appeased the anger
      of your father. We must take advantage of our temporary security. Every necessary preparation
      has been made, and our marriage can be privately performed.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>And we can quit this town—this country for ever !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>You are right, Eric—for her sake.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>I dare not think of what we have done, and yet to leave them thus!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>How if we write to them?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>I would rather write my own death-warrant! But you— you, Stella—dictate to me. <stage>(sits
      at table, R. C, leans his head on his hand, and appears absorbed in wretchedness)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(dictating)</stage> " Margaret,—If I have deceived you, forgive me; I would I could
      love you "</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>No—not so, I think.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Well, how would you—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Must we say that? Can't we say that—that—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>What?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Stay !—let me see. <stage>(after a moment's pause he writes)</stage></p>
     <stage> Enter Margaret, followed by Holbein, C. from L. </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>Wait for me, you impatient!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Stella! <stage>(runs to Stella)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(embracing her)</stage> 'Tis she! Dear Margaret! let me look at you—<stage>(embracing
      her again)</stage> dear, dear sister!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>There's a transformation !—a metempsychosis—it is another form. Eh! that dear child exists
      against every rule of the therapeutic art ! I don't know how she does it; but she has made
      Galen a fool.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Well!—here we are—here in the room you have so often described to me. <stage>(looks round,
      as removing her bonnet and shawl, then places them on the sofa, L. C.)</stage> I feel a
      sentiment of happiness I cannot explain, <stage>(sees Eric)</stage> Ah! yes, I can explain.
      Eric ! what ! you have been here all this while, yet never said a word ? Dearest Eric—
      <stage>(runs to him)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Margaret!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>What?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>It is not the custom here in town to speak to thus to gentlemen.</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="18"/>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>But my lover—my husband—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Still—in public—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Very well—in public we will not. <stage>(to Eric)</stage> Do you know. dearest—<stage>(to
      Stella)</stage> We are not in public now, you know—are we?—and when we are alone—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(biting her lip)</stage> Alone !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>Ah! see—he was writing to you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>To me ? Oh. let me see it!—his first letter! <stage>(runs to the table and snatches
      letter)</stage> Let me see! <stage>(reads)</stage> "My own dearest Margaret, <stage>(Stella
      starts)</stage> You alone can judge the sincerity of the passion which I have for you ; and
      yet I must tell you"—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(slowly turns her eyes on Eric, who stands in petrified confusion)</stage> What?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>That's all!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> At that moment you entered, and—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>And spared us a farrago of torments, and vows, and promises, which he can afford you at your
      leisure. <stage>(they sit on the sofa apart and speak low)</stage> What a picture for an
      artist, eh ? there, that's way they go on from morning till night.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Indeed !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>Even when they walked out, it was always to sit in the grotto—you remember, at the farthest
      end of the garden.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Rather too far from the house for—for prudence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, I told her it would fatigue her, but it did not in the least.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, Stella, dear! only think of his father refusing his consent to our marraige-Eric is so
      unhappy about it you can't think. <stage>(to Eric)</stage> Do you hear, sir ? How foolishly
      you sit there— are you tongued-tied ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, it is tied in a true lovers knot. He is lost in admiration of your volubility—you
      talk—talk—talk—it is delightful.</p>
     <stage> Enter the Servant, C. from L. </stage>
     <p>Your carriage waits, Signora,</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>It is the hour of the concert—had I dreamed of your arrival, I would not have engaged
      myself—but I must leave you, dear Margaret.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>May I not accompany you ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>I forbid it—no—you have scarcely arrived from a long and fatiguing journey. I will go with
      you, Stella—you, Margaret, will remain.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Come, dear father—come, Eric.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>No, thank you—since I am condemned to the house, Eric shall remain with me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>You hear your sentence?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Thank you for taking away papa.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(hastily)</stage> Yes, yes, <stage>(crosses to Eric, who places her shawl on her
      shoulders aside)</stage> avail yourself of this moment.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> How?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> From this hour your imposture becomes unmanly
      <pb n="19"/>——for her sake I asked you to deceive—for her sake I now entreat you to confess.
      <stage>(Eric makes a gesture of consent)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>Now, Stella—ah! how proud I feel to walk with you. <stage>(turns and smiles on Margaret and
      Eric)</stage> I say—you lovers—he! he! look at them, Stella, they wish us now at the—mischief,
      they do. There, we are going, he ! he ! he !</p>
     <stage> Exit with Stella, C. and L. </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(pasting his hand across his brow)</stage> And now, she must learn to hate me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>I thought they would never be gone. Oh, dear Eric, what a miserable three days I have
      passed—how have you endured them?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Margaret, listen to me !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, love—but you need not fatigue your voice with such a distance.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(sitting beside her)</stage> Do you know that every smile you bestow on me is
      torture—the caress I cannot avoid—seems to be a brand—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, Eric, I have seen this; while my life was yet in danger, all your thoughts were mine;
      your eyes met mine, and turned their gaze about my heart—they seemed to lift it up to life. My
      health returned ; and as it came, I saw a grief creep over you —my heaven faded from me—and I
      regretted my days of suffering when you were all my own.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Margaret !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Confess to me—all—all—nothing is wanting to my happiness but to share a grief with you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>You don't know what you ask me; and yet—yet you must know it. I have now to put your love to
      a sad proof.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>A proof!—go on!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>If your faith, Margaret, were blinder than your love— your hopes in visions—what would you
      say?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(Smiling)</stage> I would say—Eric restore me to the grave from which you rescued
      me—let me dream on or die.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(hesitating and in great agitation wipes his forehead)</stage> And if this union must
      bring ruin upon me—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>You! were it so, a very little spot of ground would hide me from you, and the rest of the
      wide world would never bury your despair—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>And yet—Oh, heaven, yet—this marriage is impossible! <stage>(he rises)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(rising)</stage> Impossible! You are serious ! how impossible— speak—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>I—I cannot—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>You must.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(hurriedly)</stage> Since my arrival here, I have seen my father— </p></sp><sp who="#L0106_F2"><speaker>Mar.</speaker><p>Yes—yes.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Not only does be refuse his consent to our marriage, but threatens me with every persecution
      his anger can devise—If I could have shared my fortune with you—</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="20"/>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Is that all—I can teach you to bear poverty—want and I are old friends;
      <stage>(smiling)</stage> for years I received him clandestinely in my chamber where he watched
      my needle; my father knew nothing of this lover—are <hi>you</hi> jealous of him ? yet then I
      was alone; but now we are two, two? what do I say, three! you, I , and love <stage>(placing
      her hands in his)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Love, yes <stage>(passionately)</stage> love irresistible—eternal <stage>(clasps her in his
      arms and kisses her)</stage></p>
     <stage> Enter Stella, C. from L. </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> Eric !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Ah!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>'Tis no one—only Stella—come, sister, and hear this monster—would you believe it; he wanted
      to persuade me that our marriage was impossible.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Indeed !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, and he really would have it so; you never saw such a state as he was in; but I
      convinced him of his folly <stage>(crosses to Stella)</stage> could I exist without your
      love—or yours, Stella, and yet I must confess that once—Oh, I shall never forgive myself—I—I
      felt—ha ! ha !—positively jealous.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Jealous!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Of—of whom?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(to Stella)</stage> Of you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Of me !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, as you were quitting us. Two months ago when you bade him farewell, I saw you, and you
      looked on him almost—I thought, that is—almost as <hi>I</hi> look.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>You—you thought so !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Yes—and it haunted me so, and then—I said to myself— well, were it so, could I not die, and
      leave her to love him without remorse <stage>(Stella and Eric regard each other in mute
      despair)</stage></p>
     <stage> EnterRouble, his arm in a sling, C. from L. </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R)</stage> Brava, Signora, bravissima—I was in time for the concert—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Dear me, Mr. Rouble, what is the matter with your arm?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Nothing, a—mere—a—I fell down, that is all.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R.C.)</stage> You are so awkward.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Not so very, <stage>(makes a slight gesture, as in fencing)</stage> I
      have confined him to the house for six weeks. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Ah, Signora, how you sang
      that Scena.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Yes; and some unhappy pair of feet would persist in an encore.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>There they are. <stage>(pointing to his feet)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>'Twas you, sir—you—always you!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Yes. I found a difficulty in applauding with one hand, and so — <stage>(makes a gesture of
      stamping)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>And I was burning to get back here ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, I warmed them up—they made you come on four times.</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="21"/>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Are you created to be my tormentor ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(to Margaret and Eric)</stage> You hear? What an extraordinary being it is —she
      treats her worshippers worse than Juggernaut treats his.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Mr. Rouble, have I not begged you to spare me these painful and useless visits?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Repeatedly; but at this moment it is not exactly to you my presence here is due.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Indeed ! to whom then ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>To the Count Eric.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>To me?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>I have had an interview with his noble father, and another with the prince. Ah, Signora, he
      is not so proud as you—he is very glad to see me. I have procured from the Minister this
      letter.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>To me. <stage>(takes letter, tears it open, reads hastily)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>From your father ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Ah! can it be</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>What?—what?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>I will tell you—<stage>(crushes the letter up)</stage>—later.</p>
     <stage> Enter Holbein, C. from L. </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R. C.)</stage> I cannot believe it—it is quite impossible !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, my dear sir—many thanks to your stick that seconded my heels.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>Can you believe it ? Stella is about to be married.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Married?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>This very night.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Sir, I demand satisfaction! No—I forget; 'tis of you Signora, I—no, that is—who—who—says
      so?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>I was at the concert.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>I saw you—and your stick, many thanks.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>Beside me sat a gentleman of clerical appearance, he joined me in exclamations of delight,
      and I could not help thanking him for his enthusiasm: with tears of gratitude, I said, pardon
      me, sir, but it is my child—my Stella. I have just arrived this morning. "Ah!" he replied, in
      a low whisper, "I see, to be present at the marriage this evening," And as I hesitated to
      understand, he added, "Fear nothing, I am the Abbé Ambrose."</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(aside)</stage> Destruction!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>"'Tis I who perform the ceremony." Stella, I cried— Stella married ! He perceived my looks
      of astonishment; and seeing he had betrayed himself, he began to applaud violently, and then
      quitted the room.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(L. C.)</stage> Stella !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Signora!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Well, yes—'tis true—I wished it to be a secret.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>From us ?—are we, then, strangers to you ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(evidently hurt)</stage> Perhaps, dear Stella, we are intruding on you— at this
      moment—</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="22"/>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Intruding—father—Margaret—I will confess all to you; but - but first, I would ask Eric's
      advice, ere I reveal a secret which, indeed, is not all my own.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>My dear child, I know that which you do will be right —I seek to know nothing.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>I ask but for a moment—leave me but for a moment, and do not doubt my love.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Stella, I cannot love and doubt too.</p>
     <stage rend="alignRight">[Exit Holbein and Margaret, C. and L,</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>And me—what have you to say to me?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(bowing)</stage> I have the honour</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>I believe it gives you pleasure to see the wheel of the idol pass over the body of your
      wretched adorer—ah! <stage>(sighs)</stage> Vishnou!
     <stage rend="alignRight">[Exit after Holbein, C. and L.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Eric, before I avow this secret to my sister—which, indeed— I have delayed too long—I wish
      to know the contents of that letter.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(L)</stage> I entreat you not to ask me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(C)</stage> What! you have secrets from me, Eric? <stage>(he silently hands her the
      letter. She reads)</stage> "My son, his highness can refuse Mr. Rouble nothing at the present
      juncture, you have employed a well chosen advocate, we cannot raise the new loan without his
      assistance, and that help he makes dependent on my consent to your marriage with the daughter
      of Dr. Holbein," (this man again) "such a connection is not what I hoped for my
      only son, but too thankful to have escaped the alliance with an actress that lately threatened
      our family—I suppose I ought to accept the exchange with satisfaction; therefore, I am happy
      to announce to you that his highness graciously commands you to resume your former offices,
      and I add my paternal benediction." You see, Eric, I was right to demand this letter—what
      think you of it ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>The insult contained in that letter makes my former vows more sacred—more inviolate.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Dearest Eric—I know the sacrifice you would make, but my pride would revolt at entering a
      family who scorn and repel me—but, Margaret <stage>(pauses in agitation)</stage> Margaret
      is—is accepted —you do not love her, I know it—and for my sake—you—you consented to this
      fatal—no—I mean—this sacrifice—consent, for my sake, to prolong her error—she deserves your
      love, Eric—<stage>(pauses with increased agitation)</stage> and, besides, she loves
      you—and—some day, perhaps, this—this feeling in you which is now but a pretence —might become
      a—a—reality, <stage>(pauses—fixes her eyes on Eric, who remains immoveable)</stage> and you
      might, who knows, succeed in—that is—you might end in loving—<stage>(pauses, regards him
      fixedly, then suddenly exclaims)</stage> you do love her— </p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(starting back)</stage> I—I—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>You do: or would you have let me say so much, without confounding me with reproaches for the
      thought ? You do love her, Eric—deny it not.</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="23"/>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Stella, hear me. Was it not you who forced me into the arms of that poor girl, whom I would
      have fled,  until I could not? This rebel passion which you have discovered, and I do confess
      I will abjure—destroy——</p>
     <p>Stel <stage>(Starting up)</stage> And do you think I would owe my happiness to her death, to
      your pity, and so deserve your father's curse, and— worse than all—my own contempt? You know
      me better Eric! No no! I yield her to you and now--the debt of gratitude is paid.</p>
     <stage> Enter Rouble, C. from L. </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Ah ! at last I have discovered you!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Sir! What means—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>But you do not carry it off thus, mark you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M4">
     <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
     <p>Speak lower, sir!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>I shall moderate my voice sir, as I please ?</p>
     <stage> Enter Margaret and Holbein C. from L. </stage>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>What noise is this ?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>I have found out the Abbé ; he could not resist the sentiments of my esteem <stage>(puts his
      hand into his pocket)</stage> I discovered his weak point and the Signora's secret. This very
      morning he received notice to be here at eight to-night to celebrate her marriage and he has
      the names of the parties.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(quickly)</stage> All but one—that of the intended—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Oh indeed ! and you will venture to deny that this very intended is in this room?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>He is in this room.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>It is Count Eric.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F2">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Eric!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>The man is mad—raving mad! Excuse him, dearest, joy has turned his little brains.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(R.)</stage> Oh then if not the Count who then?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(C., viciously)</stage> You !</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Me!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>Yes! You—you—you! Is that plain?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, oh! I am paralysed.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>If I did not send your names to the Abbé, it was because —because—I did not know them.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>John—Peter—Antony—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>But I did know the man who had defended my name from insult at the peril of his life, and
      who had bequeathed me his fortune .<stage>(gives Margaret the letter which Rouble wrote to
      her)</stage> Read, Margaret read.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>I knew it—it was a moral certainty—I felt my destiny— oh, oh, your husband— I can scarcely
      believe it.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>But, understand me, I give up nothing—Margaret <stage>(embracing her)</stage> is to be first
      with me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Of course—I come somewhere—third or—eh, very well — very well.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>I will remain on the stage.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>Clearly?</p>
    </sp>
    <pb n="24"/>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>I will devote to it my whole time and passion.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>I will study music at once.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>I ought to warn you, I have a hundred faults</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>I appreciate them all, and love them.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p>But I have a thousand more.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>New blisses to surprise me with? Ah Signora—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(with increasing impatience)</stage> And caprices without number.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>My fortune will satisfy them all.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_F1">
     <speaker>Stel.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(stamping with impatience)</stage> Ah ! it is impossible to hate that man.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p>She is to be my wife, my wi——Oh! <stage>(to Holbein)</stage> My dear doctor, allow me to
      congratulate you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M5">
     <speaker>Hol.</speaker>
     <p>When is the happy day to be?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0106_M3">
     <speaker>Rou.</speaker>
     <p><stage>(to the Public)</stage> To-morrow—let it be to-morrow—do ! it depends on you,
      consider our feelings, don't disappoint us! Then let to-morrow publish the reception of a new
      partner into the firm of Rouble &amp; Co.</p>
    </sp>
    <p>Holbein Rouble Stella Eric Margaret</p>
    <p>Right Left</p>
    <stage>Curtain</stage>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>