<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L0206">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt><title>'Twould puzzle a conjuror!: TEI edition</title><author>Poole, John</author><respStmt><resp>TEI conversion</resp><name>Lou Burnard</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt><distributor>Privately distributed by the Digital Lacy Project</distributor><idno type="LAE">L0206</idno><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">The Lacy Project waives all rights to the TEI encoding applied to this material, which is believed to be in the public domain. You may copy, modify, distribute and perform this work freely. </licence></availability></publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc><bibl type="origin" n="14.11"><author>Poole, John</author><title type="main" n="twouldpuzzleaconjuror">'Twould Puzzle a Conjuror!</title><title type="sub">A Comic Drama
       in two acts</title><extent>25 pp (UM copy: 252 - 277)<measure type="pp" quantity="25"/>
  <measure type="spCount" quantity="506"/>
  <measure type="spvCount" quantity="0"/>
  <measure type="txWords" quantity="10066"/>
  <measure type="spWords" quantity="9163"/>
  <measure type="stWords" quantity="903"/>
  </extent>
      <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 14, No. 0206</title><idno type="nic">N03186</idno></bibl><bibl type="surrogate"><ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.31175035148470">UC from
       HT</ref></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453194&amp;seq=252 ">UM from
       HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol14/L0206/L0206-um.pdf"/></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="TEI"><ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/L0206.html">TEI</ref></bibl><listEvent>
      <event type="firstPerf" when="1824-09-11" source="textNic" where="Haymarket">
       <desc>Premiered at Theatre Royal, Haymarket 11 Sept. 1824</desc>
      </event>
     </listEvent></sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc><!--S 2 ComicDrama F. FARCE--><textClass><catRef target="#sizeS"/><catRef target="#act2"/><catRef target="nic:F."/><keywords><term>FARCE</term></keywords></textClass><particDesc><listPerson>
<person xml:id="L0206_M1">
<persName type="role">Peter, Czar Of Muscovy </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="81">Pet.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="82">Pet</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0206_M2">
<persName type="role">Admiral Varensloff </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="16">Var.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0206_M3">
<persName type="role">Baron Von Clump </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="44">Clu.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0206_M4">
<persName type="role">Count De Marville </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="30">Mar.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0206_M5">
<persName type="role">Van Dunder </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="135">Dun.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0206_M6">
<persName type="role">Peter Stanmitz </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="116">Sta.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0206_M7">
<persName type="role">Van Block </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="31">Blo.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0206_M8">
<persName type="role">Officer </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="12">Off.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0206_M9">
<persName type="role">Waiter </persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L0206_F10">
<persName type="role">Bertha </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="38">Ber.</persName>
</person>



<person xml:id="L0206_mult">
<persName type="role">[Multiple speakers]</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">Omnes.</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="1">All.</persName>
</person>
</listPerson></particDesc></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change when="2026-01-11">Standardize header components</change><change when="2026-01-10">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change><change when="2025-11-02">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change><change when="2025-09-07">Metadata updated from new catalogue</change><change when="2024-10-03">Header enriched</change>
   <change when="2023-09-20">Header confected</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 
 <text><pb n="1"/>
  
  
  
  
  <front>
   <titlePage><titlePart type="main">'Twould puzzle a conjuror!</titlePart><titlePart type="sub">A comic drama in two acts.</titlePart><byline>by <docAuthor>John Poole</docAuthor>, Author of <title>Paul Pry</title>, <title>Simpson and Co.</title>, &amp;c. &amp;c.</byline><docImprint>Thomas Hailes Lacy, Wellingtron Street, Strand, London</docImprint></titlePage>
   <performance>
    <p>First Performed at the Theatre Royal, Haymarket, on Saturday, September 11th, 1824.</p>
   
   <castList>
    <head>Original Cast</head>
    <castItem><role gender="M">Peter, Czar Of Muscovy </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Cooper. </actor></castItem>

    <castItem><role gender="M">Admiral Varensloff </role><actor sex="M">Mr. W. Johnson. </actor></castItem>

    <castItem><role gender="M">Baron Von Clump </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Younger. </actor></castItem>

    <castItem><role gender="M">Count De Marville </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Coveney. </actor></castItem>

    <castItem><role gender="M">Van Dunder </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Liston. </actor></castItem>

    <castItem><role gender="M">Peter Stanmitz </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Harley. </actor></castItem>

    <castItem><role gender="M">Van Block </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Lee. </actor></castItem>

    <castItem><role gender="M">Officer </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Jones. </actor></castItem>

    <castItem><role gender="M">Waiter </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Coates. </actor></castItem>

    <castItem><role gender="F">Bertha </role><actor sex="F">Mrs. Chatterley. </actor></castItem>

   </castList>
 
    <p>Time in Performance, One Hour and a Half.</p>
   </performance>
   <div type="costume"><head>Costume.</head>
    <list>
     <item>Long-waisted coats with full skirts, long waistcoats, and trunk breeches, full-bottomed
      wigs and three-cornered hats, high-heeled shoes and buckles.</item>
     <item>Peter and Workmen wear their own hair.</item>
     <item>Bertha—Neat caul cap; dark velvet boddice, over white muslin body, and full short
      sleeves; stuff petticoat, coloured stockings, and high-heeled shoes.</item>
     <item/>
    </list>
   </div>
   
  
  </front>
  <body>
   <pb n="3"/>
   <head>'Twould Puzzle a Conjuror</head>
   <div type="act">
    <head>ACT I.</head>
    
     <head>Scene I.—The Dockyard at Saardam.</head>
    <stage type="setting">The Czar and Stanmitz discovered seated on a
      log of wood, and counting money. Czar L. H.; Stanmitz R. H.</stage>
    
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Well, well, what does it signify? You have to receive twelve ducats more than you expected;
      so let that content you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, but I'm puzzled—I'm bothered, you see; and I like— that is, I don't like—Look ye, my
      dear friend, Michloff, you want to persuade me that nineteen and twelve make twenty, and—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Ha, ha, ha! Look ye, my dear friend, Stanmitz, I am purse-bearer. I receive your month's
      pay—I lay out—and, at the month's end, I give you what remains; and so long as I don't attempt
      to persuade you that nineteen and twelve make fifty, you have no great reason to complain.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>But look ye: I earn twenty ducats a month; you have laid out nineteen for me—and instead of
      one, which, according to my calculations, remains, you insist—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (rises and comes forward)</stage>Plague take you, can't you put the money into your
      pocket, and be satisfied?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I can't help saying it is very odd. Before you came to work here at the dockyard at
      Saardam, I had a hard tug to make both ends meet. It was as much as I could afford to get
      drunk three times a week, and not do the thing as it ought to be done either. Now, that you
      are paymaster, I can get drunk regularly every night; aye, and in a way to do any man credit,
      yet have always money to spare. Peter Michloff, your mode of managing all this puzzles me: and
      if you were not a devilish good fellow—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>You'd take me to be the devil himself. Well, before I quit   this place, perhaps I may let
      you into my secret.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>And do you think of leaving us?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>I have now been absent from my native country a twelve-month. I have acquired some knowledge
      of shipbuilding, the object for which I came here, and it is time I should return home.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Our master, Mynheer Von Block, will be sorry to lose you, because you are the most
      industrious fellow in the yard: and I shall be sorry, because—hang it, Peter Michloff, I like
      you!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>And, hang it, Peter Stanmitz, I don't dislike you.</p>
    </sp>  <pb n="4"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Peter, you are my friend, and I think I may venture to let you into a secret.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>That you are in love with Bertha, the pretty niece of Mynheer Von Dunder, the old blockhead
      of a burgomaster.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Not exactly that, but I'm told that old Von Dunder has lately been very busy in his
      enquiries about me, and that makes me uneasy.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Why, surely you have done nothing to be ashamed of?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>No, not ashamed, but I'm cursedly afraid. But I'll tell you, I was born at Moscow.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Well, there is no crime in being born at Moscow; besides, that was no fault of yours.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>That's not it. Listen! It happened one day that a party of soldiers halted near my mother's
      hut; the commanding officer presently cast an eye at me, and was so amazingly taken with my
      appearance, that he requested I'd make one of them. I was about to   decline, but assuring me
      that the Czar Peter, our name-sake you know, having particular occasion for my services, would
      take it as an offence if I refused the invitation, he forthwith clapped a musket on my
      shoulder, and marched me off.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Aye, you were enlisted.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Enlisted! Why I can't say but I was. Now, I was always an independent sort of fellow, fond
      of my own way, and couldn't stomach being ordered about against my inclination.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>So, so!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I put up with it a long while though; till one bitter cold morning in December, just at
      three o'clock, I was roused from my comfortable warm sleep to turn out, and mount guard on the
      bleak blustering corner of a rampart, in the snow. It was too bad— wasn't it?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Well?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Well, as I couldn't keep myself warm, I laid down my musket and began to walk: then I began
      to run, and hang me if I ceased running till I found myself five leagues away from the
      outposts.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>So, then, you are a deserter!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>A deserter! You call that being a deserter, do you? Well, putting this and that together, I
      shouldn't wonder if I am.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>You know, my dear fellow, that if you are discovered, you will be shot.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I've some such idea. Indeed, it occurred to me at the time, so thinking it hardly worth
      while to be shot for being so short a distance,   as only five leagues away from my post, I
      made the best of my way to Saardam, and here I am.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>This is an awkward affair, indeed, and if Mynheer Van Dunder, the Burgomaster, were informed
      of it—however, be assured your secret is safe in my keeping.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I don't doubt you, for I suspect you're in a similar scrape yourself.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>I?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>There's something very mysterious about you, at any rate. No one knows who you are, or
      whence you come. And then, that strange man you have so many dealings with.</p>
    </sp>  <pb n="5"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>Admiral Varensloff!—A trader, a friend of my family, from whom he
      sometimes brings me little presents of money.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Well, Michloff, I don't desire to know more of your affairs than you choose to tell me, and
      so—Ah, ha! What, my little Bertha! <stage>(crosses to L.)</stage><stage>Enter Bertha, L.
      H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Don't talk to me. Let me recover breath. I should have been here ten minutes ago, had I not
      been obliged to run so fast.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>To run so fast? That's an odd mode of accounting for your delay.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>I've been obliged to go a mile about, to get rid of that French gentleman.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>What French gentleman? What French gentleman do you know?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Lord, Peter, don't be so impetuous. One who has been prying about the dockyard these few
      days past.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>  What could he have to say to you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>What no woman would be very angry at hearing, if I may judge from the little he did say.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>So then, he has spoken to you, and all he said you believed, no doubt.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>I'll leave it to you to determine. He said I was the prettiest woman in Saardam.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>And the most incorrigible coquette.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>He was too polite, Mr. Peter; besides, that is by no means my character. <stage>(sees the
      Czar in the corner, L. H.)</stage> Bless me, Mr. Michloff, <stage>(arranges her dress)</stage>
      I didn't perceive you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p> (R.)There, there, isn't one Peter at a time enough to set your cap at?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p> (L.)Good day to you, my little Bertha. Why surely you are not at words?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p> (C.)No! but your namesake here is so terribly jealous, that even should my uncle consent to
      the marriage I fear I never shall be able to make any thing of him.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (R. aside)</stage>I don't intend you should; but surely there is some cause for
      jealousy. Ever since the assembly of the Congress at Ryswick, and that ambassadors, and
      secretaries, and courtiers, and I know not what besides, are in our neighbourhood, it has been
      impossible for a pretty woman to—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Don't be uneasy, my little Peter. I dare say those gentlemen will be able to settle a treaty
      of peace without making my   surrender one of the articles. But I had almost forgotten the
      very matter I came about.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>What is it?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Mischief, I am afraid, as it always is, when my uncle, Van Dunder, puts on what he calls his
      official wig, and looks more than commonly grave and stupid. He is coming here.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>For what purpose?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>That is yet secret; but it is in consequence of an order he has just received from
      Amsterdam, and about which, as usual, in matters of importance, he seems to be amazingly
      puzzled.</p>
    </sp>  <pb n="6"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>Is my retreat discovered?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>Ah, my old colonel I suppose, uneasy at my absence, is making kind
      enquiries about me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>But who is that strange looking man that appears to be watching us?<stage>Enter Varensloff
      U.E.R.H., and makes a sign to the Czar.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>'Tis Varensloff! Fear not him. 'Tis a friend of mine. <stage>(crosses
      to R. H.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, a friend of your's, is he? <stage>(arranges her dress, and curtsies)</stage> Good day to
      you, Sir.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (places himself before her)</stage>Good day to you, Sir, good day.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (whispering the Czar)</stage>News from Moscow, Sire?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Hush! <stage>(they converse aside, U.E.R.H.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I don't like that man. He has always some secrets with Peter Michloff. If he's an honest
      fellow, why cannot he speak out before all the world?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>  He may have business with him, which it may not be necessary that all the world should
      know?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I fear there is something wrong between them. I have it—he's an usurer, he lends him money
      at a high rate, and in the end he will ruin him. He is continually bringing him papers to
      sign.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>I should be very sorry for that, but I must away, or my uncle may notice my absence.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I'll accompany you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>I'm not afraid of returning alone.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>It is not your returning <hi>alone</hi> <stage>(Czar comes L.H.)</stage> I'm afraid of; but
      the Congress you know. Take care, Michloff, what you do with that man, I don't like his
      looks.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Never fear him. You'll allow a friend <stage>(kisses Bertha.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Oh! a friend—certainly.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Thank ye, Sir. <stage>(Czar goes up)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (to Varensloff, who approaches with the same intention)</stage>Don't put yourself
      out of the way; you are merely a friend's friend. Come along,
      Bertha.<stage> Exeunt Stanmitz and Bertha, L.
      H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Ha, ha, ha! Whatever may be your credit, Count, with the Government of Holland, as
      Ambassador from the Czar, Peter of Muscovy, your reputation here, as the friend of Peter
      Michloff, is not of the best.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>Yet has your Majesty found me the faithful friend of Michloff, as I have ever been the
      honest counsellor of the Czar.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Honest! aye, and a bold one, too.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>Else, were I not your friend, Sire, you have long been absent   from your dominions, your
      subjects complain, 'tis now time that you return.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Have then my hours been idly spent? During these months of absence in this humble disguise,
      I have surely done more to promote the happiness of my people, and thence my own true glory,
      than the whole life of the Czar could have accomplished, if wasted in the careless ease of his
      Palace. Unknown, to all but you, I have travelled from land to land, and studied the useful
      arts for which each   <pb n="7"/>is renowned. These will I bring back to my own barbarians, by these will I
      civilize them—let them complain, posterity will decide between us. <stage>(crosses to
      R.H.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>Sire, 'tis only your presence can prevent an immediate revolt. The enemies of Russia are
      artfully fomenting the discontent of your people. Should they, discover the place of your
      retreat, they will doubtless endeavour to detain you here, for by your return their
      treacherous aim will be defeated.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Say no more. Our next despatches from Moscow will determine me. In the meantime let
      everything be prepared for my sudden departure, should such be necessary. Leave me—leave me,
      <stage>(crosses to L.H.)</stage> I must descend awhile from the business of the State—my
      fellow-labourer, in an humbler avocation,
      approaches.<stage> Exit Varensloff,
      U.E.R.H.</stage><stage>Enter Stanmitz, L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Michloff, I fear it is all over with me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>What has happened?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Here comes old Van Dunder, in close conversation with our master, Von Block; I heard them
      say something about Peter, and—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>  Psha! If that be all, I have as much cause for alarm as you. But come, to our work.
      <stage>(they go up.)</stage><stage>Enter Van Dunder, and Van Block, L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (an open paper in his hand, with a large seal)</stage>What can it be about?
      Important, no doubt—a special courier. What would I give now to know what it is the
      Burgomaster of Amsterdam has written to me about.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Why, then, don't you read the despatches?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Read 'em! why because—Oh, the ignoramus!—master of the dockyard indeed. You ought to be
      ashamed at asking such a question. What's this?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>The town seal of Amsterdam.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, you have sense enough to see that, have you? It is a Government despatch you
      perceive.<stage>Czar appears to listen.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>And what then?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>What then? As it was sent to me by express, don't you think it was the intention of
      Government that I should know what it is all about?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>To be sure—read it, then.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>“Read it, then!” That's very easily said. Look ye, Van Block—you may be a very good
      shipbuilder, but you know nothing of State affairs. Would it be fitting the dignity of the
      Burgomaster of Saardam, that he himself should read such a paper, with such a seal, and coming
      from such a person as the Burgomaster of Amsterdam? Would you have me treat it as if it was a
      paltry tailor's bill? Here—do you read it!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>  No, thank ye! I never meddle in State matters.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>You can't read—you can't read! Now, don't attempt to deceive me—I know what not being able
      to read is. Oh, the illiterate booby! But what is there wonderful in that? I'd bet a ducat,
      there is not a man in your service knows how to read.</p>
    </sp>  <pb n="8"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Will you?—done!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (to Stanmitz, who comes R.H.)</stage>Here, you—read this!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I'd rather not, thank ye, Sir! <stage>(goes up)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I was sure of it Come—the ducat!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Not so fast!—here's Michloff—a clever, intelligent fellow— try him. Michloff!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Do you think you could read this?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (comes R.H.)</stage>I'll try.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Come, let me hear what you call reading—though I don't expect you to read like a
      schoolmaster.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Nor like a Burgomaster.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Read—read!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (reads)</stage>“To Van Dunder, Burgomaster of Saardam.”</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>The ducat!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>That proves nothing—any booby might read that. Go on!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (reads)</stage>“The States-General have reason to believe that a foreigner, named
      Peter, has for some time past been working in the dockyard at Saardam. The interests of
      Government demand that this person, if discovered, be strictly watched, and detained at
      Saardam till further orders.”</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>  You don't say so!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>Varensloff was right, then. <stage>(reads)</stage> “Let your
      measures—”</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Let my what?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Your measures.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>There, you hear—I must take his measures!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (reads)</stage>“Let your measures to this end be prompt and vigilant, yet consistent
      with the utmost caution and secresy.— Signed, Vandermarch.”</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Is that all?—and are you sure you have made no mistake?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Certain.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Go along, and let me think. <stage>(Czar goes up)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Now pay me the ducat.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Is this a time to think of ducats? Here's a business which —an affair that—secresy—secresy,
      of course—not a soul shall know a word of the matter! This is certainly a most delicate, a
      most perplexing—I hardly know where to begin! “Detain him— and watch him—and discover him!”
      There is so much of it to do! I have it! I'll have him locked up in the guard-room, and then
      watching him will be the easiest thing in the world.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Wouldn't it be as well to begin by catching him?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>To be sure it would—but how? The idiot! Double or quits for the ducat, you can't tell me
      how!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>I'll order out all the men, and you may seek among them.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>The pretensions of that fellow! Ha, ha, ha!—why, any   blockhead might have thought of
      that.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Then, I wonder you didn't.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Go, and order all your men to appear before
      me.<stage> Van Block rings a bell,
      L.H.</stage><stage>Enter Twelve Workmen.</stage>—I've a shrewd notion this Peter is a
      suspicious character. “The   <pb n="9"/>interests of Government!” A State criminal! “Watch and detain
      him.”—Or a pickpocket—or a deserter!—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Oh lord! it's all over with me! <stage>(goes behind the others)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Are they all here?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_mult">
     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
     <p>All—all!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Now to be cautious! Stand forward, all of you! I'm to discover a man of the name
      of—<stage>(looks at the paper)</stage> What name did he say? The name you said was—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Peter!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Peter! Let me think—let me think! Ha! I have it! A bold stroke! <stage>(aloud)</stage> There
      is a man among you whose name is Peter. Don't deny it—I happen to know it.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>My name is Peter.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>There is a scheme for you! I've got him already.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Psha! as honest a fellow as any in my employ. Besides, Stanmitz's name is Peter.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Come, come—there is another Peter among you. I'm not to be deceived. Let the other Peter
      stand forth! <stage>(five Men step out from the rest)</stage> What! seven of you? What's to be
      done now? Now, isn't this enough to perplex—? Stand back, all of you, and let me think!
      <stage>(they retire to the rank)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>  Is not the Peter you are to discover a foreigner?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Now, I dare say you think yourself a very clever fellow; and you'll go about, saying you
      discovered he's a foreigner. Why is he not described so here? I wish you would not meddle with
      State matters. <stage>(to Men)</stage> There is a foreigner among you, called Peter— let him
      stand forth!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I—I am; but don't be hard with me, Mr. Burgomaster, and I promise—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Aha, my lad!—leave me alone to be prompt and vigilant.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>I am a foreigner.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Oh! What do you mean by a foreigner? Where were you born?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>At Moscow.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (to Stanmitz)</stage>And you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>At Moscow.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>At Moscow! No, no—they cannot both be born at Moscow. And your names?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Peter Stanmitz.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Peter Michloff.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Now, which of these can it be? <stage>(to Van Block)</stage> Send those men away—the sight
      of them confuses me.<stage> the Men go off U.E.R. and
      L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>What is it puzzles you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Puzzles me, indeed! It would puzzle a conjuror. There is no scarcity of Peters, you see. But
      the Burgomaster of Amsterdam is a blockhead. If he wants me to discover any Peter in
      particular,   he ought to have described his person—given me his surname—told me the street
      and the number of the house where he lives. I'd have discovered him soon enough then, I
      warrant you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Well, may they return to their work?</p>
    </sp>  <pb n="10"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Aye, that will allow me time to think. And hark'ye, you pair of Peters—do you two keep a
      sharp eye on each other; and if either of you escape, I'll hang you
      both!<stage> Exeunt Czar and Stanmitz,
      U.E.L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Well, what are you thinking about?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Stanmitz—Stanmitz? I've a great notion that's my man— that's my man!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>He? Psha!—he's as honest a fellow as the other.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>That's nothing to the point. I suspect his making love to my niece, Bertha—a thing I don't
      approve of. I'm to discover a suspicious character, and I'll—no—yes, I will—he shall be the
      man. I've plenty of Peters in hand; and if he should be the wrong one, it will be easy to give
      another. But who comes here?<stage>Enter Baron Von Clump, U.E.L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>'Tis a German gentleman lately arrived here. I suspect he is attached to the embassy.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>The embassy! <stage>(impatiently)</stage> Leave me to talk to him. The embassy! Must a
      Burgomaster speak twice? Leave us!<stage> Exit Van
      Block, L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>I believe you are the Burgomaster of Saardam?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I am—himself in person.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>My business with you is of the deepest importance. Be prudent—be secret—assist me to
      discover a certain person, and your fortune is made.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>  Fortune? If a discovery is your business, I flatter myself you've come to the right shop
      for that. But pray, Sir, who may you happen to be?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>That you shall know hereafter. Promise to be secret and faithful, and two thousand ducats
      shall reward the success of your search. You promise?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Promise!—two thousand ducats!—promise! Why not let me take my oath of it at once?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Listen! I am in search of a foreigner who is supposed to be at this place in disguise—a
      Russian.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>A Russian! <stage>(aside)</stage> Russia is in Moscow—'tis he! <stage>(aloud)</stage> I've
      got the very thing for you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Indeed!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Born at Moscow—name, Peter!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Hush! I perceive you are aware of the object of my visit here. I rejoice at having met with
      a man of so much shrewdness and penetration. You know him, then?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Know him? I know everybody—I know everything! I—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Burgomaster, the management of this business requires extreme delicacy and address, and I am
      persuaded I may entrust it to you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Only tell me exactly what's to be done, and as for delicacy, and address, and penetration,
      and so forth, bless you, they are here at my fingers' ends.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Does he know that you are acquainted with his real   character?</p>
    </sp>  <pb n="11"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>No, not exactly.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>That's well. Seek an opportunity of conversing with Peter, yet beware of intimating to him
      that he is discovered. Lead him adroitly to speak of the affairs of Russia; and, with seeming
      indifference, enquire his opinion, concerning the present views of the Emperor of Germany.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Russia, and the Emperor of Germany! Ah! I understand.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>For certain reasons, I cannot avow myself to him till I have sounded his sentiments. It is
      in this that your assistance will be serviceable to me. But be prompt, lest the French
      Ambassador, who is at Saardam, should anticipate us.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>The French Ambassador! What, he has a finger in the pie too! What can it all be about?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Be prudent, and the two thousand ducats I have promised you, will be the smallest of your
      rewards.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Two thousand! Will one Peter be enough for you? My dear Sir, if you want a dozen, I—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (crosses to R.)</stage>Some one approaches. I leave it to your discretion to
      intimate to him that you have conversed with me. In that, you will be guided by circumstances.
      In an hour we will meet again. <stage>(aside)</stage> At length I have discovered the Czar;
      and, through my means, his alliance with the Emperor is certain. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Be
      discreet. I doubt not, in the conduct of this affair, you will establish your reputation as a
      sound politician.<stage> Exit R.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>  Oh, of course. If I can make head or tail of the matter, the devil take me. Who can that
      man be? Great man, that's clear. Russia and the Emperor of Moscow—Germany, I should say. Two
      thousand ducats for telling Peter that— Well thought of—which Peter does he mean? Oh, here's
      the old bother over again! You —Mister!—he's out of sight. Let me think. I have it—there are
      but two: I'll try the first that comes, and if I'm wrong with him, I'm sure of being right
      with the other. Here comes Peter Stanmitz. I'm pretty sure he's the man. But what can he have
      to do with the Emperor of Germany? Now, either he's a great man in disguise, or a confounded—
      Ahem! ahem!<stage>Enter Stanmitz, L.H.U.E.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>He's here! My old Colonel has found me out, I dare say, and I'll know
      the worst at once.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Stanmitz, my good fellow, how do you do?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>“Good fellow!” Oh, the cruel, sneering rascal!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>My familiarity offends him. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Pardon the
      liberty, Sir: but I thought it better to be free with you, that it might not be suspected I
      know anything of your affairs.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (alarmed)</stage>My affairs! So, then, you are informed—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Informed! I fancy I am, indeed. Come, come, you had better not conceal anything from me. I'm
      in the secret.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>You have received information from my Colonel—eh?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Your Colonel, certainly. <stage>(aside)</stage> So then, that mysterious German is a
      Colonel. Well, that is something to know. <stage>(aloud, and <pb n="12"/>
      mysteriously)</stage> Beware of the French Ambassador! Should he discover   you, you are
      lost.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>The Russian Ambassador, you mean.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>The French Ambassador, I tell you. But don't be uneasy. I've had a talk with your Colonel,
      and he's your friend.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>The Colonel my—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Hush! He doesn't want to be known at present, so he has left it to me to pump.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Pump on me! An odd mode of punishing a deserter. Well, it is better than the halberts.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>To pump you, and to do it with seeming indifference. Ahem! Peter, what's your opinion of the
      Emperor of Germany?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>He's a devilish good fellow for anything I know to the contrary. But what is that to the
      point?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Everything. <stage>(aside)</stage> “Devilish good fellow!” I must not forget that.
      <stage>(aloud)</stage> Now, speak your mind freely to me, and we'll carry you through.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Will you? Then you are not my enemy?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I, your enemy! Lord bless you! <stage>(aside)</stage> This is the man.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Why didn't you speak out at once, and spare me all this alarm. So you think the matter may
      be made up?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Certainly, certainly. <stage>(aside)</stage> If I could but find out what the matter is!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Ha, ha, ha! It was a desperate bold trick of mine—was't it?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>  Oh, desperate! Ha, ha, ha! But if you would only just give me an idea; because it must be
      managed with address, and caution, and promptitude, and so forth, you know.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Hadn't you better explain to me?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>No doubt, no doubt; but hang me if I understand a syllable of the business.
      <stage>(aside)</stage> As to explanations, you see, we can't do better than leave it to the
      Colonel, since you say he is the Colonel, and he'll settle the business to the satisfaction of
      all parties.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Will he? My dear friend, do you see him instantly, make any conditions you please on my
      behalf, and—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>May I indeed! <stage>(aside)</stage> Then my fortune is made. <stage>(crosses to L.)</stage>
      Stick to the Emperor of Germany. Keep out of the way of the French Ambassador, say nothing of
      this business to any one, and —and—what a head I have for discoveries—I have found out three
      things already, that the German is a Colonel, that Peter Stanmitz is—I don't exactly know
      what—and that I—I never was so puzzled since the day I was
      born.<stage> Exit, L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Now, really the Burgomaster is a better fellow than I ever thought him. Well, since he has
      undertaken to get me out of this scrape, I can't do better than leave the affair in his hands.
      But what do I see!—'Tis Bertha, followed by—I shouldn't wonder if it were the same young
      Frenchman who was talking to her this morning.</p></sp>
    <stage>Enter Bertha, U.E.L., running, followed by the Count de Marville.</stage>
    <pb n="13"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>This time, my pretty damsel, you shall not escape me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Leave me, I desire, Sir, I don't know what you can see in me, to follow me about as you
      do.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>  Come, come, I see how it is, you have a husband, or a lover, and you are fearful he will
      interrupt us.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (coming forward between them)</stage>Nothing more likely.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Ah, ah! you are the happy man.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, I am the happy man! Peter Stanmitz. And whoever you may he, let me tell you, that—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Peter, Peter! do you want to get into a quarrel?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>Peter? should this be the Czar.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Don't you perceive the gentleman was only in jest?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (to Bertha)</stage>In jest, indeed! I'll not allow any one to run after you in
      jest.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Ah, you silly fellow! Had you rather it should be in earnest, then?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (observing him)</stage>Come friend, your hand, I have no intention to run away with
      your mistress, I assure you; my business here <stage>(pointedly)</stage> is to make a
      discovery.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>All the world is for making discoveries to-day. I wish you would make
      your discoveries at a distance, and leave us to ourselves.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>This is not he. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Your name is Peter?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (walking up to him)</stage>Peter or Paul, what business is it of yours? Upon my
      word, you are a very inquisitive fellow.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>I beg pardon, but perhaps you could inform me—<stage>Enter the Czar, U.E.L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Come, come, lad, didn't you hear the dinner-bell? I have been seeking you—why, what's to do
      here?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>  I'll tell you all about it, Mr. Peter. <stage>(Marville observes him)</stage> Here is
      Stanmitz in one of his jealous fits, because this French gentleman—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>You are a Frenchman, Sir? <stage>(aside)</stage> 'Tis as Varensloff suspected.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>What, you would find an excuse for him, would you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>That countenance, that deportment! I cannot be deceived here. Once more let me assure you,
      you have nothing to fear from me. <stage>(pointedly)</stage> In a few minutes I shall be on my
      road to Ryswick.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>So much the better, I wish you a pleasant journey. <stage>(goes up.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>You are attached to some Embassy, perhaps, Sir.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>The French. The negotiations being broken off, Congress is about to separate.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Indeed! But what is the cause of this?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>The Russian army is completely defeated, and the Czar is on the very brink of ruin.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Slave, 'tis false!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>You are the Czar! <stage>(rapidly, and in an under-tone.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>You, you are mistaken.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Your impetuosity has betrayed you, Sire. Will your Majesty deign to honour me with an
      audience? I ask it in the name of the King, my master.</p>
    </sp><pb n="14"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Who are you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>The Count of Marville, Ambassador from the Court of France. <stage>(opens his bosom, and
      shows a star)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>  Your request is granted. To prevent suspicion, I must accompany my friend to the tavern
      hard by. Meet me there. Come unattended, and simply attired.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>I shall follow your Majesty's example, and dispense with all diplomatic etiquette on the
      occasion.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>You have discovered me. What pledge do you offer that you do not betray me?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>A soldier's honor!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (giving his hand)</stage>Enough!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Well hang me, if ever I knew a fellow like Michloff. He has secrets with everybody. Come. As
      to you, Sir, <stage>(to Count)</stage> a pleasant journey to you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (stepping forward)</stage>A pleasant—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (draws her back)</stage>I have said it already.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Said it already! Whatever <hi>you</hi> may have said already, remember that I haven't yet
      said “yes” before a parson, and if such is to be your behaviour, there's a pretty good chance
      that <hi>you'll</hi> never hear me, Mr. Peter. <stage>(crosses to Marville, L.H.)</stage> A
      pleasant journey to you, Sir. Come along, <stage>(goes back and takes the arm of
      Stanmitz)</stage> you jealous monster,  do.</p></sp>
    <stage>  Exeunt Czar, Bertha, and Stanmitz, R.H.;  Count, L.H.</stage>
    
    <trailer>End of act the first</trailer>
    </div><div type="act">
    
    <head>Scene I —Interior of a Tavern—Stanmitz and others seated at different
      Tables.</head>
     <stage>Enter Czar, Count de Marville, and Varensloff, U.E.L.</stage>
  
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Enough! Be these articles the basis of a treaty between the King of France and myself. And
      now, Varensloff, go secretly, hire a vessel, and let everything be prepared for my departure
      to-night. <stage> Varensloff exits U.E.L.</stage> —To
      prevent suspicion, I will remain the usual time here among my comrades.</p></sp>
     <stage>A Waiter places
      Jug and Horns on Table—they sit, and draw L. table to L. C.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>So, here you are at last, Michloff. What a man you are for politics! I should like to know
      his opinion of the Emperor of Germany. When he can get any one to talk with him on such
      matters, he neglects even his dinner. But here's a man for long stories, if you would but
      listen to him. <stage>(pointing to one at the table)</stage></p>
    </sp><pb n="15"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>What should I learn from him?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Lord! he knows everything. He has just been telling me a long history about the Czar Peter
      of Muscovy.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Indeed! And what of him?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Enough to prove him, in my mind, a blockhead. He's travelling through Europe in disguise,
      learning different trades, and picking up knowledge of all sorts.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>How does that prove him a blockhead?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Not exactly that. But suppose, that while he's away from his own country, some rascal or
      other, and there's no lack of such in Russia, that I can tell you, should take advantage of
      his absence, to supplant him, what a queer figure he'd cut when he got home again, to find
      some other gentleman squatted on his throne, and brandishing about his sceptre.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet</speaker>
     <p>  The Czar himself, perhaps, may not be altogether free from such apprehensions.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Well, that's his business—I never meddle with politics; and though the Emperor of Germany
      seems desirous of my good opinion, yet, but no matter,—I'll give you the health of the Czar
      Peter.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (on R.H.)</stage>With all my heart. <stage>(rises and drinks.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Have you any objection, Michloff?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>I—no man wishes him better. <stage>(at table towards centre of stage, L.H.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>And now, I'll give you the pretty Bertha's good health.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Don't trouble yourself, she's very well without it.<stage>Enter Bertha through from
      L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Thank ye kindly, Sir—yours! <stage>(takes Stanmitz's cup from table and drinks.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p> (R.)What do you want here? <stage>(comes down.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p> (R.C.)Bless me! How gentle and civil some people are. You hardly deserve that I should have
      taken this trouble, but I come to tell you that—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Tell me another time. Go home.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p> (L.C.)Aye, and I'll be your convoy.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Stay where you are.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Go home, and stay where you are! Upon my word! Any one might think we were already married.
      <stage>(to Count)</stage> But we are not, if you please, Sir.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>You are a pretty girl, and it will be your own fault, if you remain long without a
      husband.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Thank ye, Sir, and I don't intend.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (crosses to Bertha)</stage>  She's not only the prettiest but she's also the best
      little girl in all Saardam; and if I live to be rich, as I may be, one day or other, I'll
      provide well for her.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Thank ye, Mr. Michloff.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (crosses to Czar)</stage>Mr. Michloff had better think of providing for himself; and
      as for you Sir—<stage>(crosses to Count.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Hark'ye Peter! <stage>(they come forward)</stage> You are a jealous monster! You know you
      have no cause for jealousy, and I'm determined to tease your little soul out, but I'll cure
      you of it. I came to <pb n="16"/> put you on your guard: my uncle is looking for you. He has been
      mysteriously muttering something about a Colonel, ând as I happen to know what I know about a
      certain—valiant—runaway—I'm afraid—<stage>(during this, Count and Czar go up to table, R., and
      talk to Workmen)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>There is nothing to fear, your uncle is my friend, and the Colonel is my friend, though hang
      me if I can explain to you why.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Can't you?—that's unlucky, for the Burgomaster appears so thoroughly puzzled himself, that
      his explanations are unintelligible to me. But here he comes. He must not see me talking to
      you, so I'll away.<stage> Exit through
      D.L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>I'll give you my arm. <stage>(Count follows her)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (catching hold of him)</stage>Here, my good friend, we'll drink Bertha's good
      health, my fine fellow.</p></sp>
     <stage>Enter Van Dunder and Van Block, through R.H.</stage>
    
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Kidnapping sailors and workmen for the service of Russia.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Upwards of fifty have deserted within these two days.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>A trifle—a mere trifle!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>  You call that a trifle, do you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>No, it is not a trifle, 'tis a very serious affair; but why tell me of it now, when you see
      I'm thinking. Where can the Colonel be with his two thousand ducats, he was to meet me
      here—and—he is not here. <stage>(Workmen go off)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>But what are you looking for? what is it perplexes you?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Everything perplexes me! you perplex me! Don't you see I'm thinking; and when I'm thinking,
      I can think of only one thing at a time, and—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I have done my duty, in making my report to you as Burgomaster, 'tis now for you to
      act as you please.</p></sp>
     <stage> Here the Czar and Count walk  off through R.H.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I'll think about that too, I'll think about it. <stage>(crosses to Stanmitz, who is sitting
      at table, R.)</stage> Ah! Mynheer Stanmitz! good day to you. Have you seen the Colonel?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Mynheer Stanmitz! Mynheer to a journeyman ship-carpenter! ha! ha! ha!—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>A journeyman carpenter! that's it. So you are sure he's a journeyman carpenter?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>What do you mean?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (mysteriously)</stage>That young man!—look at him—that young man—such as you see him
      before you—mark my words, that's all— I happen to know?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>But what do you know?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Aye, that's it! when I say I know—I mean—now don't you go about, saying that I told you,
      he's a Prince in disguise.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>  A Prince!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I said no such thing—presently you'll say I told you he's a State Criminal, who stands a
      good chance of being very speedily hanged—but this I know—he's either one or the other—at
      least he's <pb n="17"/>somebody, though we little think who he is. Now do you mark my words.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>Pugh! the blundering old blockhead.</p></sp>
     <stage>Enter Baron Von Clump through L.H.</stage>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p> (C.R.)Here he is!—your Grace—your Honour—I beg two thousand ducats—two thousand pardons, I
      mean.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Hush! have you sounded him?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Sounded him! I fancy I have indeed!—he's ready to agree to any conditions you may propose;
      and as to the Emperor of Russia —of Germany, I mean—but there he stands—let him speak for
      himself.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Are you certain 'tis he?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Certain! am I certain! ahem!—Stanmitz!—Peter Stanmitz. <stage>(Stanmitz comes
      forward.)</stage> You see he answers to his name. This is the person—the gentleman in
      question—about the—the business in question—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>Well, I never saw him but once, and I vow I shouldn't have known him
      again. <stage>(bowing)</stage> Sir—I—if you please—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>How well he preserves his incognito. I am at your orders. <stage>(crosses to Stanmitz, and
      goes a little up)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>At his orders! what means this?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Means! <stage>(comes down L. of Van Dunder)</stage> Why don't you know what it means, that
      he's preserving his cognito—he's at his   orders—but leave us—leave us
      together.<stage> Exit Van Block through
      L.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Now, speak freely, and never mind me. <stage>(aside)</stage> At last I shall learn the
      meaning of all this. <stage>(to Stanmitz)</stage> You know I have assured you of this
      gentleman's kind intentions towards you. <stage>(they sit, L. H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>If you hadn't, I should have taken to my heels as soon as I knew he was here.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Taken to his heels! 'Tis clear enough what he is.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>I'm aware of your intention to remain unknown, therefore—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, I've tried all I could, but since you have found me out, I have nothing to conceal from
      you; and I trust to your—to your—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>You may trust to me: deign to accept of the friendship I proffer, and, on behalf of my royal
      master, I promise never to desert you.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Royal master!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Desert me! I suppose you mean that I should promise never to desert you? I—I'd rather not
      make any such promise, because— in short—there's no answering for oneself in these cases.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>But when your Majesty is apprised of the condition—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (starting up, and coming forward R.)</stage>His Majesty!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Now don't joke, if you please; this is a serious business, and till I am well through
      it—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Aye, aye; no humbugging.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>I understand—the incognito.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>My dear fellow, do take care of your incognito. <stage>(sits again.)</stage></p>
    </sp><pb n="18"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>  The long and the short of the matter is, that you will get me out of this scrape. I have
      been a long while living at Saardam; I want to get back into my own country, and, while this
      affair is hanging over my head, I'm afraid of my own shadow. I'll do anything for a little
      peace of mind.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Hush! There is the basis of a treaty <stage>(shews paper)</stage>—accede to it, and you may
      rely on the protection of the Emperor of Germany.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>The Emperor of Germany! <stage>(aside)</stage> That's why he wants my opinion of the Emperor
      of Germany. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Oh—aye—you want me to enlist in his service?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Your co-operation with my royal master would certainly be to your mutual interests.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>He wants you to co-operate with the Emperor of Germany.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I don't say the contrary: but the step I have taken ought to be a pretty broad hint to you,
      that I am not over-fond of the service —and, hang me, if I enlist in any.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Aye—you prefer remaining neuter.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Neuter! <stage>(aside to Van Dunder)</stage> There can't be any harm in neuter.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>No, no, stick to the neuter, and you'll do, Peter.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Well, I'll remain neuter, if you please.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>You will find that case here provided for. Read these articles, and then—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (to Van Dunder)</stage>Will <hi>you</hi> read?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>  No. I've no curiosity.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Never mind—not just now. Give me the paper, and I'll consult a friend about it.
      <stage>(takes it.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Accept the conditions, and I answer for your safety, and that of the Russian Empire.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>If you will but answer for mine, take my word for it the Russian Empire can take care of
      itself.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>He seems confident in the national resources.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, national confident!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>And now let me warn you. The ambassadors of the other powers have sent orders to arrest you
      here in Holland.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Here's a fuss about one deserter.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Arrest him! Why then, after all, he is a—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>But I undertake to provide for your personal safety.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Then, ecod! you are a devilish good fellow, and I'll pay the reckoning. <stage>(goes
      up.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (coming forward)</stage>There's an end to the party, and I'm just as wise as
      ever.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Burgomaster, my success in this negociation is almost certain. His Majesty is well-disposed
      to an alliance.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>His Majesty! Why then, after all, he is not a—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>But keep an eye on him. Let no one tamper with him, and he cannot escape us.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Escape! Why then, after all, he is a— Oh—I'll clap him into jail at once.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>  Jail! Are you out of your senses?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Lord—no, no! I only mean—</p>
    </sp><pb n="19"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Treat him with the most profound respect.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Respect! Why to be sure. Most profound. Who can he be? This affair is beginning to grow
      suspicious, and if it be not soon explained, it will drive me crazy.<stage>Enter Czar and
      Count through R.H., Baron endeavours to conceal himself.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (to the Czar)</stage>As I live, it is the Baron Von Clump. Why, Baron, what means
      this disguise? <stage>(crosses to the Baron.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (confused)</stage>I might ask the Count de Marville the same question.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>In confidence then, I'm on a little love affair.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Ha! ha! ha! I wish you success. <stage>(aside)</stage> His intentions are clear, luckily I
      have anticipated him, and the Czar is in our interests.<stage>Enter Varensloff hastily through
      R.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>Sire!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>What news?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>The worst—an insurrection, instigated by your sister, has broken out at Moscow.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>How say you? <stage>(Varensloff gives paper to Czar)</stage> My sister! We must instantly
      away.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>All is prepared.<stage>Enter Bertha, through L. H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (down C.)</stage>Where's my uncle?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>What's the matter—what's the matter? One would think the town was on fire.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>'Tis all in confusion. <stage>(crosses to Stan.)</stage> They talk of plots   and
      conspiracies, and arrests, and I'm so alarmed on your account, Peter, for I heard something
      said about a suspicious character in Saardam. A body of troops has just marched in, and I
      heard the orders given to guard this house on all sides.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>What do you say? Treason and plot! Let me be cool— let me think. What's to be done? Let me
      go home and think.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>It is forbidden for any one to quit this house.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>We'll see that.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Aye, we'll see that! What, lock up the Chief Magistrate of Saardam, let me see who'll
      dare?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>Here comes the officer in command.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>An officer! That's a different thing. Why didn't you say at once he was a commanding
      officer?<stage>Enter Officer and Six Guards, followed by Van Block, &amp;c., through L.
      H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p> (C.)The Burgomaster of Saardam.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p> (L. C.)Here is the Burgomaster of Saardam, and I desire to know how you dare—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>Here are my orders, Sir—read. <stage>(gives papers.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Read! Oh, if he has orders you know—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (L. of him)</stage>But you don't examine whether they are in form.</p>
    </sp><pb n="20"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Aye, to be sure. I like the notion of a man in a yellow jacket, hectoring a Burgomaster,
      when perhaps his orders are not in form.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>Examine them, Sir, the signature—the seal.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, the signature, and the seal. Why, that alters the case.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>Government has discovered that great numbers of sailors   and workmen have been inveigled
      from the different dockyards in Holland, and induced to enter into the Russian service.
      <stage>(Czar and Varensloff listen.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p>I told you what was going on.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Why all the Burgomasters of Holland must be asleep to permit—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>'Tis chiefly at Saardam that these enormities have been committed.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>You don't say so—and I not to know! Now, let me think what is to be done?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>With a view to discover the agents, I am ordered to arrest all foreigners not properly
      authorised to reside in this place.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>That's exactly my idea.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (sits at table)</stage>At such a moment, too. How to escape!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Come this way, I expect I know the agents.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>Indeed!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I have observed five or six suspicious—very suspicious looking fellows about. Now, leave it
      to me. You shall see how a Burgomaster can ferret out a rogue for you. Ahem! <stage>(to
      Marville)</stage> You, Sir, with your brazen face, stand forward and tell me what you are
      doing at Saardam, and who you are?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p> (R.C.)The Count de Marville, Ambassador from the Court of France.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (staggering away)</stage>Ambassador from—Here's a lucky guess to begin with! My
      Lord, I—I didn't mean you, my Lord,—no— there's the fellow! <stage>(to Varensloff)</stage> Who
      are you, scoundrel?—   answer me!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p> (R.)Admiral Count Varensloff, Ambassador from his Majesty the Czar of Muscovy.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Your Excellency—your—Oho! I have him now. It wasn't to you I spoke. Why don't you answer,
      you dog?—you, with your rigmarole about two thousand ducats! Here's the man—he offered to
      bribe me—kidnap sailors! He'd have kidnapped a Burgomaster too, if he could. Who are you, you
      dirty dog! Your name, you rascal—your name!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p> (L.C.)Baron Von Clump, Ambassador from the Emperor of Germany.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I shall go out of my wits!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>Why, Burgomaster, you appear to be rather puzzled.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Puzzled?—don't talk to me of puzzled! 'Twould puzzle a conjuror! They set me angling for
      rogues, and I catch nothing but Ambassadors. Aha! I never liked the looks of this
      fellow—arrest that Stanmitz!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>My poor Peter!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (L., aside)</stage>'Tis all over with me!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M7">
     <speaker>Blo.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (comes down R.)</stage>He's an honest man.</p>
    </sp><pb n="21"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Hallo! do you pretend to teach me my business? Arrest him, I say!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Are you out of your senses? 'Tis the Czar!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>He! In that case—Peter Michloff, then—he's the man!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Hold! What would you do? 'Tis the Czar!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>  Oh! this won't do—this won't do! At first they were all Ambassadors—now they are all
      Czars. <stage>(to Officer)</stage> Hark'ee, Sir! Is this treatment for a Burgomaster? You come
      to me with a rhodomontade about treason, and plot, and a discovery to be made. Tell me exactly
      the person I am to discover—I'd discover him fast enough then, I warrant you!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>If you would but read your instructions—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Read! What's the use of talking to me about reading? Do you think a Burgomaster has nothing
      else to do but read?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>'Tis known the Czar Peter is here in disguise—'tis him you must discover and detain.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (to Czar)</stage>You are saved! <stage>(crosses to Baron)</stage> You have been too
      speedy in your movements for me; but, as a generous rival, I congratulate you on the success
      of your manœuvres. <stage>(to Stanmitz)</stage> Sire! <stage>(recollects Czar—runs to him, as
      he sits at the table, breaks his pipe over his head, and pulls him forward between Dunder and
      Baron, bending his head down—they stand obliquely up the stage, R.H., bowing)</stage> Sire, it
      would have been my pride in procuring your co-operation with my royal master: but
      since—<stage>(Stanmitz is astonished—Van Block overhears)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Would you compromise the safety of his Majesty, my Lord? <stage>(they retire)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>So, then, Stanmitz turns out to be the Czar of Muscovy! Who'd have thought it? I'll give the
      Captain a sample of my penetration and acuteness.—Ahem! Captain—you want the Czar, don't you?
      There's your man!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>But are you sure of it this time?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I'll answer for it with my head.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M8">
     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
     <p>  Enough! We must not let him suspect that he is under any restraint. A guard of honor,
      merely—you understand, Burgomaster. He is now in your custody—your head will pay the forfeit
      of your negligence.<stage> Exit through, with four
      Guards, followed by Van Block.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>There's an honour for a Burgomaster!—the Czar of Muscovy in my keeping—now what's to be
      done?—let me think!—let me think!—go away all of you. You distract my ideas—I must think—go
      away. My head to be the—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (to the Czar)</stage>You are
      saved!—away!<stage> Exit Czar, Count, and Varensloff,
      D.R.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p> (R.)And you. <stage>(to Bertha)</stage>What do you do loitering here? Go home, little girl,
      go home.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (L.C. weeps)</stage>Oh! oh! I'm an unfortunate girl. My poor Peter turns out to be
      the Czar of Muscovy, and there's an end to my marriage. Oh! oh! You'll be the death of me,
      please your Majesty.</p></sp>
     <stage> Exit at door.</stage>
     <pb n="22"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p> (L.)My Majesty! Why Bertha!—my dear Bertha! <stage>(Guards stop him.)</stage> I don't know
      what to make of it, but this looks very much like being treated as a deserter. If you are
      really my friend—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p> (R.C.)Your Majesty need not be alarmed at these appearances of restraint. Affect
      indifference to them. Your enemies cannot deceive me. Their motives for placing this seeming
      guard of honour near your royal person are evident; but, fortunately, the means of your
      immediate escape are in my power. In a few minutes the arrangements will be
      completed.<stage> Exit Baron through D.L.C.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (who has been reflecting)</stage>  Why, to be sure I shall. If the Czar should
      become my nephew, I shall be uncle to the Czar— —that's as clear as the sun—uncle to the
      Czar.<stage> Stanmitz walks about, followed by the
      Soldiers and Van Dunder.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Pray, gentlemen, don't trouble yourselves. I am not used to so much ceremony—I would prefer
      walking about alone.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (bowing)</stage>But, Sire—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p> (R.)Hark'ye, Master Burgomaster, I begin to suspect you are playing me false. This looks
      amazingly like the drum-head and shooting.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p> (L.)Shooting, your Majesty?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>You are in the secret, and I shall be glad if you'll explain to me, why I am treated with
      all this—respect?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I am in the secret—but as to explaining—talking of explaining —suppose now, your Majesty
      were just to explain the matter to me. I'm in the secret—so you know there would be no danger
      in your telling me what the secret is all about.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>But what do you mean by your Majesty?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Mean—what I mean? Pray, your Majesty, don't ask me what I mean; because it sometimes
      happens—but here comes the man for explanations.<stage>Enter Baron Von Clump, door
      L.C.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Sire! may I entreat a word in private?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Why, lord help you—to be sure you may.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (to Van Dunder)</stage>Leave us!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>There, leave us! I'm never to come to the rights of this affair! Is it anything I can assist
      you in! Oh! I'm gone! I   wouldn't stay, contrary to your will. No, not for the two thousand
      ducats you promised me. Oh, I'm gone.<stage> Exit
      through L.C.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>There is not now a moment to be lost. Your Majesty's stay here is fraught with danger.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Well. I know that well enough. Then why don't you get me out of the scrape as you
      promised.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>You know it! You have received intelligence that the troubles existing at Moscow are
      secretly excited by your sister.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>My sister?—the hussey! <stage>(aside)</stage> That girl has always been <pb n="23"/>a plague to the
      family. She ran off with a drummer, and I hoped we should hear no more of her. Now she is at
      home again, and playing her tricks at Moscow.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>The plan too, to detain you here, is well-concerted. An embargo, is laid on all the vessels
      in the harbour—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Then there is an end of my escape.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>There is still hope. My own Yacht is privileged. I have prepared <hi>that</hi> for your
      reception, and here is an order from the authorities for its free passage. <stage>(gives him a
      paper.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Then you are an honest fellow after all!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Is your Majesty provided with funds sufficient for your immediate purposes?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Bless you! I have twelve ducats remaining from my last month's pay.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Twelve ducats! ha, ha, ha! How well he preserves his character! Foreseeing this
      circumstance, I have placed thirty thousand   ducats in your Majesty's cabin. I must leave you
      once again. When all is ready for sailing, I will return and inform you, and mine will be the
      glory of having saved Peter, Czar of
      Muscovy.<stage> Exit through D.L.C.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>“Peter, Czar of Muscovy!” Oh, then, I'm Peter, Czar of Muscovy! Well, it never was clearly
      made out who was my father; so it's just as likely as not. At any rate, since I'd as lief be
      Czar of Muscovy as shot for a deserter, I'll let them have their way.<stage>Enter Czar, Count,
      and Varensloff, through R.H.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>But the courier you have despatched!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Hush! Varensloff knows nothing of it. He bears a mandate to the Governor of Moscow, which
      will awe rebellion. <stage>(to Varensloff)</stage> But by what stratagem can we evade this
      embargo?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>'Twill be difficult; for 'tis general on all vessels, with the exception of the yacht of the
      Baron Von Clump.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Ah, Michloff! you are just in time. I have a hint for you —take care of yourself.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Wherefore?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>It seems that the Burgomaster and the German have settled it between them, that one of us is
      the Czar, and the other a deserter. Now, as they have determined that I shall be the Czar, it
      follows that you are in rather a ticklish situation. To make matters worse, for you, this
      embargo will prevent your escape.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>And when at every moment my anxiety increases—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>'Tis beyond a doubt, he's a deserter, too. Poor lad! I've a
      fellow-feeling for all deserters. Michloff, you have always been a good friend to me: it is
      now my turn to do you a service.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>  You!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>And where's the wonder! Is it anything extraordinary that a sovereign—such as I am, should
      be able to assist a poor devil— such as you are! Besides, I am not the man to desert—that is—a
      friend in distress. I have a Yacht at my command, with permission to sail when I please, so,
      if you choose, I'll take you in my train.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Psha! This jesting is ill-timed.</p>
    </sp><pb n="24"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Jesting, do you call it? Read this paper. <stage>(gives paper)</stage> Though I am the Czar
      Peter of Muscovy, yet as I was not regularly brought up to the potentate line, my education,
      you know, has been rather neglected. Gad! I'll have a secretary!—Why shouldn't I have a
      secretary? I'll make you my secretary.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>We are saved! And did the Baron himself provide you with this?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Baron, or Colonel, or whatever he may be, he's a devilish good fellow, let me tell you. Not
      only has he given me his Yacht, but he has placed 30,000 ducats in my Majesty's cabin.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M4">
     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
     <p>Ha! ha! ha!—Poor Von Clump!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Away!—We have not a moment to loose. Stanmitz, you shall accompany me.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>I have just one word to say, if you please. As I am doing the honours in this case, it would
      be quite s civil if yon would wait till I am ready. I offer you a place, because you are a
      good sort of fellow, whom I should be glad to help out of a scrape, but I have a little matter
      to settle before we go, and—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>  Aye, your little Bertha. Fetch her instantly—and follow me—I'll provide for you both.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>He provide! But, Michloff, let me tell you—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Follow me!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p>Follow me! Well, since you choose to give yourself these airs—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (with dignity)</stage>Silence, and obey!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (staggered)</stage>I—I—Hang me, but that look of his has taken my breath away.
      <stage>(as they are going.)</stage><stage>Enter Van Dunder, Baron, Officer, and Four Guards,
      through L.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p> (R. C.)Treason and plot! I've discovered it all at last.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Psha! Is it extraordinary that the Czar should have despatched a courier?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>This blockhead is surely born to frustrate me!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Don't speak, or you'll confuse me again.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Now look'ee how I'll settle this matter, and confound the traitors. <stage>(to Stanmitz, and
      looking significantly at the Czar)</stage> Has your Majesty dispatched a courier to Moscow
      to-day?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (L.)</stage>I dispatch a courier? Ha, ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>You hear! His Majesty dispatch a courier? Ha, ha, ha! They'll endeavour to persuade me,
      next, that I wrote the despatches. But can none of you guess the traitor who employed the
      man—who gave him three hundred roubles for the expense of his journey?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (aside)</stage>'Tis my courier!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>You're a set of clever fellows! but when a discovery's to be made, it's always left to me.
      There's the traitor!—Peter Michloff—   there!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M3">
     <speaker>Clu.</speaker>
     <p>Impossible!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Impossible, is it? Perhaps I haven't seized the despatches? <stage>(shews them)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(R.)</stage>Villian! and have you dared—?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(R.C.)</stage>Keep him off! Protect your Burgomaster.</p>
    </sp><pb n="25"/>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (takes the paper)</stage>'Tis the Czar's hand, <stage>(reads and starts)</stage> and
      have you presumed to read this paper?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>I never presumed to read anything in my life—but if I am not made a Baron for this
      discovery—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>Stand aside.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Again, stand aside!—am I never to find out what is it I discover?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (takes Czar apart)</stage>Is it possible, Sire, you could command the death of your
      sister?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>One great, one terrible example of vengeance is necessary to stop the progress of a revolt,
      which she has instigated, and which threatens the destruction of my empire. I concealed my
      intention from you, for I well know the weakness of your nature. You are now acquainted with
      my will—do your duty, and let my mandate he obeyed.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>The duty of a loyal subject, of a faithful counsellor, is to spare his master the commission
      of an act which would for ever tarnish his glory. <stage>(he deliberately tears the
      paper)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Ha! <stage>(draws a dagger and rushes at him.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p>I have done my duty. <stage>(throws himself at the Czar's feet, and opens his bosom)</stage>
        Strike!—history will record the blow. <stage>(a general movement.)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (C.)</stage>Secure that fellow! First he's for striking a Burgomaster, next for killing an
      Ambassador.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>What was I about to do?—I—the reformer of an Empire, who cannot restrain the fury of my own
      passions. Varensloff, pardon your pupil—your friend.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M2">
     <speaker>Var.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (kneels, and kisses his hand)</stage>Sire!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_mult">
     <speaker>All.</speaker>
     <p>'Tis the Czar!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>Yes, my friends, <stage>(crosses to C.)</stage> he who has so long shared your pleasures and
      your toils—is Peter, Czar of Muscovy.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M6">
     <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(L.)</stage>Why then, in that case—I suppose <hi>I</hi> am not.<stage>Enter Bertha, running, at
      D.L.C.</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Is this the way you come? Pay your homage where 'tis due. Bow to the Czar, all of you, and
      make no mistake this time, you might have seen who he was with half an eye.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_F10">
     <speaker>Ber.</speaker>
     <p>And is my poor Peter nobody after all? Oh, my dear, dear Peter! then I am happy again.</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>But I will yet make somebody of my old companion. Stanmitz shall be director of my dockyards
      on the banks of the Neva; and within these two years, there shall the world behold the capital
      of Russia!</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p>Sire! when your capital is built, if your Majesty should be in want of a Burgomaster—</p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M1">
     <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
     <p>I shall choose discreetly. But come—away! Farewell, my friends! <stage>(going
      up)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    <sp who="#L0206_M5">
     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
     <p><stage> (intercepting his passage, and bowing)</stage>Sire!—your   Majesty! If your Majesty
      would but condescend to remain till I have made one other discovery—it won't take a minute. I
      want to <pb n="26"/>discover <stage>(to the Audience)</stage> whether the Burgomaster of Saardam may again
      be puzzled upon a future occasion.</p></sp>
    <stage type="tableau">
     Guards. Officer. Guards
     Varensloff. Czar. Dunder. Baron. Bertha. Stanmitz
    </stage>
     <stage>Curtain.</stage>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
 
</TEI>