<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L0945">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title n="woodcockslittlegame" type="main">Woodcock's Little Game</title>
    <author>Morton, John Maddison</author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Html transcription</resp>
     <name>Paul Haxo</name>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Curated by</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <distributor>Privately published on the Lacy Website</distributor>
   <idno type="LAE">L0945</idno></publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc><bibl type="origin" n="63.15"><author>Morton, John Maddison</author><title type="main" n="woodcockslittlegame">Woodcock's Little Game</title><title type="sub">A Comedy-Farce in two
       acts</title><extent>39 pp (UM copy: 476 - 515)<measure type="pp" quantity="40"/>
  <measure type="spCount" quantity="517"/>
  <measure type="spvCount" quantity="0"/>
  <measure type="txWords" quantity="8107"/>
  <measure type="spWords" quantity="8107"/>
  <measure type="stWords" quantity="0"/>
  </extent>

      <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 63, No. 0945</title><idno type="nic">N16044</idno></bibl><bibl type="surrogate"><ref target="https://gutenberg.org/ebooks/57451">Gutenberg
       transcription</ref></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453798&amp;seq=476 ">UM from
       HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol63/L0945/L0945-um.pdf"/></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="TEI"><ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/L0945.html">TEI</ref></bibl><listEvent>
      <event type="firstPerf" when="1864-10-06" source="textNic" where="St.James's">
       <desc>Premiered at Royal St.James's Theatre 6 Oct. 1864</desc>
      </event>
     </listEvent></sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc><textClass><catRef target="#sizeM"/><catRef target="#act2"/><catRef target="nic:C.F."/><keywords><term>Comedy</term></keywords></textClass><particDesc><listPerson>
  <person xml:id="L0945_M1">
   <persName type="role">Mr. Woodcock </persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="184">Wood.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0945_M2">
   <persName type="role">Mr. Christopher Larkings </persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="49">Lark.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0945_M3">
   <persName type="role">Mr. Adolphus Swansdown </persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="41">Swans.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0945_M4">
   <persName type="role">David </persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="22">David.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0945_F5">
   <persName type="role">Mrs. Colonel Carver </persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="106">Mrs. C.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0945_F6">
   <persName type="role">Mrs. Woodcock </persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="17">Mrs. W.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0945_F7">
   <persName type="role">Mrs. Larkings </persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="1">Mrs. Larkings.</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="90">Mrs. L.</persName>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="L0945_F8">
   <persName type="role">[Maid]</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="5">Maid.</persName>
  </person>

  <person xml:id="L0945_Mul">
   <persName type="spkr" n="1">Bridesmaids.</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="1">Friends.</persName>
   <persName type="spkr" n="1">Mrs. C. | Mrs. W.</persName>
  </person>




 </listPerson></particDesc></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change when="2025-11-02">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change><change when="2025-09-07">Metadata updated from new catalogue</change><change when="2024-10-03">Header enriched</change>
   <change when="2023-09-01">Header confected</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text><pb n="1"/>
  <front>
   <titlePage><titlePart type="main">Woodcock’S Little Game:</titlePart><titlePart type="sub">A Comedy-Farce,</titlePart><titlePart type="sub">In Two Acts.</titlePart><byline>By <docAuthor>John Maddison Morton</docAuthor>, (Member of the Dramatic Authors’
     Society), Author Of <title>Lend me Five Shillings, Three Cuckoos</title>, <title>Catch a
     Weazel</title>, <title>Where there’s a Will there’s a Way</title>, <title>John Dobbs</title>,
     <title>A Most Unwarrantable Intrusion</title>, <title>Going to the Derby</title>, <title>Your
     Life’s in Danger</title>, <title>Midnight Watch</title>, <title>Box and Cox</title>,
     <title>Trumpeter’s Wedding</title>, <title>Done on Both Sides</title>, <title>Poor
     Pillicoddy</title>, <title>Old Honesty</title>, <title>Young England</title>, <title>King and
     I</title>, <title>My Wife’s Second Floor</title>, <title>Who do they take me for?
     </title><title>The Thumping Legacy</title>, <title>Milliners’ Holiday,</title><title> Wedding
     Breakfast</title>, <title>Irish Tiger</title>, <title>Attic Story</title>, <title>Who’s the
     Composer?</title> <title> Who’s my Husband?</title><title> Slasher and Crasher</title>,
     <title>Prince for an Hour</title>, <title>Away with Melancholy</title>, <title>Waiting for an
     Omnibus,</title><title> Betsy Baker</title>, <title>Who Stole the Pocket-Book?
     </title><title>Two Bonnycastles</title>, <title>From Village to Court,
     </title><title>Grimshaw</title>, <title>Bagshaw, and Bradshaw</title>, <title>Rights and Wrongs
     of Women</title>, <title>Sent to the Tower</title>, <title>Our Wife</title>, <title>Brother
     Ben</title>, <title>Take Care of Dowb—</title>, <title>Wooing One’s Wife</title>,
     <title>Margery Daw</title>, <title>The Double-Bedded Room</title>, <title>the “Alabama,”
     </title><title>Drawing Rooms, Second Floors, and Attics,</title> &amp;c. &amp;c. </byline><docImprint>Thomas Hailes Lacy 89, Strand, London. </docImprint></titlePage>

   <pb n="2"/>

   <performance>
    <head>Woodcock’S Little Game.</head>

    <p>First performed at the Royal St. James Theatre (Under the management of Mr. Benjamin Webster)
     On Thursday, 6th October, 1864.</p>



    <castList>
     <head>Characters.</head>

     <castItem><role gender="M">Mr. Woodcock </role><actor sex="M">Mr. Charles Mathews.
      </actor></castItem>

     <castItem><role gender="M">Mr. Christopher Larkings </role><actor sex="M">Mr. H.j. Montague.
      </actor></castItem>

     <castItem><role gender="M">Mr. Adolphus Swansdown </role><actor sex="M">Mr. J. Johnstone.
      </actor></castItem>

     <castItem><role gender="M">David </role><actor sex="M">Mr. W. Chamberlaine. </actor></castItem>

     <castItem><role gender="F">Mrs. Colonel Carver </role><actor sex="F">Mrs. Frank Matthews
      </actor></castItem>

     <castItem><role gender="F">Mrs. Woodcock </role><actor sex="F">Miss Fanny Hunt.
      </actor></castItem>

     <castItem><role gender="F">Mrs. Larkings </role><actor sex="F">Miss Wentworth
      </actor></castItem>

    </castList>

   </performance>

   <set>
    <p>Modern Costumes.</p>



    <p>Time in Performance—One Hour.</p>
   </set>
  </front>


  <pb n="3"/>
  <body>
   <div type="act">
    <head>Woodcock’S Little Game.</head>



    <head>Act I.</head>

    <stage type="setting">Scene.—An Apartment in the house of Mrs. Colonel Carver at
     Stow-on-the-Wold, fire-place in C., doors, R. and L. of it; another door R. 2. E.; a sofa, L.;
     at L. a window; table, C., with writing materials; chairs, &amp;c., &amp;c.</stage>

    <stage>David in livery and wearing a large wedding favour, is seated at little table,
     writing.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Let me see what I ha’ written! <stage>(reading letter)</stage> “Dear Cousin Jane, I write
      this from the little town of Stow-on-the-Wold, in Gloucestershire—last week the population
      amounted to 2719, but as soon as master and me arrived, it suddenly shot up to 2721—the church
      bells have been ringing all the morning in honour of my master’s marriage with Miss Caroline
      Anastasia Sophia Elizabeth Carver, which is now being solemnized”—<stage>(noise of shouting
      and hurrahing heard)</stage> hey-day! <stage>(jumps up and looks out of window)</stage> it be
      all over, and here comes the bride and bridegroom! <stage>(shouts repeated—David, in his
      enthusiasm waving his arm out of the window and hurrahing with all his might, then coming
      down)</stage> Poor master! he’s gone and done it now, and no mistake!
      <stage>(listening)</stage> Here comes the wedding party—I must finish my letter to Cousin Jane
      by-and-bye! <stage>(putting letter in his pocket)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Mrs. Woodcock, Mrs. Colonel Carver in bridal attire, and two Bridesmaids enter at door R.
     C.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Don’t agitate yourself, my darling child, it is rather a nervous affair, I know, but it’s
      all over now—nothing could be better, you got through it charmingly.</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="4"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_Mul">
     <speaker>Bridesmaids.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, yes, charmingly!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> A little repose, a mouthful of sponge cake and glass of sherry will soon compose you.
      Ladies, support your precious charge—come.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Exeunt, door R. 2 E.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(without)</stage> This way, my dear friends.</p>

     <stage>Enter Woodcock, door R. C., in his bridegroom’s costume, followed by two or three Male
      Friends, with whom he is shaking hands in succession.</stage>

     <p>I’m obliged to you—very much obliged to you, indeed, for seeing me through the awful—I mean
      the interesting ceremony! You’ll excuse my following you to the dining room; you’ll find my
      respectable bride and her blushing mother there—no—I mean—really, what with the excitement,
      the agitation, the—the——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_Mul">
     <speaker>Friends.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(laughing)</stage> Ha, ha! of course!—all right, old fellow—ha, ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Exeunt, R. 2 E.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(coming slowly down—after a short pause)</stage> It’s all over! there’s not the
      slightest doubt about its being all over! the knot is tied, and I am fairly launched on the
      sea of matrimony! I felt uncommonly nervous at first, and then, to make matters worse, I
      thought I never should have got my white kid gloves off; and yet they were quite loose when I
      put them on. I can’t imagine what made them shrink so, unless it was the state of nervous
      excitement they were in—I mean, I was in! ’Pon my life, after all, a wedding in a country town
      is a very jolly affair! In London, a couple walk into church and out again, and it makes no
      more sensation than if they went into a pastrycook’s and bought a bun a piece! but in the
      country it creates a general excitement—the bride and bridegroom become objects of universal
      sympathy—I mean, curiosity—everybody wishes them joy, at least they say they do! In short, as
      I said before, it’s a very jolly affair! I shouldn’t mind being married two or three times a
      week for a considerable time to come. <stage>(seeing David)</stage> Ah, David!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(sighing, and very seriously)</stage> So, you be really married, sir?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(assuming a very hilarious manner)</stage> Yes, David! quite married! You may look
      at me with the perfect
      <pb n="5"/> conviction that you are contemplating the portrait of a gentleman thoroughly,
      totally, and completely married. <stage>(David turns away to hide his laughter)</stage> You
      needn’t turn your head away, David. I don’t mind your laughing. I’m laughing myself, ha, ha,
      ha. <stage>(forcing a very loud laugh—then after a short pause)</stage> It does seem funny
      though, doesn’t it, David?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l. c.)</stage> Yes, sir! it <emph>is</emph> a rum go and no mistake!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I said nothing about a “rum go,” David,—I limited myself to the expression “funny!”</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Only to think of <emph>your</emph> settling down into a respectable member of society!
      Dear, dear, when I think of your desperate, wild, <emph>au</emph>dacious capers——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Hush, David! not so loud? my respected mother-in-law might hear you; and between you and me
      Mrs. Colonel Carver is rather a formidable sort of person!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Ees, sir! she <emph>has</emph> a stiffish, frumpish look with her!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I said nothing about “stiffish and frumpish,” David,—I limited myself to the expression
      “formidable.” As you say, David, I have been a sad scapegrace—a desperate rascal—but when a
      man has been cutting capers and nothing but capers for twenty years, it’s high time he cut
      them altogether—in plain English, I felt I had had my <emph>whack,</emph> and that’s why I’ve
      just married Miss Caroline Anastasia Sophia Elizabeth Carver!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Well, sir, they do say a reformed rake makes the best husband, and you certainly had a
      regular good “innings” at it.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I said nothing about “innings,” David,—I limited myself to the expression
      <emph>“whack!</emph>” Has anything been sent from the railway station?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Yes—sir, three parcels—here they be, sir! <stage>(three brown paper parcels are on the
      table)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(taking one parcel and opening letter, which is fastened to it)</stage> “Two morning
      gowns in merino—best quality, quilted and lined,—cords and tassels as to order,” that’s all
      right; now the other parcels, David—<stage>(opening the papers attached to them)</stage>
      “Three woollen smoking caps, three cloth ditto, three silk ditto, three velvet ditto”—all
      right. <stage>(opening third paper)</stage> “Twelve pairs of slippers
      <pb n="6"/> to measure, three lined with fur, three with flannel, &amp;c., &amp;c.” Quite
      correct.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Morning gowns, caps, and slippers! Why, I never seed you with one or the other in all my
      life, never!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Exactly; because, hitherto, my existence has been passed in coats that cramped my body,
      hats that pinched my head, and boots that crippled my feet! But that’s all over, David;
      to-morrow I insert my body into a morning gown, my head into a cap, my feet into a pair of
      slippers, and in that easy and unencumbered state I sink into a comfortable arm chair for the
      remainder of my existence. Not a bad notion, eh, David?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> I call it a first-rate dodge, sir!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I said nothing about a “dodge,” David; I limited myself to the expression “notion.” That
      being the case, David, I hereby convey, transfer, and make over to you from the time being my
      entire stock of dress coats, ditto trousers, ditto waistcoats, white neckcloths, black hats,
      and patent leather boots.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, thank’ee, sir, thankee!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. Larkings.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(without)</stage> Don’t trouble yourself! I dare say you’ve plenty to do on such a
      day as this.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Heyday! see who it is, David.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(looking off at r. c.)</stage> It be a lady, sir. Lor! how I should laugh if it was
      one o’ your old London sweethearts come down to forbid the banns—ha, ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Hold your tongue, sir, and shew the lady in!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>As David goes up, enter Mrs. Larkings, at door R. C., in travelling costume.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(running back to Woodcock, and aside to him)</stage> All right, sir—I never seed her
      afore!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Leave the room! <stage>(David runs out—Woodcock advances to Mrs. Larkings)</stage> Madam,
      may I—eh? yes—Mrs. Larkings!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p><emph>Yes</emph>! in <emph>propria persona.</emph> Well, am I too late? I see I am. You’re
      married? I see you are. <stage>(looking at Woodcock and then bursting into a laugh)</stage>
      Ha, ha, ha! I can’t help laughing!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> So it seems. Yes, fair lady, I entered the holy
      <pb n="7"/> state of wedlock exactly seventeen minutes and a half ago. <stage>(looking at
      watch)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p>I should so like to have seen you! what fun it must have been—ha, ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> What does she mean by “fun?” and what <emph>can</emph> she be
      laughing at? <stage>(aloud and assuming a very solemn manner)</stage> Mrs. Larkings, if you
      allude to the solemnization of the nuptial rites, <emph>I</emph> saw no fun in it.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p>No, of course <emph>you</emph> didn’t! ha, ha, ha! but tell me how is—how is
      <emph>Mrs.</emph> Woodcock? Ha, ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Mrs. Larkings is gradually becoming unpleasant.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p>Of course I couldn’t allow the dear girl to be married without wishing her joy, poor
      thing.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> What does she mean by “poor thing?”</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p>So I took the express train, and here I am! I suppose she was dreadfully agitated, poor
      thing?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> That’s <emph>two</emph> poor things! <stage>(aloud)</stage>
      Agitated! not she; she was all animation—all joy—all——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, yes! she naturally would be <emph>at first,</emph> poor thing.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Another “poor thing,” and Mrs. Larkings and I shall have a row.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Well, as I have unluckily arrived too late to witness the ceremony—I’d have given anything
      to have seen you—ha, ha! <stage>(laughing immoderately)</stage> You don’t mind my laughing, do
      you?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Not at all; it’s rather pleasant than otherwise!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> All I can do is to give the bride and bridegroom my blessing, and go back by the next train
      to London!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> And to Larkings! By-the-bye, how is your Christopher? I hope your Christopher is still the
      same fond, indulgent Christopher you’ve always found your Christopher.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(enthusiastically)</stage> He’s a darling! we are happy as the day is long! and no
      wonder—we married for love; our tastes, our opinions are the same, and what is still more
      important, we are nearly the same age—Christopher is twenty-four; I am twenty-two! now between
      you and Caroline the gap is much wider.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> The what?</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="8"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> The gap! <emph>she</emph> is under twenty, while you are—how old shall we say?
      <stage>(smiling)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(very quietly)</stage> Thirty-nine!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, that’s the age you’ve decided on, eh? well, if you wish it, we’ll say thirty-nine!
      <stage>(smiling again)</stage> I’d better tell Christopher in case he might let the cat out of
      the bag! <stage>(smiling)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Pleasant creature! very! <stage>(aloud)</stage> Yes, Mrs.
      Larkings—and <emph>at</emph> thirty-nine I think it time for a man to marry.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Then why didn’t you? <stage>(smiling)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I <emph>am,</emph> married! at least, such is my impression.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, yes! but I don’t mean <emph>this</emph> thirty-nine! your other thirty-nine! your
      <emph>first</emph> thirty-nine! <stage>(smiling)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Her sex protects her. <stage>(aloud)</stage> I repeat that having
      reached the age of thirty-nine, and having moreover, sufficiently enjoyed what is called
      “life”——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> You determined to marry and settle down quietly, and all that sort of thing—exactly! that’s
      intelligible enough, as far as you are concerned; but—your wife?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> My wife? Well? what?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> She <emph>hasn’t</emph> enjoyed what is called “life.”</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Eh? no—of course not; but——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> You intend that she <emph>shall!</emph> of course! indeed, Mrs. Colonel Carver writes me
      word that she has arranged a delightful wedding trip for you.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Has she? <stage>(aside)</stage> That’s kind of Carver! very!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! Brussels, Switzerland, Italy, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.; she hasn’t quite settled
      which.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Hasn’t she? to tell you the truth no more have I. <stage>(aside)</stage> I shall seize the
      earliest opportunity of giving Carver notice to quit.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> With a young and blooming bride for a companion, how delightful it will be! The Alps! Mount
      Vesuvius! the Colosseum at Rome!——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, very delightful; but very fatiguing; besides, I’ve seen it all. I know Switzerland and
      Italy, just as well as I do St. Martin’s Church. I admit I’ve only seen the Colosseum at Rome,
      twice; but as on my <emph>second</emph> visit I found it in exactly the same state as on my
      <pb n="9"/> <emph>first</emph> visit, I’ve no wish to pay it a <emph>third</emph> visit,
      merely to establish the fact that on my third visit, I found it in exactly the same state as
      on my second visit.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> But your <emph>wife</emph> hasn’t seen it.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> What of that? I can describe it to her, can’t I? besides, I married to stop at home, not to
      go abroad! in a word, Mrs. Woodcock, like a sensible woman, entirely approves of the programme
      I have drawn up for our connubial existence. <stage>(taking paper out of his pocket)</stage>
      Here it is—I haven’t consulted her about it, but she entirely approves of it, nevertheless. In
      the morning she’ll attend to her household duties, while I go out fishing—I’m very fond of
      fishing! After dinner she’ll do a little gardening, water the plants, pull up the weeds, kill
      the caterpillars, while I smoke my cigar, and—look on. In the evening she’ll take her work,
      darn the stockings, sew on buttons, and so on, while I take a nap in my arm chair. Then we
      wind up with a lively game at dominoes, or “double dummy,” have a light supper—pork chops, or
      a basin of gruel, and—retire! <stage>(throwing paper on the table)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(smiling)</stage> Very charming, indeed! but pray be cautious! if you plunge poor
      dear Caroline too suddenly into such a vortex of gaiety and dissipation, I’m afraid it will be
      too much for her! <stage>(satirically)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> What Larkings could possibly see in this woman, I can’t imagine!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> One word more! now, Mr. Woodcock! look at me, Mr. Woodcock! When Mrs. Colonel Carver
      consented to your marriage with her daughter, was she acquainted with your previous career,
      Mr. Woodcock? your long catalogue of follies and extravagancies, Mr. Woodcock?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(alarmed and anxiously)</stage> Hush!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Your notorious reputation for gallantry, Mr. Woodcock?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Hush—hush! don’t speak so loud! <stage>(looking round, then in a low tone to Mrs.
      Larkings)</stage> I’ll tell you how it happened! You see, we were two Woodcocks—in fact, a
      brace of Woodcocks, Benjamin and Marmaduke. I’m Marmaduke, from which you may infer with a
      tolerable degree of accuracy that my brother was Benjamin!
      <pb n="10"/> Well, Benjamin was always one of the quiet going sort, in short, a serious young
      man; in fact, he was known as the “tame Woodcock,” because he was what is called decidedly
      “slow;” now I was called the “Wild Woodcock,” because——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> You were decidedly “fast!”</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! Well, when Mrs. Colonel Carver made the usual enquiries as to respectability, moral
      character, and all that sort of thing—she somehow or other stumbled on the wrong Woodcock—the
      tame one instead of the wild one—and——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> And you took advantage of her mistake? Fie, fie, Mr. Woodcock! I couldn’t have believed it
      of you.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> The very words I said. “Woodcock,” said I, “I couldn’t have believed it of you.” But you
      won’t betray me, my dear and highly valued friend? you won’t go and dash the cup of connubial
      bliss from my lips? because I have seen Mrs. Colonel Carver turn very red in the face at the
      merest trifle, and—here she comes. <stage>(with an imploring look at Mrs.
      Larkings)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Carver, R. 2 E.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Mrs. Larkings here? where is she? Ah, my dear, delighted to see you! and yet I’ve half a
      mind to scold you for arriving so late; we’ve been obliged to get married without you, haven’t
      we, Mr. W.? <stage>(crossing to Woodcock)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, Mrs. C.!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Tell me—how is dear Caroline?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Very well, but very agitated—and no wonder <stage>(seeing Woodcock, who is approaching, and
      in a severe tone of astonishment)</stage> Mr. W.!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(bothered)</stage> Yes, Mrs. C. <stage>(Mrs. Carver motions him to keep at a
      distance, Woodcock retreats quite bewildered)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(to Mrs. L.)</stage> Go to her, my dear! you’ll find the dear child in her room,
      exchanging her bridal attire for her travelling dress.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(overhearing, l. c.)</stage> Umph! Travelling dress? did you say “travelling
      dress?”</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="11"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, Mr. W.! but I forgot, you were to know nothing about it! <stage>(to Mrs.
      Larkings)</stage> I think we arranged that Mr. W. should know nothing about it?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r. c.)</stage> Of course not! our object was to give him an agreeable surprise.
      <stage>(smiling)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Our object?—then <stage>(crosses to Mrs. Larkings)</stage> you joined in this charming
      little plot, eh? ha, ha! <stage>(forcing a laugh)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Joined in it? She concocted it!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Did she? ha, ha! <stage>(with a savage grin at Mrs. Larkings)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Yes; why don’t you thank her, Mr. W.?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(sulkily)</stage> I do. <stage>(very savagely, to Mrs. L.)</stage> I’m obliged to
      you. Do you hear?—I’m obliged to you.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(smiling satirically at Woodcock)</stage> I am thanked sufficiently already, in
      having suggested a proposal, which evidently gives you so much satisfaction! And now I’ll join
      dear Caroline!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Do. Mr. W.! <stage>(Woodcock takes no notice—very loud)</stage> Mr. W!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(sulkily)</stage> Well!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Hand Mrs. Larkings to the door.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Eh—very well. <stage>(taking hold of Mrs. Larkings’s hand)</stage> Come along!
      <stage>(pulling her after him to door, r. 2 e., and then pointing to it)</stage> There you
      are! <stage>(looking fiercely at Mrs. L., who bursts out laughing in his face and goes
      out—Woodcock, buttoning up his coat, and with an air of resolution)</stage> I don’t
      care—though it should come to a fight between Carver and me, I will <emph>not</emph> pay a
      third visit to the Colosseum at Rome.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(anxiously watching Mrs. Larkings out, and then throwing off her former stiff and
      disguised manner)</stage> Done at last! <stage>(looking knowingly at Woodcock, and shaking her
      head playfully at him)</stage> Ah!—ah!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r. c., astonished—aside)</stage> What the deuce is the matter with Carver?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l. c., still in the same playful manner)</stage> And has Marmy been deceived—has
      Marmy been taken in?—he! he! he!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> I see, Carver’s been at the sherry!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Come here, Marmy! you don’t mind me calling
      <pb n="12"/> you Marmy? Marmaduke is such a mouthful, whereas, Marmy is——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Mrs. Carver, you’re at liberty to Marmy me as much as you think proper, but allow me to
      observe, that having already paid two visits to the——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, yes! now, listen to me! in a word, I am not the woman you take me for!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Eh? you’re not Mother Woodcock?—I mean, Mrs. Woodcock’s mother?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Pshaw! I don’t mean that! in short, Marmy, you have repeatedly said to yourself—don’t deny
      it—“What a regular wet blanket I shall have for a mother-in-law.”</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> No, no! I solemnly protest that—<stage>(aside)</stage>—I have said so no end of times!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> You are mistaken, Marmy! that austerity of deportment—that rigidity of manner was all
      assumed. Listen! You see this brooch? <stage>(pointing to one in her dress)</stage> It
      contains the portrait of the late Lieutenant-Colonel Carver, done in oil.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Carver done in oil? Yes!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> He was a very handsome man.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Was he? You’re quite right to mention it.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Especially on horseback.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Then I should certainly have had him taken on horseback!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> He vowed that he had never loved before!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Of course! ha, ha! that’s what they all say! ha, ha! <stage>(forgetting
      himself)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(astonished)</stage> Marmy!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I mean to say, I’ve heard say that’s what they all say—that’s all I say!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> I believed him, and we were married! That very day, Marmy, he retired on half-pay!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Did he though? and, how old was Carver done in oil?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Thirty-nine!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> You mean, he said he was thirty-nine. Ha, ha! I’ve known lots of fellows who say they’re
      thirty-nine when in fact they—never mind!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> I was under twenty, had been strictly and
      <pb n="13"/> severely brought up—is it then to be wondered at that I yearned, I may say,
      panted for those gaieties, those amusements so natural to my age? But, alas! it was not to be,
      for while I was revelling in the anticipation of entering into what is called “Life,” he told
      me, and I repeat his own unfeeling selfish words, that he had had his <emph>whack.</emph>
      <stage>(Woodcock looks astonished)</stage> Whack! such a vulgar expression!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Low! very low, indeed! a colonel, especially a colonel on horseback, ought to have been
      above it!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> But that wasn’t all; he actually had the barbarity, on our very wedding day, to draw up
      what he called a programme of our matrimonial existence, <stage>(Woodcock still more
      astonished, suddenly remembers his own programme, which is lying on the table)</stage> in
      which <emph>I</emph> was condemned to the dull monotony of household duties.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> How very odd. I wonder if there was anything in it about killing
      buttons, and sewing on caterpillars.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> While <emph>he,</emph> forsooth, was to enjoy himself; go out fishing, smoke his cigar, and
      take his nap in his arm chair. <stage>(angrily)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> This is a very singular coincidence; because, I’ll take my oath,
      <emph>I</emph> never saw Carver’s programme! <stage>(he has gradually approached the table,
      and, watching his opportunity, suddenly snatches the paper off it and crams it into his
      pocket)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> What’s the matter?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Nothing!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> But <emph>that</emph> wasn’t all; he actually expressed his intention of laying aside his
      splendid regimentals—those regimentals that I loved so much, and wearing nothing but those
      odious abominations called morning gowns for the remainder of his existence. <stage>(here
      Woodcock, watching his opportunity, opens table drawer, and thrusts in the parcel containing
      the morning gowns, then slams the drawer)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> What is the matter?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Nothing.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(going to table, and standing on the side opposite to Woodcock, who is eyeing the
      remaining two parcels with anxiety)</stage> But <emph>that</emph> wasn’t all! <stage>(banging
      her hand on one
      <pb n="14"/> of the parcels to Woodcock’s great alarm)</stage> Hanging up his noble helmet in
      the hall, and giving his military boots to his servant, he inserted his head into one of those
      atrocities called smoking caps, and his feet into a pair of embroidered slippers.
      <stage>(during the above, she has kept on banging the paper parcels)</stage> Yes; embroidered,
      no doubt, by some unhappy creature he had professed to love as he did me. <stage>(walking away
      in an excited manner—Woodcock immediately opens table drawer, and thrusts in one of the
      parcels, there not being room for the other, Woodcock hastily thrusts it up under his
      waistcoat in front)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> What is the matter?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Nothing!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Such, Marmy, was my married life for twenty years. Anxious, therefore, that Caroline should
      escape my wretched fate, I resolved to find her a husband who, like herself, had never enjoyed
      what is called “Life.”</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> And you pitched upon me!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> I did; every enquiry I made about you convinced me you were the very man I was looking for.
      “He is no second Carver,” said I, “he is not satiated with the pleasures, the gaieties, the
      amusements of the world,” said I, “he has never even tasted them,” said I, “and therefore,”
      said I, “he’ll be the more ready to plunge headlong into the dazzling and intoxicating scene
      before him,” said I.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Did you?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! “Caroline will plunge in with him,” said I, “and I—I shall plunge in after both of
      them,” said I.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> You?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Of course! <stage>(with increasing animation)</stage> Haven’t I to make up the twenty years
      I lost with Carver? yes, and what’s more, I mean to make them up! Yes, Marmy! balls, concerts,
      operas, assemblies, masquerades, regattas, races!—wherever you are, there will I be! Wherever
      you go, there will I go. Oh, how I long to begin! how I pant to mingle in “the gay, the gay,
      the festive scenes—the halls, the halls of dazzling light,” and sport the light fantastic toe
      in the merry, joyous dance! <stage>(dancing a few steps)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(after a stare of astonishment)</stage> Dance? a
      <pb n="15"/> woman of her substance! she couldn’t do it! <stage>(aloud)</stage> I’m only
      afraid, my very dear Mrs. Carver, that “light fantastic toe” of yours won’t have much to do in
      our quiet little town of Stow-on-the-Wold!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Stow-on-the-Wold? Faugh! I’m speaking of London!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(with a start)</stage> London?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! Where we shall be this very evening. Yes, Marmy, that’s the little agreeable surprise
      we had in store for you, ha, ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Now, Woodcock, prove yourself a man, Woodcock—assert your dignity,
      Woodcock—and let Carver see you’re not going to stand any of Carver’s nonsense, Woodcock!
      <stage>(aloud and drawing himself up)</stage> Mrs. Lieutenant Colonel Carver—<stage>(thrusting
      his hand in his waistcoat, the paper parcel shews itself below it—Woodcock hastily thrusts it
      up again)</stage> I repeat, Mrs. Lieutenant Colonel Carver——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> I know what you are going to say, Marmy, but don’t be alarmed! we’ve settled everything
      without you—in short, you’ll have nothing whatever to do except to supply the money—there!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(still more dignified)</stage> Mrs. Lieutenant Colonel Carver—<stage>(here the
      parcel again appears below his waistcoat—he thrusts it up so violently that it shews itself
      above it under his chin)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> In the first place that kindest, best of creatures, Mrs. Larkings has already secured
      apartments for us close to their own residence in the Regent’s Park, eight guineas and a half
      a week, the cheapest thing I ever heard of!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Mrs. Lieutenant Colonel Carver——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Especially as it includes everything except plate, linen, firing and attendance; but that’s
      not all, Marmy, she vows she’ll not accept a single invitation unless we are included! When I
      say we, I mean Caroline, Marmy and me! <stage>(playfully and skipping about, r.)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside—after a savage look at her)</stage> There are circumstances under which a man
      ought to be allowed to strangle his mother-in-law!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Ah! here comes Caroline, already equipped for travelling!</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="16"/>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Woodcock, R. 2 E., in travelling costume.</stage>

    <p>Come here, my darling—there! <stage>(pointing to Woodcock, who is looking very sulky)</stage>
     Look at him, isn’t he the very picture of happiness? Doesn’t his very eye twinkle with
     delight?</p>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> Yes. And if I were not so happy myself, I should scold you well, sir, for keeping this
      charming, delightful visit to London a secret from me. <stage>(playfully shaking her finger at
      Woodcock, who tries to get up a smile)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> He knew nothing about it, my dear, he’s quite as agreeably surprised as you are—ain’t you,
      Marmy?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(sulkily)</stage> Yes; of course.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> Why, what a serious tone you say it in!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Do I? <stage>(shouting)</stage> I’m delighted! enchanted! There—is that better?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(c.)</stage> Yes, much better. <stage>(suddenly)</stage> I see how it is—this
      arrangement of mamma’s may have interfered with some plan or your own—perhaps you intended
      taking us to Switzerland?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(quickly)</stage> No, no!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(knowingly, r.)</stage> No, my dear; if Marmy had taken us anywhere it would have
      been to Italy.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(still more quickly, l.)</stage> No, no, no; in short, I wish it to be distinctly
      understood, that having already paid two visits to the——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(interrupting)</stage> Yes, yes; never mind, Marmy, if you are a good boy, you shall
      take us to Italy next year! We’ll climb up Mount Vesuvius together, Marmy—to the very top,
      Marmy! <stage>(with enthusiasm)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside, after a savage look at her)</stage> Only let me once get her there, and I’ll
      plunge her headforemost into the crater.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> In the meantime let us only think of London.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, dear; delightful London! Remember, this is my first visit to the Metropolis! You have
      been there, I suppose? <stage>(to Woodcock)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(forgetting himself)</stage> Ha, ha! I should rather think I have—I mean, I’ve
      passed through it once or twice.</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="17"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Yes; but only on business.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Of course—only on business. <stage>(aside)</stage> What an atrocious humbug I am!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> And therefore it will be quite as much a novelty to <emph>him</emph> as to
      <emph>you.</emph></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes. <stage>(aside)</stage> Novelty! to a man who has had twenty years of it! I’m in for
      it—I’m booked for a second innings. Never mind: there’s <emph>one</emph> point on which
      they’ll find me firm and immovable as Gibraltar itself, and that is, that having already paid
      two visits to the——</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Larkings in travelling dress, door R. 2 E.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r. c.)</stage> Well, good people? but I needn’t ask—I see by your happy faces
      <stage>(Woodcock puts on a grin)</stage> that my plan of the campaign has met with universal
      approbation.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r.)</stage> Yes, we’re all charmed with it! Mr. Woodcock especially! he positively
      can’t find words to express his delight!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l. c.)</stage> Is it to be wondered at, that having hitherto led so calm, so
      tranquil, so sedate a life, <stage>(looking with intention at Woodcock)</stage> he should long
      to taste the forbidden fruit? ha, ha! My only fear is, that when he once begins there’ll be no
      stopping him! ha, ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l.)</stage> Ha, ha, ha! <stage>(making a savage face at Mrs. Larkings,
      aside)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Here, ladies, is a programme I have drawn up of your first three weeks’ “Life in London,”
      <stage>(shewing a paper)</stage> an incessant, unflagging whirl of dissipation, I promise you.
      By-the-bye, I quite forgot to mention that Mr. Larkings has placed his riding horses at your
      disposal.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> How delightful! I long to be in the saddle.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside, and looking at Mrs. Carver)</stage> She’ll never stop in it unless she’s
      tied in, she’s too round, she’ll roll off, to a certainty!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(to Mrs. Larkings)</stage> And can you, will you indeed fulfil all your delightful
      promises?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! not only those I have made to you, but to Mr. Woodcock, <stage>(with intention, and
      then aside to Woodcock)</stage> namely, not to strip the “Wild Woodcock” of his borrowed
      plumes—not to betray him to a certain
      <pb n="18"/> lady who turns “very red in the face at the merest trifle,” provided he promises
      to think less of himself, and more of his wife; in other words, that he consents to exchange
      programmes. <stage>(after some hesitation, Woodcock draws his programme out of his pocket,
      looks imploringly at Mrs. Larkings, who shakes her head—he then gives her his programme, and
      snatching hers out of her hand, thrusts it angrily into his pocket)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter David, door, R. 2 E.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(announcing)</stage> The wedding breakfast be all ready for the company, and the
      company be all ready for the wedding breakfast!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Come along! a mouthful of wedding cake and a bumper of champagne to the health of the bride
      and bridegroom, and then—hey for London! <stage>(David looks very much astonished)</stage>
      Now, Marmy, your arm to Mrs. Larkings.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l. c.)</stage> Yes—one moment! <stage>(taking David aside)</stage> David, my stock
      of dress coats, ditto trowsers, white neckcloths and patent leather boots, that I made you a
      present of——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l.)</stage> Yes, sir, ’cause you said you had done with them.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I thought I had—but I haven’t! I want them again, David, for my “second innings.” David,
      <stage>(making a wry face)</stage> you can have the morning gowns, caps and slippers instead.
      <stage>(stopping David who is about to exclaim)</stage> Hush! the morning gowns and caps
      you’ll find in that drawer, <stage>(pointing to table)</stage> and—<stage>(looking towards the
      Ladies)</stage>—here are the slippers! <stage>(pulling out the parcel from under his waistcoat
      and slipping it into David’s hands)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(impatiently)</stage> Now, Marmy! <stage>(they go off, r. 2 e.)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Coming! <stage>(runs up to join the Ladies—pitches the parcel to David, who stands in a
      state of wonder)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <trailer>End Of The First Act.</trailer>
   </div>
   <div type="act">
    <pb n="19"/>

    <head>Act Ii.</head>

    <stage type="setting">Scene—Handsomely furnished Apartment at Mr. Larkings’. Large folding doors
     at C., shewing Ball-room within illuminated and decorated; handsome clock, with practical
     hands, R. C.; dance music heard from inner room, when door is open; doors, R. and L. Very loud
     double knock heard.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F8">
     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(outside)</stage> This way if you please, ladies.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Carver and Mrs. Woodcock, at L., preceded by Lady’S Maid—the Ladies are both
     in very fashionable evening costume, opera cloaks, &amp;c., &amp;c.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(as she enters, and turning to wing)</stage> Now, Mr. Woodcock, we’re waiting for
      you.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(without)</stage> Here I am, Mrs. Carver.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Woodcock, L., he has a crush hat on, a shawl round his neck, an Inverness cape, and
     carries a large bouquet in each hand—he is also in an elaborate evening dress.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> At last! I thought you were never coming!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(who looks miserable and in a sulky tone)</stage> You wouldn’t have me rush into a
      gentleman’s drawing room as if I’d got a wild bull at my heels?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F8">
     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
     <p> Allow me, madam. <stage>(taking off Mrs. Woodcock’s cloak)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Now, Marmy, make yourself useful! <stage>(motioning him to take off her cloak)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Eh? oh, I know! <stage>(taking hold of Mrs. Carver’s cloak behind and giving it a violent
      tug)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> How clumsy you are to be sure! <stage>(Maid assists in taking off her cloak)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F8">
     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
     <p> Here’s the ticket, madam. <stage>(presenting ticket)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Wait a minute, young woman! <stage>(putting both the bouquets under his arm)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> What are you doing? <stage>(taking the bouquets and arranging them)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(to Maid)</stage> Here’s my hat—here’s my comforter—here’s my Inverness
      cape—<stage>(giving the articles to her)</stage>—and, now, give me a ticket for the lot?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F8">
     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
     <p> Here it is, sir, No. 81. <stage>(giving ticket)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="20"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> 81? it’s 18!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F8">
     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
     <p> No, sir, you’ve got it upside down! <stage>(Maid goes out with things, r.)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I see! One’s obliged to be particular, because at the very last dinner party I was at, I
      got a ticket No. 9 in exchange for a bran-new brown silk umbrella; and when I asked for my
      bran-new brown silk umbrella in exchange for ticket No. 9, they told me that ticket No. 9 was
      ticket No. 6, and handed me one American overshoe and a walking stick.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> Do, mamma, arrange the flowers in my coronet.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> They’re all right, my dear; that’s more than I can say for my dress! only see how Marmy has
      rumpled it! <stage>(smoothing dress)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(c.)</stage> Me? come, I like that! considering I had to ride outside, if I rumpled
      any body, it must have been the coachman!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Now, my dear, I think we may venture into the ball room!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> Without our fans and gloves, mamma?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Marmy has got them.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l.)</stage> Eh? yes. <stage>(feeling in his pockets)</stage> No, I haven’t.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Nonsense, you put them in your pocket, you must have them somewhere about you!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> If I have, they must have slipped down into my boots! Would you like me to take off my
      boots? <stage>(sulkily)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> I dare say you’ve dropped them.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> No, I’m positive I didn’t drop them. <stage>(aside)</stage> I flung ’em away!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> How careless of you! what’s to be done?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Well, it strikes me there’s only one thing to be done—go home again. <stage>(hurrying to
      door, r., and calling out)</stage> Ticket No. 18! No. 81! two opera cloaks, one hat, one
      comforter, one Inverness cape.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Larkings, at C., in fashionable evening dress.—Ladies and Gentlemen are seen
     promenading within—Music.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(seeing the ladies)</stage> Ah! you’ve arrived at last, I quite began to despair of
      you.</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="21"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(still at door r., he has got the two opera cloaks, the hat, and the comforter, and
      is holding up and examining an Inverness cape)</stage> Holloa! this isn’t my Inverness cape!
      I’ll take my oath this is not my Inverness cape!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Why! What is Mr. Woodcock about?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(plaintively)</stage> Getting our things together to go home! He’s either lost or
      mislaid our fans and gloves!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> What of that! I can supply you with no end of fans, and dozens of pairs of gloves!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_Mul">
     <speaker>Mrs. C. | Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p>Oh, thank you—thank you!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>(Woodcock, who overhears this, rolls all the things together in a lump and flings them
     back into the room with disgust)</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> But what makes you so late?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Oh! it was entirely Marmy’s fault.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(sulkily)</stage> Of course—of course it was Marmy’s fault!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> You can’t deny it, Mr. Woodcock. You must know—<stage>(to Mrs. Larkings)</stage>—that I had
      bought this coronet expressly for your ball to-night, but when I wanted it to put it on, it
      had disappeared! <stage>(Mrs. Larkings looks aside at Woodcock—puts on a look of
      innocence)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! We hunted for it everywhere. At last where do think it was found? In Marmy’s writing
      desk! ha, ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(forcing a loud laugh)</stage> Ha, ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Poor fellow! he remembered afterwards putting it there to prevent its being lost.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(very quickly)</stage> Yes!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Indeed! <stage>(looking at Woodcock)</stage> Some people might imagine it was to prevent
      its being found!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <emph>and</emph> Mrs. W. <stage>(c.)</stage> Oh, no—no!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, no—no! <stage>(aside)</stage> As I have observed two or three times already, what
      Larkings could ever have seen in that woman——</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter David, at L., as a page.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Please, sir, coachman says you didn’t tell him what time he’s to come with the
      carriage.</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="22"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r.)</stage> Now, remember, Mr. Woodcock, you promised me faithfully that we
      shouldn’t be late—say half past two.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Very well! <stage>(to David)</stage> A quarter past two,</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> I said, half-past! <stage>(smiling)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(shouting, l.)</stage> Half-past!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Exit David, L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! We really must have a good night’s rest, or we shall not be fit for the fancy dress
      ball to-morrow. <stage>(to Mrs. Larkings)</stage> We’ve settled our costume, my dear! Caroline
      is going as Little Red Riding Hood, Marmy as a Neapolitan brigand—<stage>(Woodcock makes a wry
      face)</stage>—and I—<emph>à la Pompadour</emph>!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> I don’t exactly know what a <emph>pumpadoor</emph> is, but I hope
      it’s something decent! <stage>(dance music again heard)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Come, ladies! by-the-bye, I mustn’t forget your fans and gloves—this way! you’ll find us in
      the ball room in less than five minutes, Mr. Woodcock, this way.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Exeunt Mrs. Larkings, Mrs. Carver, and Mrs. Woodcock at door, C. to L.—door
     closed.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> That attempt of mine upon Mrs. Woodcock’s coronet was a contemptible failure.
      <stage>(yawning)</stage> I wonder if I shall ever have a good night’s rest again! Never mind,
      I’ll make up for it when I get back to Stow-on-the-Wold—if ever I do get back; I won’t get up
      for a month! I believe Mrs. Woodcock would go back if it wasn’t for Carver. I wish somebody
      would marry Carver! I’ll give any man a thousand pounds if he’ll marry—and after all, Carver’s
      not absolutely repulsive—and I’m sure there’s plenty of her for the money.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Swansdown in evening dress at C. from L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(going to door r., and taking ticket out of his pocket)</stage> Ticket No. 37.
      <stage>(Maid appears, takes ticket, and disappears)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Why, that’s Swansdown! he’s actually giving up his ticket!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(seeing Woodcock)</stage> Ah, Woodcock! how d’ye do? <stage>(receiving a hat and
      cloak from Maid, and coming forward putting them on)</stage> That’ll do! Good night, Woodcock!
      <stage>(crosses to l.)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="23"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Stop a bit! you don’t mean to say you’re going home, Swansdown?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Of course I am! I ought to have been in bed two hours ago. <stage>(yawning)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> So ought I! <stage>(yawning)</stage> I say, Swansdown, how do you manage it?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Manage what?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> To go home without Mrs. Swansdown?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> I leave her behind!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Exactly—but—how do you manage to leave her behind?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> I go home without her!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I see!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Good night! <stage>(going)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(stopping him again)</stage> Don’t be in a hurry!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> I am so sleepy! <stage>(yawning)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> So am I. <stage>(yawning)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> The fact is, Woodcock, <stage>(yawning, Woodcock does the same)</stage> before I got
      married, I had seen a good deal of this sort of fun. <stage>(yawning very loud)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> So had I! <stage>(yawning very loud)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> In short, I married, not to go out, but to stop at home! <stage>(yawning)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(yawning)</stage> So did I! but how do you manage it?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Manage what?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Why, to stop at home?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> I don’t go out!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Exactly—but how do you manage to “don’t go out?”</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> I stop at home.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I see!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> I hit on a very simple plan! I had a regular stock of sudden indispositions to meet every
      invitation that came in; headaches, rheumatisms, lumbagoes, &amp;c., &amp;c., Mrs. Swansdown
      grumbled a good deal at first, but she soon got used to it, and——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(suddenly grasping Swansdown’s hand, and shaking it violently)</stage> Thank you,
      Swansdown! I’m obliged to you, Swansdown! good night, Swansdown. <stage>(stopping him
      again)</stage> One moment—when you married Mrs. Swansdown, had she got a Carver?</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="24"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> A what?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> A Carver—I mean, a mother?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> No!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Never mind! Good night, Swansdown! Go home to bed, Swansdown!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Exit Swansdown, L.</stage>

    <p>I’ll try it! I will, by Jove! there’s that horrible fancy dress ball to-morrow night! what
     “sudden indisposition” shall I have—I’ve had the measles——</p>

    <stage>Enter Larkings at C. in very fashionable evening costume.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r. c., seeing Woodcock)</stage> Ah, Woodcock! All alone, eh? I’m afraid you’re not
      enjoying yourself?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l. c.)</stage> Yes, I am—in a quiet way!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Delightful party, eh? By-the-bye—I congratulate you—your wife is really a very nice sort of
      person—very nice, indeed! <stage>(in a patronizing tone)</stage> but her dancing has been
      sadly neglected. However, make yourself easy, I’ve engaged her for the next three polkas on
      purpose to teach her the proper step!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Have you?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> After that I’m engaged to Mrs. Swansdown for the rest of the evening. Swansdown’s gone home
      as usual! ha, ha! poor Swansdown! “when the cat’s away,” you know, eh? ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(drawing himself up)</stage> Mr. Christopher Larkings!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Come, come, Woodcock—that grave face won’t do with me, besides, it isn’t because I flirt
      with my friend’s wives that I love them! I flirt with yours, but I don’t love her, at least,
      not yet! ha, ha! but I say, old fellow, don’t follow Swansdown’s example—what can a man on the
      wrong side of forty expect if he will go home to bed and leave a pretty young wife behind him,
      eh? ha, ha! <stage>(poking Woodcock in the side)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Sir! my friend, Swansdown, has too much confidence——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(laughing)</stage> Of course he has, that’s the delicious part of it, ha, ha! I say,
      Woodcock. <stage>(taking his arm, and aside to him)</stage> I don’t mind telling you—and after
      all, I meant no harm—but when Mrs. Larkings went down to your wedding at—what d’ye call the
      place—Toad in the Hole——</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="25"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Stow-on-the-Wold, sir! <stage>(with dignity)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> No matter! well, I suddenly remarked what a fascinating person she was——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Mrs. Larkings?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> No, Mrs. Swansdown! I used to say all sorts of stupid things to her——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> That I’ll be bound to say you did; well, there’s no great harm in that!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> No, but that’s not all—not that I meant any harm—well, after a luncheon of grilled chicken
      and champagne, this afternoon—I don’t know how the deuce it happened, but I’ve a sort of
      stupid, misty recollection of writing a stupid sort of letter, full of doves and loves, and
      Cupid’s darts and bleeding hearts—you know what I mean—which letter, I’m under a very strong
      impression, Mrs. Swansdown will find on her dressing table when she gets home to-night.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Mr. Larkings!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, yes, it was a stupid thing to do, I know, and I heartily wish I had the confounded
      letter back, but it’s too late now, and after all, I meant no harm. <stage>(polka music
      heard)</stage> There’s the polka! I mustn’t keep Mrs. Woodcock waiting. Good bye!
      <stage>(going)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Stop!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Larkings runs out at C. to L.</stage>

    <p>Catch me leaving Mrs. Woodcock alone for a single moment! No, no, I’ll stick to her like her
     shadow. I’ll revel in Redowas! I’ll plunge into polkas! I’ll have a shy at the sausages—I mean
     Schottisches! <stage>(here the polka music becomes louder)</stage> I don’t half like my wife’s
     skipping about with that fellow now; if I could only manage to get her away. <stage>(looking at
     clock, which is in a conspicuous part of the stage)</stage> Only a quarter past one.
     <stage>(after a short pause)</stage> That clock’s too slow. <stage>(lounging up stage, assuming
     an unconcerned manner and humming a tune—when near the clock, looks right and left, then jumps
     up into a chair, puts the clock on one hour, and jumps off chair again—then taking out his
     watch)</stage> Hey-day! my watch is an hour too slow by that clock, and I know there isn’t a
     better clock in England. <stage>(putting his watch on an hour, then hastily thrusting it into
     his pocket, aside)</stage> Just in time!</p>

    <pb n="26"/>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Woodcock, at C. from L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> Still here, my dear? Why don’t you come into the ball-room?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I will presently—there’s plenty of time! It’s quite early yet! <stage>(seeing that he is
      standing between Mrs. Woodcock and the clock, moves aside)</stage> I repeat, it’s <emph>quite
      early yet!</emph> <stage>(pointedly, and looking at clock)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(seeing clock)</stage> Eh? Can it be possible? Twenty minutes past two?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Oh! that clock’s too fast! Look here! <stage>(taking out his watch)</stage> Holloa! Why
      it’s half-past two! That clock’s too slow.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> How the time slips away!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! the last hour’s gone remarkably fast.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Music—some five or six couples, including Mrs. Larkings and Mrs. Carver, come in at C.,
     dancing the polka—the last couple consisting of Mrs. Carver and a very Young Man—polka
     ceases.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(who has gone to door, l.)</stage> Ticket No. 81—two opera cloaks—a hat—a
      comforter—an Inverness cape!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Why! What is Marmy about? <stage>(to Mrs. Woodcock)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> Look at the clock, mamma!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Half-past two!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Larkings, at C. from L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> What’s that? Half-past two? No such thing, gentlemen—I appeal to you! Out with your
      watches! <stage>(Larkings and Gentlemen take out their watches—each presenting his to his
      Lady)</stage></p>
    </sp>
    
    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> Another hour! Delightful!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Charming! <stage>(polka music resumed)</stage> Mrs. Woodcock, allow me. <stage>(polka—Mrs.
      Carver seizing her former partner and whirling him out after the others, at c. to
      l.)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(who has been standing looking on with the opera cloaks, &amp;c., &amp;c., in his
      arms—dashes them down in a
      <pb n="27"/> lump on the stage)</stage> That’s a failure! Then I won’t go home at all! I’ll
      sleep here! <stage>(seizing up the cloaks, &amp;c., and dashing them one after the other on
      the sofa, l. c., and then throwing himself upon them)</stage> There! <stage>(burying his head
      in the pillow)</stage> This is very comfortable——</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Swansdown hurries in, at L., very pale and excited.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(as he enters)</stage> Woodcock! Woodcock! <stage>(seeing him on sofa)</stage> Ah,
      there he is! <stage>(shaking him)</stage> Woodcock, get up!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(jumping up)</stage> Halloa, Swansdown, come back again!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(with a savage grin, r.)</stage> Yes! ha, ha, ha! <stage>(with a forced
      laugh)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l.)</stage> Don’t make such dreadful faces! What’s the matter?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Matter? <stage>(furiously and grimacing)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Don’t grind your teeth in that horrible way. Recollect they’re not your own!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Listen! <stage>(grasping Woodcock’s arm)</stage> On my return home, I found Mrs.
      Swansdown’s maid in Mrs. Swansdown’s room fast asleep! Something was lying on the dressing
      table! It was a letter!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Larkings’s billet!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! A letter for Mrs. Swansdown, from—from—fiends and furies!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I don’t know either of the gentlemen.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> From Larkings! Christopher Larkings! There was no signature; but I knew the handwriting! It
      was a declaration—a declaration! Don’t you hear? <stage>(shouting)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes—yes! Well!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> I rushed into my library—opened my desk—took out my duelling pistols—put them in my pocket,
      and—here I am! <stage>(savagely and walking to and fro)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(following him)</stage> Pistols? Oh, I say, Swansdown—Swansdown! Oh, I say!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(stopping suddenly)</stage> Larkings dies!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes; but don’t—don’t go and cut him off in the flower of his polka—I mean, his youth!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Ah! here comes Mrs. Larkings! She shall know all!</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="28"/>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Larkings, at C. from L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> No—no! <stage>(holding Swansdown back, who tries to join Mrs. Larkings)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r.)</stage> Still here, Mr. Swansdown, then I shall claim you for my partner in the
      polka!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside to Swansdown)</stage> A thousand pardons, madam——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Refuse a lady? Fie—nay, I insist upon it!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>(polka music without—Swansdown begins very unwillingly to dance with Mrs.
     Larkings—Woodcock anxiously following them and dancing a polka steps after them)</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(while dancing)</stage> Besides, Mr. Larkings is dancing with Mrs. Swansdown!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Ah! <stage>(polking savagely)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, fourth time to-night!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(still dancing after them, and aside to Mrs. Larkings)</stage> Don’t tell him that,
      mum—don’t tell him that!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Luckily, I’m not jealous! Christopher is constancy itself!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(savagely)</stage> Is he? Ha, ha!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(still dancing after them, and aside to Swansdown)</stage> Hush, Swansdown,
      hush!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, any woman has my full permission to wean Christopher’s affections from me, if she
      can!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(still polking by their side, and aside to Mrs. Larkings)</stage> Don’t aggravate
      him, mum—don’t aggravate him!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Indeed! What if I place in your hands the proof of your husband’s infidelity?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(same play)</stage> Hush, Swansdown!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Ha, ha! I defy you!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(same play)</stage> Don’t defy him, mum, don’t defy him.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Indeed! then that proof shall be in your hands in half an hour.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(same play)</stage> Hush, Swansdown!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> A letter! a declaration! addressed to my wife by—your husband!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(suddenly stopping)</stage> Christopher unfaithful!
      <pb n="29"/> Support me! <stage>(falling into Woodcock’s arms, who quite bewildered goes on
      dancing the polka)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Carver, C. from L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(seeing Mrs. Larkings in Woodcock’s arm)</stage> Ah! Support me! <stage>(falling
      into Woodcock’s other arm, who, still more bewildered, unconsciously keeps up a polka
      step)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Larkings, C. from L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Ah! <stage>(about to run to Mrs. Larkings)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(stopping him)</stage> One moment! <stage>(drags him forward—then, savagely aside to
      him)</stage> We must fight, sir. I know all! all!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> The devil! <stage>(aloud)</stage> Well, sir, to-morrow morning!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> No! Now! Now! it’s a moonlight night! Primrose Hill close at hand, and I’ve pistols in my
      pocket! Woodcock! <stage>(to Woodcock, who has placed Mrs. Larkings and Mrs. Carver each in a
      chair and is fanning them alternately, still dancing a polka step—Swansdown goes up, seizes
      Woodcock by the arm, and drags him down—aside to him)</stage> You’ll be my second? I’m going
      to shoot Larkings!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(grasping Woodcock’s other arm)</stage> You’ll be my second? I’m going to shoot
      Swansdown!</p>
    </sp>
    
    <stage>They drag Woodcock out between them at L., Woodcock struggling, &amp;c.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(who recovers and runs to Mrs. Larkings)</stage> My dear Mrs. Larkings, look up,
      there’s a dear creature.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, oh, oh! <stage>(sobbing)</stage> I’m the most miserable woman in the world!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(soothingly)</stage> So you shall be, there! but what has happened?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(c.)</stage> My husband—Christopher has written a love letter to Mrs. Swansdown! Oh,
      the base, fickle, perfidious monster!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r. c.)</stage> My dear friend, never indulge in a plurality of epithets; select
      one, a good one, and stick to it! I
      <pb n="30"/> never called Carver anything but a brute! But are you sure?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Quite certain! Mr. Swansdown has promised to send me the letter in half an hour; if it
      contains the proof of Christopher’s inconstancy, oh, what shall I do?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Nothing, ’till Mr. Swansdown has sent you the letter——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Very well! I’ll wait ’till the half hour has expired—patiently, very patiently,
      <stage>(tearing her handkerchief)</stage> if the letter doesn’t come, I’ll go to Mr. Swansdown
      for it—yes—late as it is, I will! and you’ll go with me, won’t you?
      <stage>(imploringly)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, we’ll go together; in the meantime, come with me into the ball room—everybody has
      doubtless left by this time, and you’ll find a glass or two of sherry and a few sponge cakes a
      great support in your affliction. Come!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Exeunt at C. to L.—Mrs. Carver supporting Mrs. Larkings, at the same moment the door, L.,
     slowly opens, and Woodcock peeps in, then speaks off.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> The coast is clear; you can come in.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Larkings with his right arm in a sling—Swansdown following, evidently very much out
     of temper—takes a chair, bangs it down on stage, and falls into it, L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r., pressing his right arm)</stage> How confoundedly painful my arm is.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(c., soothingly)</stage> Yes! I daresay it smarts a little!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(dashing his hat down on stage)</stage> I’m disgusted! yes, disgusted that this
      stupid ridiculous duel should have occurred! <stage>(to Larkings)</stage> Why the deuce didn’t
      you tell me you were sorry for what you’d done—that you meant no harm? my feelings wouldn’t
      have been wounded!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(pressing his wounded arm)</stage> Nor mine either! but that’s not the worst of
      it—if Mrs. Larkings discovers what has taken place, do you know what she’ll do? She’ll leave
      London and bury me alive in the country for the rest of my existence.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Good gracious! I wonder if Mrs. Woodcock would serve <emph>me</emph>
      the same if <emph>I</emph> were to—by jingo! it’s worth thinking about. <stage>(aloud)</stage>
      But how <emph>is</emph>
      <pb n="31"/> Mrs. Larkings to know anything about it? <emph>I</emph> shan’t betray
      you—Swansdown won’t—you won’t betray yourself?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> No; but my wounded arm will! besides there’s that unlucky letter of mine, which Swansdown
      has promised to send to my wife.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(producing letter)</stage> Here it is. If I <emph>don’t</emph> send it, what can I
      say?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(taking the letter)</stage> Say? why—that you made a mistake in the handwriting—that
      it wasn’t Larkings’s after all!—but somebody
      else’s!—anybody’s—<stage>(suddenly)</stage><emph>—Mine!</emph></p>
    </sp>
    
    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes! What’s the consequence? When it’s known that you and I have been fighting, no one will
      imagine it’s on account of Mrs. Swansdown, consequently her reputation will be saved!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> True! but zounds then! what have we been fighting about?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Eh? oh, for the fun of the thing! or else some difference of
      opinion—<stage>(suddenly)</stage>—the war in America! that’s the very thing! you’re for the
      Federates! I’m for the Confederals!—that’ll do famously—it’ll save <emph>you</emph> <stage>(to
      Swansdown)</stage> from being laughed at; <emph>you</emph> <stage>(to Larkings)</stage> from
      being buried alive in the country.</p>
    </sp>
    
    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Never mind me. Woodcock’s got a little game of his own. <stage>(aside)</stage> It’s a
      capital idea—a sublime idea! <stage>(to Swansdown)</stage> Now go home; and spread the report
      of our duel right and left; mention it at your butcher’s, baker’s, and candlestick maker’s—in
      short everywhere; and don’t forget you’re a Confederal—I mean—never mind; go along.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Swansdown hurries out at L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> But I say, what the deuce is to become of me in the matter?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Eh? I have it; you’ve been my second.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Very well? then I can go to Mrs. Larkings.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes. Stop! take that sling off.</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="32"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Well, but——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Take it off, I say!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(taking off sling and fitting his arm in his waistcoat, with evident pain)</stage>
      There! and now give me that confounded letter of mine.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Oh dear, no! I can’t spare that. <stage>(taking letter out of envelope and reading)</stage>
      “To see you is to love you.” <stage>(aside)</stage> And to think I’ve got to copy such twaddle
      as that. <stage>(listening)</stage> Hark! I hear some one. You know what you’ve got to do;
      don’t go and make a mess of it. <stage>(aside)</stage> And I got married to settle down
      quietly—it looks like it! Never mind; Woodcock’s got his little game!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Hurries out at L.</stage>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Larkings and Mrs. Carver, C.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(assuming an air of unconcern)</stage> Ah, my dear!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r.—extending her arm)</stage> Keep your distance, sir. I know all—all! In a word, I
      am now going to Mr. Swansdown’s—you hear—to Mr. Swansdown’s, for a certain letter—a love
      letter, sir, written by you to Mrs. Swansdown.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(c.)</stage> By me! Ha, ha, ha! I should like to see it. Go and fetch it, my dear;
      why don’t you go for it, my love? Tra, la, la! <stage>(humming a tune)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter David, L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(to Mrs. Larkings)</stage> Please, ma’am. <stage>(aside)</stage> Don’t let me forget
      what master told me to say. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Here be a letter, ma’am, from Mr.
      Swan—Swan——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(eagerly)</stage> Swansdown? give it me? <stage>(snatching letter from David, but
      keeping her eyes fixed on Larkings, who tries to appear unconcerned, and endeavours to get up
      a whistle)</stage> You may go, David!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Exit David, L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Woodcock’s gone and bungled the business—I knew he would.
      <stage>(Mrs. Larkings tears open the envelope)</stage> She’s opened it; it’s all over with
      me!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(reading)</stage> “To see you is to love you.” <stage>(suddenly)</stage> Eh! can it
      be? yes! yes! <stage>(with an exclamation of joy, and throwing her arms round
      Larkings)</stage> Oh, my dear, darling Christopher!</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="33"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(suffering pain in his arm, and trying to disengage himself—aside)</stage> Confound
      it! how she’s hurting me!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> What do you mean?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> That I’m the happiest woman in the world—that Christopher is innocent! <stage>(throws her
      arms again round him)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Don’t! don’t!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Innocent?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, as a lamb! the letter isn’t in his handwriting—look! <stage>(giving letter to Mrs. C.,
      and making another spring at Larkings, who keeps her off)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(reading letter)</stage> “To see you is to——” <stage>(suddenly, and with a violent
      scream)</stage> Ah!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <emph>and</emph> Lark. <stage>(startled)</stage> What’s the matter?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(after a pause gives another louder scream)</stage> Ah! the wretch! the monster!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Who? who?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Woodcock! the handwriting is <emph>his!</emph> <stage>(Larkings laughs aside)</stage> Ah!
      <stage>(another loud scream)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Hush! you’ll alarm the neighbourhood.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l. c.)</stage> I don’t care—I must scream! I shall die if I don’t scream! take me
      somewhere where I can scream!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Hush! for Caroline’s sake.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> True! she must know nothing—and yet I must scream. I’ll go out in the street and
      scream.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Hush! had you not better take poor Caroline home on some pretext or other!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> I will! and then I’ll come back and kill Woodcock. I’ll send for a cab this moment!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Pray be cautious.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> I will! but I shall suffocate if I don’t scream—I have it—I’ll scream in the cab!
      <stage>(hurries out, c.)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(with an imploring look at Larkings)</stage> Oh, can you forgive me?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(in a patronizing tone)</stage> Yes, yes!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Dearest, best of Christophers— <stage>(suddenly embracing him again)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Don’t! don’t!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> How could I suspect you? but isn’t this dreadful conduct of Mr. Woodcock’s! actually before
      the honeymoon is over!</p>
    </sp>

    <pb n="34"/>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Very shocking, indeed.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> The man ought to be put in the pillory!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> At the very least.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Ah! <stage>(tenderly)</stage> you wouldn’t deceive your fond confiding wife?
      <stage>(affectionately putting her arm in his wounded one)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(making a grimace)</stage> Not for the world!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter David, L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(in a flurried manner)</stage> Oh please, ma’am, a policeman has just rang at our
      bell——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> A policeman?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, ma’am; seeing we hadn’t gone to bed, he called to say that as he was going over
      Primrose Hill, about a quarter of an hour ago <stage>(Larkings pricks up his ears)</stage> he
      picked up this card case, ma’am! <stage>(Larkings hastily fumbles in all his
      pockets)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Mine, by Jupiter!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> So he opens it, ma’am, and—<stage>(to Larkings who is making violent signs to him to hold
      his tongue)</stage> What’s the matter, sir? <stage>(Mrs. Larkings turns towards Larkings, who
      again tries to get up a whistle)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> But why bring it to our home?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Because it’s Mr. Larkings’s card case, ma’am!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(to Larkings, suspiciously)</stage> So you’ve been to Primrose Hill, it seems?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(bothered)</stage> Yes—the fact is—the rooms were so hot—and—never having seen the
      sun set—I mean the moon rise—I—<stage>(aside)</stage> I’d better hold my tongue.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(after a searching look at him)</stage> Where did the man say he picked this card
      case up?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Where the shooting took place, ma’am.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> The shooting?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M4">
     <speaker>David.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, ma’am. <stage>(seeing Larkings again making signals to him)</stage> Yes, sir!
      <stage>(Mrs. Larkings looks round and Larkings again assumes an air of unconcern)</stage> He
      heard two shots, ma’am—bang, bang; and ran to the spot just in time to see three gentlemen
      walking off; and——</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>(during this Larkings has been again repeating his signals to him)</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> You can go, David.</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Exit David, at L.</stage>

    <pb n="35"/>

    <p>Larkings! <stage>(eagerly to him)</stage> what does this mean? Speak, Christopher—what has
     happened? <stage>(grasping Larkings’s arm, who makes a grimace)</stage> Ah! you needn’t
     explain; I see it all—there has been a duel?</p>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l.)</stage> Well——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(c.)</stage> Don’t speak; between Mr. Swansdown and you.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> No, no.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Who then? He believed that <emph>you</emph> wrote the letter to his wife?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, yes.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> And challenged you?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, yes.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> And you fought?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Yes—no, no.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, yes—no, no. Explain! No! I see it all.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> She’s always seeing it all! <stage>(crosses to r.)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> When you got on the ground, Mr. Woodcock, who was probably your second——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> My second! yes—exactly.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Confessed that he was the real culprit——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(quickly)</stage> That’s it.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> And received Mr. Swansdown’s fire——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> In the arm.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Wounded! Mr. Woodcock wounded!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Yes. <stage>(recollecting)</stage> No; that is—— <stage>(aside)</stage> Zounds! nothing was
      said about <emph>that.</emph></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Poor Mr. Woodcock! Which arm was it?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Eh—why—the arm that held the sword!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> The sword!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> Yes—no, I mean the pistol! <stage>(aside)</stage> Now to find Woodcock, and put him on his
      guard. <stage>(turns and sees Woodcock, who enters at l., with his left arm in a
      sling—aside)</stage> Huzzah! he’s got his arm in a sling!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(looking at Woodcock, who comes slowly forward, as if very much ashamed of
      himself)</stage> It is true, then. Unhappy man, I pity you!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(assuming a very penitential voice and manner)</stage> I don’t deserve it.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Confound it! he’s got the <emph>wrong</emph> arm in
      <pb n="36"/> the sling! Ahem! <stage>(making violent signs to Woodcock to change
      arms)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(looking at Woodcock)</stage> Why, how’s this? <stage>(to Larkings)</stage> You told
      me Mr. Woodcock’s wound was in the right arm!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(confused, r.)</stage> Did I?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> Yes—you distinctly said “the arm that held the pistol.”</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(very quietly, c.)</stage> That’s quite right! I’m a left-handed Woodcock.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l.)</stage> It’s very shocking! but there’s something worse behind.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(looking behind him)</stage> Where?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> I mean that Mrs. Colonel Carver knows everything. She’ll return immediately; when she’s
      done screaming, your only hope is to plead guilty at once and sue for pardon for Caroline’s
      sake—you know that’s her tender point!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I will! I’ll throw myself at once upon her tender point.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(without)</stage> Don’t tell me! I can’t—I won’t believe it!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Carver, hurriedly, R., and sees Woodcock with his arm in the sling.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(assuming a very pathetic attitude)</stage> Ah! it’s true! <stage>(screams and falls
      into chair, Mrs. Larkings runs to her—Woodcock and Larkings exchange winks and
      laugh)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(to Mrs. C.)</stage> Hush! the arm is only slightly, very slightly wounded.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> I know better! they’ll have to amputate it! I shall have a one-armed son-in-law—a wretched,
      helpless cripple! <stage>(suddenly to Mrs. Larkings)</stage> My dear friend, go to poor dear
      Caroline—don’t leave her till I’ve had time to do all my screaming! I know I screamed in the
      cab, but not half enough! Go, go!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Exit Mrs. Larkings, C., followed by Larkings, who again exchanges winks, &amp;c., with
     Woodcock.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(watching them out and then turning to Woodcock, who looks at her and then turns his
      head away as if ashamed of himself)</stage> Am I awake? or is it a dream—a
      <pb n="37"/> nightmare? No! there he stands—at least, all that is left of him. Oh, Marmy!
      <stage>(sobbing loudly and burying her face in her handkerchief)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(r.)</stage> Oh, Carver! <stage>(imitating Mrs. Carver)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(indignantly)</stage> So, sir! Scarce ten days married to the sweetest, the gentlest
      of her sex, you actually have the audacity to indite a declaration of love to another woman—a
      married woman too! <stage>(suddenly bursting again into sobbing)</stage> Oh, Marmy!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, Carver! <stage>(same play)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(l.)</stage> I couldn’t have believed it! <stage>(ditto)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> No, more could I! <stage>(ditto)</stage> You’ve done it, Carver! You <emph>would</emph>
      bring me to London, and what’s the result?—that I’m a lost Woodcock. <stage>(in a tone of
      pretended anguish)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, Marmy! <stage>(sobbing very loud)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, Carver! <stage>(ditto)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> But no! you can’t be utterly depraved in so short a time!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, I am! I feel I’m rapidly settling down into an atrocious profligate, and I can’t help
      it! That’s the melancholy part of it, I can’t help it! You’ve done it, Carver, you
      <emph>would</emph> bring me to London!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, Marmy! <stage>(a fresh burst of sobbing)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, Carver! <stage>(ditto)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(suddenly)</stage> There’s only one thing to be done! go back at once to
      Stow-on-the-Wold, <stage>(Woodcock winks, aside)</stage> and there, with your dear
      Caroline——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(putting on a very excited manner)</stage> It’s too late now; if you had let me stop
      at Stow-on-the-Wold, I should have been perfectly satisfied with my “dear Caroline;” but you
      would bring me to London—you know you would, and what’s the result? that one dear Caroline
      isn’t enough for me! I must have a dozen—two dozen—three dozen “dear Carolines!” an unlimited
      quantity of “dear Carolines!!” <stage>(very wildly)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(indignantly)</stage> Silence! reprobate!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Gently, Carver! gently! I’m not going to be bullied! dash my wig if I am!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Mr. Woodcock!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> I can’t help it! You’ve done it, Carver! I
      <pb n="38"/> love!—I adore the whole sex! <emph>You’re</emph> a fine woman, Carver!—I love
      <emph>you!</emph>—Come to my arms, Carver! <stage>(making a rush open-armed at Mrs. Carver,
      who, alarmed, avoids him)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(alarmed)</stage> The man’s mad! I’m ashamed of you!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> So am I! But you would bring me to London! you know you would! <stage>(trying again to
      throw his arms round her)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Help!</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Maidservant, running, R.</stage>

    <p>Oh, Susan! <stage>(running to her)</stage></p>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, that’s Susan, is it? Lovely Susan! embrace your Woodcock! <stage>(rushes with open arms
      at Susan, who, alarmed, rushes out screaming)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(clasping her hands)</stage> And this is my work!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> Yes, you’ve done it Carver! never mind; don’t cry, old girl! <stage>(throwing his arm round
      Mrs. Carver’s neck)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Oh, Marmy, Marmy, if you’ve any love for Caroline, leave this wicked, abominable,
      detestable town this very morning by the very first train, and go back to Stow-on-the-Wold—I
      implore! I entreat you!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(after a pretended struggle with himself, then smiling benignantly)</stage> Carver,
      your tears have conquered! do with me as you will. <stage>(throws himself into her arms and
      makes a wry face over her shoulder, then looking towards l.)</stage> Swansdown! what the deuce
      can he want? <stage>(retiring to back as Swansdown enters, l.)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(as he enters)</stage> It’s all right, Woodcock—— <stage>(seeing Mrs.
      Carver)</stage> Madam—I——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Mr. Swansdown, I know all; your duel with my unhappy son-in-law——</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside)</stage> Bravo! she’s on the wrong scent. <stage>(aloud)</stage> Well, madam,
      I presume I have as much right to sympathize with the Federals as he has with the
      Confederates?</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(who has been trying to attract Swansdown’s notice by making signals)</stage> He’s
      made a mess of it! I knew he would.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Federals—Confederates! I see—a subterfuge to conceal the <emph>real</emph> cause of your
      quarrel. You may rely
      <pb n="39"/> on receiving a letter of apology—ample apology from Mr. Woodcock!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Not till he’s recovered the use of his right arm, I beg.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(behind)</stage> Eh? of course; it was the <emph>right</emph> arm! <stage>(taking
      his left arm out of the sling and inserting the right)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> The <emph>right</emph> arm, you mean the <emph>left.</emph> <stage>(Woodcock changes arms
      again)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> The right! I think I ought to know.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> The left! I suppose I can believe my eyes.</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> Right!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F5">
     <speaker>Mrs. C.</speaker>
     <p> Left!</p>
    </sp>
    

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(who has kept on changing arms rapidly)</stage> Oh, bother! there! <stage>(stuffing
      both arms into the sling)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Larkings hurriedly, at C. from L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(running to Woodcock)</stage> She’s here—Caroline! she’s heard of the duel; that you
      are wounded in the right arm—<stage>(Woodcock who has both arms in the sling, draws out the
      left)</stage> though of course I knew it was the left, <stage>(Woodcock changes arms
      again)</stage> when luckily—I don’t know how it came into my head—I told her it was not her
      husband but mine who—she’s here—don’t undeceive her; but first off with this. <stage>(dragging
      the sling violently off Woodcock’s neck)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Enter Mrs. Woodcock, hurriedly C. from L.</stage>

    <sp who="#L0945_F6">
     <speaker>Mrs. W.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(running to Woodcock)</stage> You are not wounded? it was not you then—Oh, I’m so
      happy! <stage>(here Larkings appears at c.)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(seeing him, runs to him and flings the sling over his neck)</stage>
      Hush, not a word! <stage>(taking hold of his right arm and thrusting it violently into
      the sling)</stage></p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(crying out with pain)</stage> Oh!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_F7">
     <speaker>Mrs. L.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside to him)</stage> That’s right—pretend it hurts you!
      <stage>(leading him down)</stage> Here is the real culprit; but as he is
      sufficiently punished already, I forgive him. <stage>(aside to Larkings, who is about
      to speak)</stage> Hush! You’ll have
      <pb n="40"/> to wear the sling for a week. I’ll tell you why another time!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M2">
     <speaker>Lark.</speaker>
     <p> With all my heart. <stage>(aside to Woodcock shaking his hand)</stage>
      Thanks to you, my wife suspects nothing!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M3">
     <speaker>Swans.</speaker>
     <p> <stage>(aside, to Woodcock, and shaking Woodcock’s other hand)</stage>
      Thanks to you, no one suspects mine!</p>
    </sp>

    <sp who="#L0945_M1">
     <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
     <p> And thanks to both of you, <stage>(shaking both their hands)</stage> I’m
      going back to Stow-on-the-Wold—that is, if our kind friends assure us that success has crowned
      “Woodcock’s Little Game!”</p>
    </sp>

    <stage>Curtain.</stage>
   </div>
  </body>
  <back>
   <head>Transcriber’s Note</head>

   <p>This transcription is based on a copy of the Samuel French edition, scans of which have been
    posted on the Internet Archive at:</p>

   <p><ref target="https://archive.org/details/MortonWoodcocksLittleGame">
    archive.org/details/MortonWoodcocksLittleGame</ref></p>

   <p>Because of the print quality of the Samuel French edition, an American reprint published by
    Harold Roorbach in 1889 was used as an additional resource. Scans of the copy held by the
    Library of Congress are posted at:</p>

   <p><ref target="https://archive.org/details/woodcockslittleg00mort">
    archive.org/details/woodcockslittleg00mort</ref></p>

   <p>In general, this transcription attempts to retain the formatting, punctuation and spelling of
    the source text. Variant spellings such as “bran-new” and “trowsers” have been retained as have
    some inconsistencies in spelling, such as “ball room” vs. “ball-room” and “thank’ee” vs.
    “thankee”. Some changes were made to correct for printing errors and for minor inconsistencies
    in formatting, punctuation and spelling.</p>

   <p>The following changes were made to the text:</p>

   <list>
    <item>p. 2: The upper right side of this page in the Samuel French edition was blank. Thus, the
     name of the theater and the last names of the actors were corrected or added based on the
     Roorbach edition.</item>

    <item>p. 4: there’s not the slightest doubt about it’s being all over!—Change “it’s” to
     “its”.</item>

    <item>pp. 6-7: Yes, fair lady. I entered the holy state of wedlock—Changed what appears to be a
     period to a comma in keeping with the Roorbach edition.</item>

    <item>p. 8: The gap! <emph>she</emph> is under twenty, while you   —how old shall we
     say?—Inserted “are” in the blank space after “you” based on the Roorbach edition.</item>

    <item>p. 10: I could’nt have believed it of you—Changed “could’nt” to “couldn’t”.</item>

    <item>p. 11: (taking hold of Mrs. Larking’s hand)—Changed “Larking’s” to “Larkings’s” for
     consistency.</item>

    <item>p. 13: he actually expressed his his intention of laying aside—Deleted the second
     “his”.</item>

    <item>pp. 13-14: <stage><stage><stage>(banging her hand on one of the parcels to Woodcock’s
     great alarm)</stage></stage></stage>—Changed “<emph>Woodcock’s</emph>” to “Woodcock’s” for
     consistency.</item>

    <item>p. 14: Yes; embroidered, no doubt, by some unhappy creature he had professed to me as he
     did me.—Changed “me” after “professed to” to “love” based on the Roorbach edition.</item>

    <item>p. 17: <emph>Enter</emph> Mrs Larkings <emph>in travelling dress, door</emph> r. 2
     e.—Inserted a period after “Mrs”.</item>

    <item>p. 19: (taking off Mrs. Woodcock’s cloak)—Changed “<emph>Mrs. Woodcock’s</emph>” to “Mrs.
     Woodcock’s” for consistency.</item>

    <item>p. 19: (taking hold of Mrs. Carver’s cloak behind and giving it a violent tug)—Changed
     “<emph>Mrs. Carver’s</emph>” to “Mrs. Carver’s” for consistency.</item>

    <item>p. 20: <emph>Enter</emph> Mrs. Larkings, <emph>at</emph> c., <emph>in fashionable evening
     dress.</emph>—Ladies <emph>and</emph> Gentlemen are seen promenading within—Music)—Changed the
     closing parenthesis to a period.</item>

    <item>p. 22: (to Mrs. Larkings) we’ve settled our costume, my dear!—Capitalized “we’ve”.</item>

    <item>p. 28: Wood. (still dancing after them, and aside to Mrs. Swansdown) Don’t tell him that,
     mum—As Mrs. Larkings has the previous line, changed “Mrs. Swansdown” to “Mrs. Larkings”.</item>

    <item>p. 28: Mr. L. Luckily, I’m not jealous!—Changed the character title “Mr. L.” to “Mrs. L.”
     in keeping with the Roorbach edition.</item>

    <item>p. 29: Mrs C. (r. c.) My dear friend, never indulge in a plurality of epithets—Inserted a
     period after “Mrs”.</item>

    <item>p. 31: But how <emph>is</emph> Mrs Larkings to know anything about it?—Inserted a period
     after “Mrs”.</item>

    <item>p. 33: Confound it! how she’s hurting me?—Changed the question mark to an exclamation mark
     in keeping with the Roorbach edition.</item>

    <item>p. 34: David. So he opens it, ma’am, and (to Larkings who is making violent signs to him
     to hold his tongue) What’s the matter, sir?—Inserted an em dash after “and”.</item>
   </list>
  </back>







  

 </text>
</TEI>