<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="L1183">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Irishman in London : TEI edition</title>
<author>Macready, William</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Curated by</resp>
<name>Lou Burnard</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<distributor>Privately published on the Lacy Website</distributor>

<idno type="LAE">L1183</idno></publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl type="origin" n="79.12"><author>Macready, William</author><title type="main" n="theirishmaninlondon">The Irishman in London</title><title type="sub">A Farce in one
       act</title><title type="source" n="#EN">Adapted from the “Intriguing
       Footman”</title><extent>25 pp (UM copy: 420 - 445)<measure type="pp" quantity="21"/>
  <measure type="spCount" quantity="227"/>
  <measure type="spvCount" quantity="2"/>
  <measure type="txWords" quantity="5688"/>
  <measure type="spWords" quantity="5688"/>
  <measure type="stWords" quantity="0"/>
  </extent>

      
      <title level="s"> Lacy's Acting Edition, volume 79, No. 1183</title><idno type="nic">N80491</idno></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="copytext"><ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015067453749&amp;seq=420 ">UM from
     HT</ref><ref target="local:Vol79/L1183/L1183-um.pdf"/></bibl><bibl type="surrogate"><ref target="https://www.fadedpage.com/showbook.php?pid=20121129">Faded Page transcription</ref></bibl><bibl type="surrogate" subtype="TEI"><ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/L1183.html">TEI</ref></bibl><listEvent>
      <event type="firstPerf" when="1792-04-21" source="textNic" where="Covent">
       <desc>Premiered at Theatre Royal, Covent Garden 21 April 1792</desc>
      </event>
      <event type="otherPerf">
       <desc><name>Drury Lane; Covent Garden; Haymarket</name><date notAfter="1828">20 Sept. 1830;
         1823; 18 July 1828</date></desc>
      </event>
     </listEvent></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc><textClass>
<catRef target="#sizeS"/>
<catRef target="#act1"/>
<catRef target="nic:F."/>
<keywords>
<term>FARCE</term>
</keywords>
</textClass><particDesc><listPerson>
<person xml:id="L1183_M1">
<persName type="role">Mr. Frost </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="57">Frost.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1183_M2">
<persName type="role">Mr. Colloony </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="24">Coll.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1183_M3">
<persName type="role">Captain Seymour</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="28">Seym.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1183_M4">
<persName type="role">Edward</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="49">Edward.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1183_M5">
<persName type="role">Cymon </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="7">Cymon.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1183_M6">
<persName type="role">Murtoch Delany</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="28">Murt.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1183_F7">
<persName type="role">Louisa Frost</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="4">Louisa.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1183_F8">
<persName type="role">Caroline Belmont</persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="17">Caro.</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="L1183_F9">
<persName type="role">Cubba </persName>
<persName type="spkr" n="12">Cubba.</persName>
</person>

<person xml:id="L1183_Mul">
<persName type="spkr" n="1">All.</persName>
</person>
</listPerson></particDesc></profileDesc>
<revisionDesc><change when="2025-11-02">Metadata refreshed from catalogue and Partix folder</change>
<change when="2025-09-11">@who fixed</change>
<change when="2025-09-07">Metadata updated from new catalogue</change>
<change when="2025-06-16">TEI Header generated by makeHdr script</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><pb n="1"/>

<front>
<titlePage><titlePart type="main">THE IRISHMAN IN LONDON.</titlePart><titlePart type="sub">A FARCE, IN ONE ACT</titlePart><titlePart type="source">Adapted from the “Intriguing Footman.”</titlePart><byline>By <docAuthor>William Macready</docAuthor>, Author of <title>The Bank
Note; or, A lesson for ladies</title>,etc., etc.</byline><titlePart type="desc">With an illustration and remarks by D. G—.</titlePart><docImprint>THOMAS HAILES LACY, 89, STRAND, LONDON.</docImprint></titlePage>

<div type="liminal">
<head>REMARKS. </head>
<head>The Irishman in London.</head>
<p> It is amusing to contemplate the various singularities of men.<note place="foot">A physician once observed that he could tell of what country a man
was, by his <hi>complaint</hi>. If it laid in the <hi>head</hi>, he was a
<hi>Scotchman</hi>—if in the <hi>heart</hi>, he was an <hi>Irishman</hi>—if in
the <hi>stomach</hi>, he was an <hi>Englishman</hi></note> The Cockney, to whom
the <hi>V</hi> and the <hi>W</hi> are a source of as many perplexities as were
the <hi>two Dromios</hi> to the good people of Ephesus, has his patent for
cutting King George’s English most divertingly. The <hi>Welshman</hi> enjoys his
leek, his pedigree, and his toasted cheese. The <hi>Irishman</hi>, his brogue
and his bulls. There is no fun about a <hi>Scotchman</hi> ; unless (in the
absence of a post) when he is excited to dance to his national <hi>fiddle</hi>:
<hi>his</hi> peculiarities, though not pleasing, are nevertheless
profitable—for, like the mouse in the fable, he generally becomes too proud and
too pursy to creep in at the cranny from whence his leanness originally crept
out. These characteristics have not escaped the observation of dramatic writers;
and abundant mirth has been derived from their exhibition. The eccentricities of
<hi>Pat</hi>
<note place="foot">A gentleman, stepping into the Belfast mail, was asked by an
Irish waiter for something to drink, for the trouble of calling him. “To drink!”
exclaimed the gentleman—“ why, I gave <hi>Rooney</hi> a shilling.” “Och! bat,
plase your honour, I called <hi>him</hi> !” One Irishwoman, having fallen out
with another, was complaining to to a third how sadly she had been abused by an
<hi>Irishwoman</hi>. “And are you not an Irishwoman yourself?” exclaimed the
latter. “Och! and to be sure I am; bat I don’t come from <hi>them hot parts</hi>
that she does !” </note> have not been behindhand in contributing their full
share to the gayety of nations ; and, while we have laughed heartily at his
careless humour, his queer-sounding compound epithets, his antipodean
association of <hi>thunder</hi> and <hi>turf</hi>, and such-like comical
amalgamations of elementary and vegetable matter, some kind-hearted
<hi>trait</hi>, some dash of genuine feeling, has suddenly come across us, and
made us long to take him by the hand and claim acquaintance, <pb n="4"/> even
though we should receive the peculiar token with which St. Patrick is wont to
greet his particular friends— “From his sprig of shilelah and shamrock so green
!” </p>
<p> The farce of The Irishman in London is borrowed from “The Intriguing
Footman, or the Humours of Harry Humbug,” a piece attributed to James Whiteley,
formerly manager of the Nottingham and other provincial theatres, and acted at
Sheffield in 1791. It was originally produced at Covent Garden, at Mr.
Johnstone’s benefit; that admirable comedian taking the part of Murtoch Delany.
It has little plot, but is very ingeniously made up of incident and character.
It exhibits the various stratagems practised by Edward, an intriguing footman
(the Harry Humbug of the <hi>original</hi> farce), to deliver a letter from his
master, Captain Seymour, to Caroline, the daughter of one Mr. Frost, a
pertinacious old gentleman, who had taken a voyage from the West Indies to
London for the sole purpose of avoiding the importunities of the said captain,
and of marrying the young lady to Mr. Colloony, a simple native of the Emerald
Isle. The latter personage is accompanied, on his matrimonial trip, by his Irish
servant, Murtoch Delany. This is enlivened by the introduction of Cubba, a
faithful African, who falls in love with Murtoch, and in the simplicity of her
heart acquaints him with his good fortune; and of Cymon, who is almost as full
of quaint comparisons as Dean Swift’s celebrated song of <hi>Similes</hi>. There
is nothing comical about Mr. Frost, but his passion for Louisa; the young lady’s
return of his affection is, however, equally comical. The dialogue is pleasantly
written ; and, what with Edward’s rattling rhodomontade, Cymon’s pat and
provoking similes, and Murtoch Delany’s national whim, there is no want of
amusement in this farce. One of its chief attractions was the original
<hi>Planxty</hi>, which Johnstone sung in a manner that made every heart, Irish
and English, dance to its melody. </p>
<p> A first-rate actor of Irish characters is indispensable on a London stage.
We are not old enough to have seen Moody perform; but we remember him, many
years ago, a hale, respectable-looking old gentleman, taking his walks in
company with the veteran Boaden, the well- known performer of Robin Hood. Rock
(with many declensions) was of the Moody school—rigidly true to the brogue, but
occasionally heavy and listless. Webb <pb n="5"/> sings an Irish air with
admirable spirit; but he cannot act. The late Mr. Connor <hi>acted</hi> with
humour; but then (like the three unmusical rogues in good King Arthur's
days)<note place="foot"><l>«In good King Arthur’s days,</l><l> Oh, he was a very
good king !</l><l> Three sons of w * * * * were turn’d out of doors</l><l>
Because they <hi>couldn't sing !”</hi></l>
</note> he <hi>couldn't sing</hi>. Johnstone possessed both qualifications in
high perfection: his <hi>voice</hi> was full, clear, and melodious—his
<hi>acting</hi> rich, sparkling, and original. He was equally fine in genteel
comedy and in the broadest farce——in the finished gentleman and the veriest
Teague. His <hi>Major O'Flaherty</hi> was gallant and gay; his <hi>Foigard</hi>
<hi>(Kilkenny, by my soul!)</hi> was arch and pointed. In <hi>Looney</hi>, he
looked as if he had been born in a field, with a hay-fork in his hand. And how
he stood up for the honour of ould Ireland and her <hi>“manufactrys,”</hi> and
reiterated <hi>“bad travelling !”</hi> and <hi>“Oh! murther, murther !”</hi>
those who have seen his <hi>Murtoch Delany</hi> can amply testify. His pathos
was deep—his humour quick and sly; he had Pat’s hereditary fun and frisk—his
national naiveté and dancing hilarity. He could assume a-look of brisk
intelligence and of ineffable stupidity ; there was a peculiar archness in his
smile, and he had an <hi>Irish front</hi>. To follow <hi>such</hi> an actor is
no easy task; to fall short of him cannot be considered a failure. Mr. Power has
many of the qualifications that distinguished his predecessor: his brogue is
rich, his air smart and vivacious—the jokes come trippingly from his tongue,
lighted up with a leer whimsically illustrative of potatoes and whiskey. His
attempts have hitherto been confined to low comedy. His <hi>Irish Tutor</hi> is
good—so are his <hi>Loony</hi>, <hi>Murtoch</hi>, and <hi>Dennis
Bulgruddery</hi>. Mr. Power has a clear stage to himself; he has no competitor
in Irish characters. To him we apply Walsh's advice to <hi>Pope</hi>,—“study
<hi>correctness</hi>.” We have seen many a natural genius run to waste, for want
of attending to this necessary precaution. However excellent <hi>nature</hi> is
of herself, she may still derive improvement from <hi>art</hi>. </p>
<signed>D.—G.</signed>


</div>







<performance>
<head>The Irishman in London. </head>
<p>[The print source gives details of four distinct performances : <list>
<item xml:id="perf1">
<name>Theatre Royal Covent Garden</name><date>Saturday, April 21, 1793</date>
("Original")</item>
<item xml:id="perf2"><name>Drury Lane</name><date>September 20,
1830</date></item>
<item xml:id="perf3"><name>Covent Garden</name><date>1823</date></item>
<item xml:id="perf4"><name>Haymarket</name><date>July 18 1828</date></item>
</list> ]</p>
</performance>

<castList>

<castItem>
<role gender="M">Mr. Frost </role>
<actor>|Mr. Wilson |Mr. Cherry |Mr. Blanchard |Mr. Williams</actor>
</castItem>
<castItem>
<role gender="M">Mr. Colloony </role>
<actor>|Mr. Macready |Mr. Bartley |Mr. Baker |Mr. Brindal</actor>
</castItem>
<castItem>
<role gender="M">Captain Seymour</role>
<actor>|Mr. Harley |Mr. Holland |Mr. Mason |Mr.Fredericks</actor>
</castItem>
<castItem>
<role gender="M">Edward</role>
<actor>|Mr. Fawcett |Mr.Bannister,Jun. |Mr. Farley |Mr. W. West</actor>
</castItem>
<castItem>
<role gender="M">Cymon </role>
<actor>|Mr. Blanchard |Mr. Collins |Mr. Meadows |Mr. Ross</actor>
</castItem>
<castItem>
<role gender="M">Murtoch Delany</role>
<actor> |Mr. Johnstone |Mr. Johnston |Mr. Connor |Mr. Power</actor>
</castItem>
<castItem>
<role gender="F">Louisa Frost</role>
<actor>|Mrs. Mattocks |Miss Mellon |Miss Love |Mr. Waylett</actor>
</castItem>
<castItem>
<role gender="F">Caroline Belmont</role>
<actor>|Miss Chapman |Mrs.Southey |Miss Henry |Miss Holland</actor>
</castItem>
<castItem>
<role gender="F">Cubba </role>
<actor>|Mrs. Fawcett |Miss Tryer |Mrs. Pearce |Mr. O. Carr</actor>
</castItem>
</castList>

<div type="costume">
<head>COSTUMES.</head>
<list>
<item><label>Seymour.—</label>An undress military suit. </item>
<item>
<label>Frost.—</label>Blue body coat, yellow waistcoat, nankeen trousers and
gaiters, grey hair.</item>
<item>
<label>Colloony.—</label>Cut-off green body coat, striped waistcoat, breeches,
and striped boots. </item>
<item><label>Edward.—</label>1st Dress: Undress livery. 2nd. Dress Eccentric
suit. red Dress: Same as first. </item>
<item><label>Cymon.—</label>Old-fashioned livery. </item>
<item><label>Louisa and Caroline </label>Modern young ladies dresses. </item>
<item><label>Cubba.— </label>Striped dress, red ’kerchief round her head, black
face and hands. </item>
</list>
<p>Time: in performance—Forty minutes.</p>
</div>
</front>
<body>
<pb n="7"/>
<head>IRISHMAN IN LONDON.</head>
<div type="scene">
<stage>SCENE FIRST.—A Street. </stage>
<stage>Enter Seymour, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Welcome, once more, my native country! yet am I almost insensible to the
pleasure, from being at so great a distance from my beloved Caroline.—Oh
Jamaica, happy place! which contains all that is dear to me on earth. Her cruel
father must have intercepted the letters I wrote from America, or she would have
contrived to let her Seymour know, she still retained the same tender affection
for him——Good heaven! is it possible? Ha! reason contradicts my sense of seeing,
and tells my eyes they are deceived—'Tis he! <stage>Enter Mr. Frost, L.</stage>
Dear sir, my joy at seeing the parent of my Caroline so unexpectedly——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(❌'s R.)</stage> This assurance is past bearing! I left the West Indies
to live in quiet; and here, one of the first things that presents itself, is the
person of all others I wish to avoid.—But my daughter is in my power, and shall
marry the man I have selected for her directly—I'll take care of her
happiness.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Great care, indeed, to sacrifice her against her inclinations to some
wretch!—But who is he? Let me know where——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> No matter who he is, or what he is; or where he lives, or where I live: you
know but little of my family at present, and I am determined you shall know
less. <stage>(Exit R.</stage></p>
</sp>
<pb n="8"/>
<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Astonishing! 'Tis some comfort, however, to know she is in England,</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Edward, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(L)</stage>Oh, sir, such news! Miss Caroline is in town, has been here
these two months—I found it out by the greatest chance.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> How, how?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Why, sir, I met Cymon, pretended to him that I had left you in America, and
he told me they were all come; and that there was great doings preparing for an
elegant young fellow from Ireland, who was to marry Miss Caroline
immediately.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> By heavens! no such circumstance ever shall take place; and how to prevent
it? Edward, you, in general, have a happy invention, and I am certain, if you
exert it, you might gain me an interview, or, at all events, some further
intelligence.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p><stage>(sings)</stage> "The perquisite softens us into consent."—Ah! my
invention and genius are at present employed, contriving how I shall avoid the
civilities of my tailor, shoemaker, washerwoman, and a few other friends, whom I
left rather abruptly—Now they'll renew their former mode of paying their
respects to me; and though I never return one visit, they'll still continue
their kind enquiries. If I had but a few pounds to satisfy those gentry, my mind
would be easy, my person free; and, thus disencumbered, I should most certainly
devise means to deliver from my master a letter to his dear Caroline, before she
consults her downy pillow this night.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> My honest fellow, make good your words, and twenty pounds shall be your
reward.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Twenty pounds! twenty! She has—or I mean she shall have the letter. Write
it, sir, write it—Let me have it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> While I go to write, be very particular in observing any gentleman that may
be hereabouts; and if he should seem at a loss, direct him to me, or come
directly for me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Oh Lord! Oh sir, yonder I see my tailor—I told you these people would impede
my march, if I was not prepared for them. Dear me, how shall I avoid him?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Avoid him. Who is he? What's his name?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> His name is a—the—oh damn it, 'tis very odd I never can remember the name of
a man I owe money <pb n="9"/>to—that is, when I am poor; for then I am always
dejected at the sight of them. But when I have money, and can pay them, I face
them as bold as a lion. How do you do? says I, how do you do?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> With those principles, 'tis a pity you should ever want. Here, take this,
and observe my directions while I write the letter. <stage>(Exit R.</stage>
</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> I will, sir.—What's here? ten poundss! Mr Snip!—Oh, he's off some other way,
and I'll be hanged if I call him back—Let me see; ten pounds! My master is a
noble fellow—I wish he was a General, then his pocket might keep pace with his
heart. At present, the one is always a day's march behind the other. But how
shall I contrive to deliver my master's letter? No matter I'll trust to chance,
and convince him, with all his despair ——</p>
<l>That English wit, howe'er despised by some,</l>
<l> Like English valour, still shall overcome.</l>
<stage>(Exit R.</stage>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Colloony, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Och ! London! London! dear London, as Ercher says, had I millions, I'd spend
it all there ! it's the mert for enjoyment—the leedies so bewitching, the
squeers so elegant, the theatres so enchanting, and, in short, every thing so
captivating, that I wish, from my heart, I may never leave it. Where is this
servant of mine? I decleer there is no bearing his inattention. I desired him to
meet me here at this time precisely: 'pon my honour I must no longer neglect
visiting Mr Frost and the leedies.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murtoch</speaker>
<stage>singing without, L.</stage>
<l>We Irishmen both high and low, we are both neat and handy,</l>
<l>The ladies every where we go, allows we are the dandy.</l>
<l>To be sure we are, and indeed we are -</l>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Murtoch, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Indeed I'll break your thick head if you don't hold your tongue, and till
me, did you find the pleece, and bring me the money?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<stage>L.</stage>
<p> Well, well; I will sir—the—a—och, sir, I wish we were at home again; this is
the divil of a place.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> I say, sirrah, have you found the banker's?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> No, in troth, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> No! pray thin, where's the chick I gave you?</p>
</sp>
<pb n="10"/>
<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Where! why sure, sir, you didn't bid me kape it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> I bid you give it to the banker, and bring me the money — where is it?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Why, I'll tell you, sir—The truth is, I did not give him the chick—Nor the
divil a farthing he gave me—for I didn't see him at all, at all.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Was there ever such a provoking scoundrel? Tell me this moment, where, and
what you have been about ?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Och! faith! and I have been tumbled about bravely; for the people here walk
the streets as if they couldn't see—for one parson gave me a drive on one side,
and when I only turned to ax him what he done that for, another gave me a
shoulder with his elbow on the t'other side—So, upon my sowl, sir, I was going
backward every step I went forward.—But at last, I saw a crowd staring up; so
myself axed dacently what was the matter—Stop, and luck up, says the man, and
you'll see: myself did so, and there was two black pictures of men, with
shillelys in their fists, thumping at one another, because the clock was
striking. When it had done, they had done, and I was done; for I found they
picked my pocket of the chick that I held fast in my hand, and every thing I had
in the world; and the hat off my head into the bargain!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> The rascal has been gaping about, instead of minding his business.—I will
most certainly send you home, Dill.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Och! worrow do, sir, send me home; but mind, I won't go by say, I got enough
of that; if once I got to sweet Balinrobe, the devil burn me if ever I wish to
see foreign parts again, or any but our netral parts at home—to be sure, it is
the sweetest little place in the world, Ireland is.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Why, you scoundrel, do you want to bring a mob about us? hold your tongue
about Ireland, I say—Go wait at home for me, and don't be exposing. <stage>(Exit
R.</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Exposing! to talk of Ireland! Faith, sir, begging your pardon, I think a man
does not desarve to belong to any country, that's ashamed to own it.<stage>(Exit
R.</stage></p>
</sp>

</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>SCENE SECOND.—A Chamber. Table and two chairs, doors R. 1 R. and L. 1
R.</head>
<stage>Enter Frost, Caroline, and Cubba, R. </stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Come, cheer up, Liny—Your lover certainly will be here to-day—The knot shall
be tied to-morrow.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Dear sir, don't impose upon your Caroline the <pb n="11"/> misery of
refusing, when nature powerfully informs her, 'tis her duty to obey you—Indeed,
indeed, I never can love this Mr Colloony.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> How do you know? You have never seen him—Why, he is young, handsome,
rich—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Mention not his qualifications, sir, for my heart is engaged.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Yes, and my word is engaged—The young fellow coming all the way from Ireland
on purpose—A fine settlement made on you—Is not that better than starving with
your Seymour?</p>
</sp>


<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> I don't know what your resolution may be, but mine is unalterably fixed—Dear
sir, I have only to entreat you will give up the idea of plunging me in
wretchedness—Remember that you're a father, sir, and that indulgence should ever
unite with that name.<stage>(exit R.</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> Ah! poor missa, she be so good—Still she cry great deal—Bochro do wrong,
laugh and be happy—nobody ought to be merry when missee frette.<stage>(exit
R.</stage></p>
</sp>


<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Ay, follow her, you—you—whenever I am vext, or in trouble, that angel of
darkness is sure to come in my way—I tell her every hour that she is in a
blessed land of liberty, that she's her own mistress, free as air, in hopes I
shall get rid of her; but she won't stir—no, she sticks like birdlime. <stage>(a
single knock, L.)</stage>Then, that cursed Cymon comes with his similes.</p>
</sp>


<stage>Enter Cymon, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p>Well, sir, what do you want? Who was that knocked at the door?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M5">
<speaker>Cymon.</speaker>
<p> A man, sir: he gave me this as nimble as a fencing-master, and stepped away
like a dancing-master.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh curse your similes! Let me see, from Mr Colloony—That's delightful!
[<hi>Reads.</hi>] "Sir, my anxiety to take you by the hand, can only be equalled
by my passionate desire to see your amiable daughter, and with the speedy
assistance of Hymen, shall glory in the liberty of being her slave. The earliest
moment possible I hope to make acceptable to Mr Frost the devoirs of his truly
devoted and most assured humble servant, William Patrick O'Brien Colloony." Oh!
he's a fine ardent lover. They shall be married to-morrow morning—D'ye hear,
Cymon? take care every thing is ready for the reception of your new master. How
does my purchase come on, the coach horses?</p>
</sp>
<pb n="12"/>
<sp who="#L1183_M5">
<speaker>Cymon.</speaker>
<p> Troth, sir, bad enough—They are only fit for the crows. One of them, the
sorrel horse, puts me woundily in mind of a lawyer.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> A lawyer! How now, how can that be?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M5">
<speaker>Cymon.</speaker>
<p> Why, sir, he is well paid for every journey he goes; and the other is
downright game, for he'd sooner die than run. <stage>(exit L.</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> That fellow's as bad to me as the gout—I can find no cure for him.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Re-enter Cymon, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M5">
<speaker>Cymon.</speaker>
<p> Sir, sir—here's a grand gentleman dressed like a peacock, and talks like a
magpie.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Was there ever such an affronting scoundrel! show him in. <stage>(exit
Cymon, L.)</stage> It must be Mr Colloony—I say, Cubba, send your mistress to me
immediately—Oh dear, this is lucky.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Caroline, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Did you send for me, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Yes, yes; here's Mr Colloony—it can be nobody else. <stage>Enter Edward, L.
dressed in a tawdry manner.</stage> Sir, I rejoice to see you—how do you? so is
my daughter, indeed, sir, though she says nothing— <stage>(to her)</stage> Why
the devil don't you speak? </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Sir, I—I—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(aside)</stage> I have got into the house at all events, and must trust
to impudence for the rest ! </p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Sir, she's excessively fond of you; but she naturally expects you to speak
first.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Certainly, my dear sir—Fond of me! Oh, ho! then I must be in love—Here goes!
<stage>(aside)</stage> Oh, Madam, you're such a beauty, so full of charms, so
all over engaging, such a hand, such symmetry, such eyes, such lips, such
smiles, such frowns, such love, such——Oh! I'm quite out of breath.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Well, this is a comical fellow! How he has gallopped over the poor girl! I
don't think he has much of the brogue—But, sir, I say, my—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Then, her foot, sir—do but look at her foot, sir—A foot proportioned to the
body; the body suited to the face, the face suited to the soul, the soul to the
heart, the heart to the mind, the mind to—as my friend Hamlet says, in his
advice to the actors, "the action to the word;" and then she has so much—Oh
dear, oh dear, I can go <pb n="13"/> no further—Now to try to give her the
letter. <stage>(aside, ❌'s L.)</stage>]</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> How his tongue does run! I am afraid Liny will never have him, he's such a
fool. But, sir, you confound her with your compliments.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Compliments - you wrong me, sir; I can't flatter—I truly love, I adore, I
live for you—I—I can't find the letter <stage>(aside, ❌'s C.)</stage>]—Oh,
madam! say that you'll marry me, or I shall curse my stars, go mad, and die!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Die ! you're the strangest fish I ever met with. Sir, I'll speak to my
daughter, and if—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Oh! that <hi>if</hi> has driven me to despair, for— <stage>(aside)</stage> I
have lost the letter—My peace of mind is— Hang me, but it's gone!
<stage>(aside)</stage>] It has undone my quiet, ruined me, blasted all my
hopes—Farewell, board-wages, laced liveries, all joy, peace, happiness! Oh!,
farewell!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Sir, I'll withdraw a little to order some refreshment, and— <stage>(❌'s
R.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Dear sir, don't leave me with this wretch, this fool!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Don't abuse him, Liny; 'tis your charms have made him a little flighty—I
wish they had cut his wings before they had let him away, for he's the wildest
Irishman I ever saw. <stage>(exit R.</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Sir, I say—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Stop, madam, for heaven's sake!—I am Edward—my master, Captain Seymour, is
in town.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Ha! can it be! My Seymour in England!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, ma'am, and has sent you— <stage>(searching for letter.</stage></p>
</sp>


<stage>Enter Frost, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> I don't like leaving my child with this wild Irishman. Eh! egad they seem
very quiet, I'll listen.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Dear, dear, I have certainly left it in my other clothes—But the
circumstance is this, ma'am— my master, this morning, saw your father; and, on
finding you were in town, wrote a letter, which I undertook to deliver to you.
<stage>(Frost comes between them - Caroline sees him and runs off R. Edward
continues telling her of the letter.)</stage> But I have unfortunately mislaid
it—I can assure you he loves you as much as ever; and if you would but write a
few lines, to say that you love him, he'll run away with you, in spite of that
cruel curmudgeon your father, and <stage> (turning about, meets Mr. Frost face
to face.)</stage> Oh! murder!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Thieves! Cymon! thieves! knock him down!</p>
</sp>
<pb n="14"/>
<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, sir.—<stage>(knocks Cymon down as he enters L., and exits
L.)</stage>.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh! Murder! thieves!—Cymon, where are you?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M5">
<speaker>Cymon.</speaker>
<p> Here I be, sir, as flat as a flounder.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> My poor fellow!—Go shut the door, and be sure to bolt, lock, and chain
it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M5">
<speaker>Cymon.</speaker>
<p> Yes, sir—I'll see every thing as safe as a guinea in a miser's purse.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh! curse your similes!—I must go myself, and see every thing secure.</p>
<stage>(exeunt L.</stage>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Caroline and Louisa, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Thank heaven! I know my Seymour is in England—I have heard enough to
convince me he still loves me; and constancy's the only proof of true
affection—I hope he may devise some means to free me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F7">
<speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
<p> If he did not, I am sure he should not have me. </p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Cymon, in haste, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M5">
<speaker>Cymon.</speaker>
<p> Ma'am, he's come; Mr Colloony. Oh dear! I am as much out of breath as a
trumpeter.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>(without, L. </stage> Walk in—walk in, sir.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Frost with Colloony, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p>I am overjoyed to see you, walk in, sir, walk in. Ladies, ladies, this is Mr
Colloony: Sir, my daughter and her friend Miss Belmont. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Ladies, your most obedient. This warm and kind reception is truly
flattering, and impresses me strongly with the idea of my future happiness.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh! I'm sure you'll be very happy——There's a husband for you, Liny! Is he to
be compared to your captain?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> No, indeed, sir, I don't think he is.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> That's a good girl—Well, sir—You shall be married this morning—Oh dear! and
how is my old friend, your worthy father, and all your family? What sort of a
passage had you? I suppose you were very much fatigued after your journey? Will
you have some refreshment? Oh! I'm so happy! Come tell me all.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> All, upon my honour, he asks all, and will hear <pb n="15"/> nothing—Sir, I
left my father and all the family very well, as his letters will acquaint you—I
say, Dill, bring up that parcel, Dill, I say, Dill.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Murtoch with portmanteau, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Here, sir, here! Arrah, Maister Pat, don't be calling me Dill, myself can't
bear it; it's making so little of one. My name, ladies, saving your prisence, is
Murtoch Delany; and though Maister Pat's my maister, I don't know who made him
my godmother.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Get away, sirrah, Sir, you will find by these letter the liberality of my
father, he gives me his whole estate while he lives; and makes me heir to all
the rest when he dies.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Oh, the divil burn the blade of grass, horse, cow, servant, or any other
fixture upon the estate, even to the value of a sucking-pig, but will be all his
own.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh! I'm too happy. You shall be united directly.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> I should think myself unworthy, indeed, if words could express how much I
feel indebted to your goodness. Before I had the felicity of seeing the lady I
could think of nothing else; and such an effect had the description of her on my
mind, I decleer I could not sleep a wink for draming of her.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> But you did not tell me what sort of a passage you had.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Why, sir, they said it was a good one, but I was sick of it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Sick! Arrah, ladies, we were kilt, myself was quite dead, I was all—a—I
called to the captain to stop; "stop and put me out", says I. "Nonsince, man,"
says he, "if I put you out, it will be in the water, and then you'll go to Davy
Jones.@ "Oh, thank you," says I, "it's time enough for me to go and live with
that jintleman when I am dead in earnest.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F7">
<speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
<p> Then you are not fond of the sea, Mr Colloony?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> No, indeed, ma'am; if they'd give me the finest estate upon earth, I could
not live in it with any enjoyment on board of ship.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> But come, are not the towns through which you came worthy of
observation?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Certainly, sir; your manufactories are so astonishingly greet, they prove at
once the wonderful industry and wealth of your nation.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="16"/>
<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Ax your pardon, ladies, the devil a manufactory I saw equal to our own. Och!
if you could only look at the oyster-beds in Poolbeg, the Foundling or the
Lying-in-Hospital at Dublin, they are the right sort of manufactories.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_Mul">
<speaker>All.</speaker>
<p> Ha, ha, ha!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Faith you may laugh, but I am sure there can't be better manufactries in the
world than those that provides comfortable lodgings, and every other sort of
bread and meat, for poor craters that can't provide for themselves.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Hold your preeting, sirrah; leedies, I hope you'll excuse him.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> But, Mr Colloony, do now favour us with your opinion of our country, and an
account of your journey.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> 'Twas a very pleasant journey. Travelling here is much better than in
Ireland.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<stage>(aside)</stage>
<p> Oh! murther, murther! Maister Pat, don't be running down our country; myself
can't bear it; you know the roads are a thousand times better in Ireland.
Ladies, the miles there are three times as long as they are here; and then the
divil a half mile can you go, but there's a beautiful wooden milestone; I'm sure
from the time we left the hill of Howth, till we got to that spalpeen place they
call Holy-head, the divil a bit of land I saw but what was all covered over with
water. Pretty travelling indeed!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Begone, you scoundrel - lave the room, I say.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Sir!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Lave the room, I say, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Lave the room, you say, sir? Oh, mighty well; there's more o' the yarn. Did
you think I was going to take it wid me? Bad travelling in Ireland! I'll say
nothing before the company, but if ever I forgive this ! Ladies, your most
engaging conversation— <stage>(goes muttering)</stage>] I never can forgive
this. <stage>(exit L.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Your father, in this letter, seems particularly anxious that the marriage
ceremony should be performed as soon as possible; now I'm desirous it should be
so too; what do you say, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> What do I say, sir? why I say, ask the lady; I deem it the happiest moment
of my life! He must be covetous indeed, that could form a wish beyond what is
here to be found. <stage>(bows to Louisa)</stage>
</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Liny, thank him—Isn't he an elegant, polite, <pb n="17"/> well-bred man?
An't you surprised and rejoiced?—The licence is ready—I'll go to the parson; it
must be done before twelve; we have but an hour and a half.</p>
</sp>
<stage>(Exeunt Frost and Colloony, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_F7">
<speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
<p> Caroline, how could you treat Mr Colloony in such a manner? you scarce
looked at him. Are not you on the very brink of matrimony? To disappoint him
now, what would the world say?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Yet disappointed he shall be, and I am in no dread of what people may
say—The truly virtuous mind makes itself judge, and, satisfied within, smiles at
that common enemy, the world.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Frost, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Come, girls, prepare; Louisa, you shall go too—you shall be a bridesmaid.
Hadn't you rather be a bride?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F7">
<speaker>Louisa.</speaker>
<p> Why, sir, I can't say I should have any objection.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh, charming! you make me young again—Egad, I begin to think—Oh dear—go and
prepare, for Mr Colloony will return directly. <stage>(exit Louisa, R.)</stage>
Oh, the lovely, sweet——</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Edward, singing.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Well, sir, what do you want?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Sir, I—a—beg pardon, sir, I believe I am come to the wrong house——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Then pray, sir, go to the right house.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, sir. <stage>(exit, singing, L.</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Do, sir. Cymon, who is that fellow? He had but an ill look, methought. Shut
the door there. Now, Liny my love, be a good girl. I'm so pleased, that I shall
give you an additional hundred pounds, for you to—— <stage>Enter Edward,
L.</stage> He here again! I thought you were gone to the right house!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> This is it, sir. Pray did not a gentleman of the name of Colloony—I got that
from the Irish servant <stage>(aside)</stage>]—go out of this house a little
time ago?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Yes, sir; but if you want him, he'll be back directly.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> No, sir, he will not, a sad accident has happened to him.</p>
</sp>
<pb n="18"/>
<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Mercy on me! I hope not.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Truth indeed, sir—I'll tell you the particulars. At the corner of the next
street a gentleman attacked him. "Sir", says he, "you are a villain!", then drew
his sword, and pushed violently at him. Thus, sir, thus, madam—thus
<stage>(pushes the letter over Frost's shoulder, which she does not
notice.)</stage> Oh, the blind creature!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Dear me, how unlucky! I wish he was returned, I hope he is not hurt.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> He is, sir; yes, he is—It's rather an odd place.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Where? where? Is it in a mortal part?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> It's in the back, sir—in the back, ma'am, in the back—Damme but she'll die a
maid. <stage>(he turns his back to her, and the letter is fastened to it; she
takes no notice of it)</stage>] And so Captain Seymour, ma'am——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh! that cursed captain!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Captain! What was it my——?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> No, no, it was not.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, yes, ma'am, it was—a——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p>
<stage>Stopping his mouth.</stage> No, no, she must not know he is so near her.
I don't think, at least, I hope it was not Mr Colloony.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, it was, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Why, how was the gentleman dressed?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Why, sir, he was dressed in a pair of boots, sir, and a hat, sir, with a
band round the hat, sir. <stage>fixes the letter in his hat-band and pushes it
towards her - she takes it.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> And how is Mr Colloony? Tell me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Why, sir, as soon as Captain Seymour saw the blood trickle from his
antagonist, he jumped to him, took him in his arms, thus, and carried him to Dr
Julep's this way.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Blessed contrivance! 'tis from my Henry; but how to send an answer? If I go
to my room, Edward may be gone before I can write—What shall I do? Invention
assist me. <stage>(writes with her pencil on the Letter)</stage>]</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> But what did the doctor think him in danger?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Why, sir, we hope not—He probed the wound, and after muttering a great many
gallipot phrases, that none but the brethren of the pill-boxes understand, he
pronounced him out of danger, and ordered him to be put to bed, his stomach to
be fomented with a—a—bason of soup, and—</p>
</sp>
<pb n="19"/>
<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> If this does but succeed—<stage>(aside).</stage> Sir, sir, this fellow's an
impostor—I'll let my honoured father know your villainy—Sir, while you were
listening to his story, he forced this letter into my hand; but to show how I
regard the writer, there, take his impertinent scrawl back again. <stage>throws
it on the ground.</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> The art of man won't prevent her being an old maid.—Ma'am——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh, you damn'd dog! Let me see it, my dear—We'll throw it into the fire, and
this fellow out of the window.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> No, sir, I cannot wish him a greater punishment than to return his letter
just in that manner.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Here's usage for my poor master—but, Ma'am, is there nothing for—or by way
of—a—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh, you want something, do you? I'll pay you <stage>(beats Edward off,
L.</stage> —there's wood upon wood. Come along, Liny, and if ever I catch you in
this house again, I'll leave you no more brains than a fiddler. <stage>(exeunt
nFrost and Caroline, R.</stage></p>
</sp>

<stage>Murtoch heard singing, L.</stage>


<l>Och, whiskey, it's you that's my darling,</l>
<l>It's you that keeps me on my feet,</l>
<l>And often you cause me to stagger,</l>
<l>Wheniver we chance for to mate.</l>


<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Maister Pat, I'm come to desire that you will—a—Oh, he's gone! It's well for
him—I was just going to discharge him—he vexes me so when he speaks
congrumshously about the sod—I won't, for I can't bear it—I have made Cymon
blind drunk in love wid Ireland—I was telling him all about it, and he supped up
my intelligence like a jintleman; to be sure he mixt it a little, for he emptied
the best part of two bottles of port, that Miss gave him to make much of me, and
there he lies stretched on the floor, snoring as quiet as a stone in a wall. I'm
quite up—I'm almost corned, faith, with looking at him drinking it. I wish I had
something to do—that somebody would affront me, or a fine young lady fall in
love with me—or any divarting accident of that nater.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Cubba, R.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> You want to speak a wi' me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Och, honey, what's this? Sure the crater <pb n="20"/> wou'dn't be in love
with me—She is, she is! And I am sorry for her—but she can't help it—Honey, it
won't do—Now don't think of it, avourneen.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> Me no understand you.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> She does not understand me—What a misfortune it is to want larning—if your
schoolmistress had been a jintleman, she'd tache you the manners to say you did,
whether or not. I'll larn you to spake good English when my master marries your
young lady.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> Me hope me not live till den, me sure missee break her heart, and me rader
die den see it.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Oh faith, if you die, you won't see it to be sure—May be you'll hear of it,
and that will be the same thing—Miss a—troth I forget your name.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> Me name Cubba.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Pooh, pooh, be asy, Miss Cubbaugh!—That's being too agreeable— and your
father's a king!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> Iss, a king.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Oh! it's king of the morice-dancers she manes; ay, ay, that fellow had a
black face—I saw him yesterday.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> No, no; him live at de Gold Coast.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Where? Where all the silver comes from, eh?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> At de Gold-Coast—Now nobody here, you shut your eye, me tell you something
dat make my heart open in two. But you look so good—you not be angry with
Cubba.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Oh! the divil an angry I'll be—I never was angry with one of the fair sex in
my life—There, honey, my eyes are shut—go on—now the divil a word I can
hear.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> Me love a you dearly—but me no want you love me—dat be very wrong—Your face
white, me poor negro—me only tell you make me easy, den me pray for you be
happy.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> I knew it—I knew it—Black, brown, green, or yellow, I bother them all—Oh,
Murtoch, you murtherer of beauty—What are you about—but the milk of compassion
rises within me for poor Cubbaugh—I wish she was not sooty. Who knows, may be
the journey will bleach her. Troth, it's a shame your mistress never found out
that fellow, that advertises to whiten ladies' hands and faces, he'd make you
fair as a daisy. Och! if you had even a bit of the violent soap, honey!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> No matter, my color, if me do right—Good black face be happier den bad
white. <stage>(Exit Cubba, R.</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Troth and I believe she may be the daughter of <pb n="21"/> a king, for she
has the mind of a prince—If her face was but as white as her heart, she'd be a
wife for a Pope. I'll take her wid me to ould Ireland, and sing her every night
the praise of the most beautiful flower of the earth,. and the finest gim of the
say.</p>
</sp>



<stage>SONG.</stage>



<l>If you'd travel the wide world all over, </l>
<l>And sail across quite round the globe, </l>
<l>You must set out on horseback from Dover, </l>
<l>And sail unto sweet Balinrobe.</l>
<l> 'Tis there you'll see Ireland so famous, </l>
<l>That was built before Adam was breech'd, </l>
<l>Who lived in the reign of King Shamus, </l>
<l>Ere he was at Boyne over-reach'd.</l>

<stage>CHORUS.</stage>
<l>With my whack fal de ral, &amp;c. </l>
<l> O, the Land of Shillelah for me.</l>

<l>There you'll see Ulster, and Munster, and Leinster, </l>
<l>Connaught, and sweet Kilkenny likewise, </l>
<l>That city where first, as a spinster, </l>
<l>I open'd these pair of black eyes; </l>
<l>In this town there is fire without smoking, </l>
<l>For a penny you'd buy fifty eggs, </l>
<l>And then there's such wit without joking, </l>
<l>And rabbits without any legs.</l>
<l>With my whack, &amp;c.</l>

<l>There you'll see my ancestors glorious,</l>
<l> The sons of the brave O's and Mac's, </l>
<l>Who died whene'er they were victorious, </l>
<l>And after that ne'er turn'd their backs. </l>
<l>Our heads are stout and full of valour, </l>
<l>Our hearts are wise and full of brains, </l>
<l>In love we ne'er blush nor change colour, </l>
<l>And the ladies reward all our pains.</l>
<l>With my whack, &amp;c.</l>

<l>Saint Patrick is still our protector, </l>
<l>He made us an island of saints, Drove out snakes and toads like an Hector, </l>
<l>And ne'er shut his eyes to complaints. </l>
<l>Then if you would live and be frisky, </l>
<pb n="22"/>
<l>And never die when you're in bed, </l>
<l>Come to Ireland and tipple the whiskey, </l>
<l>And drink tin years after you're dead.</l>
<l>With my whack fal de ral, &amp;c. </l>
<l>The Land of Shillelah for me!</l>
<stage>Exit R.</stage>
</div>
<div type="scene">
<head>SCENE THIRD.—A Street.</head>
<stage> Enter Seymour and Edward, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> There's your letter again; that's all the answer I could get.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> My letter! 'Sdeath, you rascal, is this your boasted cleverness? Did you see
my Caroline?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, sir; and after many efforts, at last I gave the letter into her own
hand, and her father in the room. But she returned it just as you see, and is
positively to be married this morning.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Unlucky scoundrel! 'tis to you I owe all my misfortunes; by listening to
your wretched paltry schemes, I have lost all that was dear to me on earth; but
you shall injure me no more—all the punishment I can at present inflict is, to
divest you of my property, and discard you—so strip, sir, and never let me see
your face again.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Sir!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Call a coach, sir, throw the clothes into it, and begone—Strip, I say.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> What, sir, in the street? I shall catch cold, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Do as I desire you, rascal, or——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, sir, yes—coach—co—Lord, sir, you are joking!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> I am serious, sirrah—Do as I order you;—no words—but—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, sir, yes—Here's gratitude! who the devil would be a footman now, I
wonder.—There, sir, there's your coat, all the rest is my own.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Quit my sight—and here, sir, take this letter as your reward.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Oh! sir, virtue is its own reward—I look for none. Eh! what's this?
<stage>(sees the writing on letter)</stage> Ha! kind fortune, you never deserted
me.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> What is the fellow loitering about? I wish he'd ask for his coat again.
<stage>(aside.)</stage>]</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Sir, I have one favour to beg before I go; will you be so kind, as just to
look at the outside of that letter?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Look at —— <stage>(taking letter)</stage>] Ha! what's here?
<stage>(reads)</stage> "This is the only method I have to acquaint my dear
Seymour <pb n="23"/>, that I am still the same; my heart is wholly his."
Transport! <stage>(kisses the letter)</stage>] Charming!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Ahem! ahem!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> My dear Edward, what shall I say to you?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Nothing, sir; you've said enough—'Tis to me you owe all your
misfortunes.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Nay, nay, put on your coat.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> No, no, sir; get another servant. I'll never——</p>
<stage>(❌'s R.)</stage>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Nay, for Heaven's sake, Edward—I own I have been rash.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Rash! to make me strip here in the open street, and expose me to all the
world——<stage>(walking about from L. to R.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<stage>(following him)</stage>
<p>But, Edward, do put on your coat.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Not I, sir, I despise a coat—when there's no money in the pockets.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<stage>(gives money)</stage>
<p>Now, my dear fellow, have done.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Lord, sir, I have done; money and a good place have stopped greater men's
mouths than mine.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Take your coat, and put it on.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, sir—A little of your assistance, if you please.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> My assistance!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Yes, sir, I'll not put it on without it. <stage>(Seymour helps him on with
his coat</stage>. I have often assisted you on a similar occasion.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Well, come, only think of my anxiety.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Who would not be a footman now? It's well you're a gentleman, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Why?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> You make a very good master, but you'd be a precious bad servant.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Cubba, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> Massa, bring a my dear good Missee to make her marry great man. She send a
me to look for you. Here a shee come. Oh, dear, Missa!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Why, there's no man but her father.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F9">
<speaker>Cubba.</speaker>
<p> Na; chum-chum meet her at the church.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M3">
<speaker>Seym.</speaker>
<p> Never! let the consequence——</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M4">
<speaker>Edward.</speaker>
<p> Here they come, sir. Let's retire a little—Come, Cubba, and mind what I say.
<stage>(they retire)</stage></p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Frost and Ladies, one on each side, L.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Dear me, the time is getting rapidly over, and I <pb n="24"/>dread that
fellow's having any more schemes to bamboozle and cheat me; but I think if he
does now, he must be cunning. Come on, Liny.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Why, sir, how very ridiculous you'll make yourself and me in this
business—You see, plainly, Mr Colloony won't be here. Pray, sir, put it off till
to-morrow.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> No, no; I am certain he will be here—Egad, yonder he comes—Louisa, your turn
shall be next—tomorrow, we'll—oh dear!</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Colloony and Murtoch.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> I hope, sir, I have'n't kept you weeting. Madam, I take <stage>addresses
himself to Louisa. Edward takes Cubba's hand, slips Caroline's gently away, and
puts Cubba's in its place, under Frost's arm, Seymour and Carolione run off
R.U.E, followed bt Edward.)</stage></p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Mr Colloony, don't be ashamed to be seen with your wife before marriage—here
she—Oh the devil!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Arrah, is it my own little daffy-down-dilly you want, Maister Pat, to bring
home? Oh thunder! arrah! be asy!</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Oh! thunder indeed! What hocus pocus is this?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Sir, I take your daughter as the greetest gift this world can be—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Take her! where will you find her?</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Here, sir—This lady—</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> That lady! No, no, no; she is no daughter of mine—She is engaged—She is—Oh,
Liny! Why don't you pursue and bring back your wife that is to be? This poor
girl has no fortune.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M2">
<speaker>Coll.</speaker>
<p> Why then it is very lucky I have enough for us both; and if this lady will
make it more by sharing it with me, it's all at her service.</p>
</sp>

<stage>Enter Seymour, Caroline, and Edward, R.U.E.</stage>

<sp who="#L1183_F8">
<speaker>Caro.</speaker>
<p> Dear sir, be reconciled; and our future conduct shall prove, that to make
you happy is all we wish.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M1">
<speaker>Frost.</speaker>
<p> Ah, confound you all! I'll never—yet stop; she is yours, sir, with a good
fortune, and the blessing of an affectionate father.</p>
</sp>

<sp who="#L1183_M6">
<speaker>Murt.</speaker>
<p> Faith, you're right, old gentleman—But all our great joy and happiness, will
be nothing but downright grief and misery, if the hands of all our friends do
not loudly whisper in our ears, they have no objection to the "IRISHMAN IN
LONDON."</p>
</sp>

<stage>R. Edw. Car. Sey. Frost. Coll. Lou. Murt. Cubba. L.</stage>
<stage>CURTAIN</stage>
</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>